. >> GOOD AFTERNOON AND WELCOME
TO THE DECEMBER 2ND, 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS .
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
YES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN
PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR
SARDAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT SUPERVISOR WANG WANG
PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK AND WELCOME SUPERVISOR HUANG
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA
ALONI WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE ROMITA WE
HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE ROMITA ALONI COMMUNITY AND BY
AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME AND RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA WHICH IS A REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY
PARTICULARLY KALEENA MENDOZA THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? YES, MR. PRESIDENT.
FIRST THE BOARD RECEIVED A COMMUNICATION FROM THE
HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE DATED DECEMBER 1ST, 2025,
ANNOUNCING HIS APPOINTMENT OF ALAN WONG TO FILL THE VACANCY
IN DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WANG HAS TAKEN THE OATH OF
OFFICE IS COVERED UNDER THE BONDING CREDENTIALS AND IS NOW
A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
WELCOME SUPERVISOR WONG. THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
WELCOMES YOUR ATTENDANCE HERE IN PERSON AT THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHANGE PER CHAMBER ROOM TWO 52ND FLOOR OF CITY
HALL. WHEN YOU CAN'T BE HERE THE
PROCEEDINGS ARE AIRING LIVE ON S.F. GOV TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR
LIVE STREAMING AT W W W DOT S.F. COVID TV DAWG.
SUBMIT PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING EITHER BY SENDING AN
EMAIL TO BOSS AT S.F. GOP TALK OR VIA U.S. POSTAL SERVICE TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN
FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102. TO MAKE A REASONABLE
ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS
WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE
PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS
DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING (415) 554-5184.
THAT CONCLUDES MY COMMUNICATION.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. >> THE APPROVAL OF THE OCTOBER
28TH 2025 REGULAR BOARD MEETING MINUTES AND THE OCTOBER 20TH
SPECIAL MEETING MINUTES AT THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION
COMMITTEE MEETING WHICH CONSTITUTED A QUORUM OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO
APPROVE THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN
SECONDED BY WALTON MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON THE MINUTES SUPERVISOR FILTER FILTER I SUPERVISOR MY
VOTE MAHMUD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I AMENDMENT I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WANG HUANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE
APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO OUR CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS ONE THROUGH 18 ITEMS ONE
THROUGH 18 ARE ON CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED
ROUTINE. IF A MEMBER OBJECTS ANY ITEM
MAY BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY PLEASE CALL THE ROLL
ON ITEMS ONE THROUGH 18 SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE
PASSED ON FIRST READING AND FINALLY PASSED AND THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
REGULAR AGENDA NEW BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 19.
>> ITEM NUMBER 19 IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE
APPROXIMATELY 4.5 MILLION OF STATE COST REIMBURSEMENT
REVENUE TO THE DEPARTMENT OF ELECTIONS TO SUPPORT COSTS
ASSOCIATED WITH THE STATEWIDE NOVEMBER 2025 SPECIAL ELECTION.
THIS ORDINANCE REQUIRES A TWO THIRDS APPROVAL VOTE OF ALL
MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS PURSUANT TO CHARTER
SECTION 9.113 SEE I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 20.
ITEM NUMBER 20 IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AMENDMENT NUMBER ONE
TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY, THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
HEALTH AND CATHOLIC CHARITIES TO PROVIDE HIV HEALTH SERVICES,
RENTAL SUBSIDIES, SERVICES TO EXTEND THE TERM BY FIVE YEARS
FROM JUNE 30TH 2026 FOR A TOTAL TERM OF JULY 1ST 2021 THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2031 AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY 7.3
MILLION FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT NOT FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 13.4 MILLION. >> AGAIN WE CAN DO THIS ONE
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 20 ONE. >> ITEM NUMBER 21 IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE RETIRED THE REVISED TERMS
AND CONDITIONS AND AUTHORIZE THE GENERAL MANAGER OF THE SFP
U.S. AND OR CITIES DIRECTOR OF PROPERTY TO EXECUTE A PURCHASE
AND SALE AGREEMENT AND EASEMENT DEEDS WITH AN OAKLAND UNIFIED
SCHOOL DISTRICT FOR THE ACQUISITION OF AN APPROXIMATELY
4000 SQUARE FOOT EASEMENT FOR AN UNDERGROUND WATER PIPELINE
AND ASSOCIATE ASSOCIATED APPURTENANCES AND APPROXIMATELY
35,000 SQUARE FOOT TEMPORARY CONSTRUCTION EASEMENT ACROSS A
PORTION OF ALAMEDA COUNTY KNOWN AS 11 601 MAIN STREET FOR
35,000 PLUS AN ADMINISTRATIVE FEE OF 5000 AND UP TO 10,000
AND CLOSING COSTS FOR A TOTAL AMOUNT OF 50,000.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
22. >> ITEM NUMBER 22 IS A
RESOLUTION TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE FIRE DEPARTMENT
TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND APPROXIMATELY $637,000 GRANT
FROM THE FEDERAL EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AGENCY THROUGH THE
CALIFORNIA OFFICE OF EMERGENCY SERVICES FOR THE FIRE
DEPARTMENT'S NEW TRAINING FACILITY FOR THE PERFORMANCE
PERIOD OF AUGUST 1ST, 2024 THROUGH APRIL 20TH, 2027
AND WAIVING INDIRECT COSTS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL M23.
ITEM NUMBER 23 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE SETTLEMENT OF THE
LAWSUIT FILED BY TOMMY O. JOHNSON BY AND THROUGH HIS
ATTORNEY. IN FACT, REVEREND DAWSON WHITE
AND JOHN DOE BY AND THROUGH HIS CONSERVATOR THOMAS O'CONNOR ON
BEHALF OF THEMSELVES AND ALL OTHER SIMILARLY SITUATED
AGAINST THE CITY FOR APPROXIMATELY 5.8 MILLION.
THE LAWSUIT INVOLVES CLAIMS OF ELDER DEPENDENT ADULT ABUSE,
INVASION OF PRIVACY, NEGLIGENCE AND VIOLATION OF PATIENTS
RIGHTS BROUGHT BY OVER 700 FORMER AND CURRENT RESIDENTS OF
LAGUNA HONDA HOSPITAL. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 FOUR.
>> ITEM NUMBER 24 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE A SIX
MONTH WAIVER OF THE CITY'S BEHEST ID PAYMENTS ORDINANCE
FOR THE MAYOR, MEMBERS OF THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC
AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT TO SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM TWO
NONPROFIT ARTS PRIVATE ORGANIZATIONS GRANT MAKERS,
FOUNDATIONS AND OTHER PERSONS AND ENTITIES FOR THE PURPOSE OF
SUPPORTING THE CONTINUED ECONOMIC REVITALIZATION OF SAN
FRANCISCO SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN.
COLLEAGUES TO BE CLEAR THIS IS AN EXTENSION OF A SIX MONTH
WAIVER AT THE TIME WHEN THIS ITEM WAS HEARD IN THE GO
COMMITTEE OR IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE WERE UNABLE TO PROVIDE
ADEQUATE INFORMATION ABOUT WHO IS SOLICITED UNDER THIS WAIVER
IN A STATEMENT AS TO WHY THEY MIGHT BE INTERESTED PARTIES
IN CONTRAST AGENCY WAS ABLE TO DELIVER THESE ANSWERS ABOUT
THEIR BEST PAYMENTS WAIVER QUITE EASILY IN COMMITTEE
DESPITE THE FACT THAT SOME OF THIS INFORMATION WAS READILY
AVAILABLE VIA THE MAYOR'S PUBLICLY ACCESSIBLE FORM 8O3
FILINGS CONWAY FAMILY FOUNDATION LEE OR SUSAN RIPPLE
LABS SHORENSTEIN REALTY LLC ARE JUST A HANDFUL OF THOSE THAT
WERE SOLICITED IN AN EFFORT OF GOOD FAITH.
>> I SENT THESE QUESTIONS TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AN ENTIRE
WEEK IN ADVANCE. I ASKED THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO
SEND SOMEONE TO COMMITTEE WHO CAN SPEAK TO THESE QUESTIONS
INSTEAD THEY SENT SOMEONE FROM D WHO WITH ALL DUE RESPECT
AND TO NO FAULT OF HER OWN HAD NO ANSWERS.
THE MAYOR'S OFFICE SENT A MEMO TO US TODAY THAT CONTAINS ZERO
ANSWERS TO MY QUESTIONS OF HOW THE MAYOR HAS SAID PARTIES
MIGHT BE INTERESTED PARTIES AND YET HERE WE ARE ABOUT TO
APPROVE THIS WAIVER WITHOUT ANY ANSWERS TO MY QUESTIONS AS
CHAIR OF THE GOVERNMENT AUDIT OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE, I'M
COMMITTED TO ENSURING THAT CITY OFFICIALS ADHERE TO OUR HAZARD
PAYMENT ORDINANCE TO PREVENT ANY POTENTIAL INDICATIONS OF
IMPROPRIETY. >> THESE WAIVERS STATE THAT THE
WAIVERS SERVES TO FURTHER THE PUBLIC INTEREST AND DO NOT
CREATE AN APPEARANCE OF IMPROPRIETY.
>> WE HAVE A DUTY ON THE BOARD AND A RESPONSIBILITY TO THE
RESIDENTS OF SAN FRANCISCO TO ENSURE THAT WE ACTUALLY STAND
BEHIND THAT STATEMENT GIVEN THE LACK OF INFORMATION PROVIDED BY
THE MAYOR'S OFFICE, I CONTINUE TO HAVE REAL CONCERNS ABOUT THE
CITY BEING ABLE TO CONDUCT MEANINGFUL OVERSIGHT ON
POTENTIAL CONFLICTS OF INTEREST FOR THIS SPECIFIC WAIVER.
FOR THAT REASON I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST THIS ITEM.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL WELL OVER
THE PAST YEAR WE'VE MADE MAJOR STRIDES TOWARDS REVITALIZING
DOWNTOWN. DOWNTOWN IS YOU KNOW THE HEART
OF THE TAX REVENUE THAT WE GENERATE IN THIS CITY.
IT IS ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL NOT ONLY FOR THE SUCCESS OF
BUSINESSES AND WORKERS HERE BUT ALSO FOR THE FUNDS THAT THAT
HELP GET MORE POLICE OFFICERS FOR EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD, MORE
FIREFIGHTERS FOR EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD, MORE STREET
CLEANING FOR EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD.
WE NEED TO BE USING EVERY TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL TO HELP THIS
ECONOMIC REVITALIZATION AND RECOVERY.
AND SO I'M EXCITED TO CO-SPONSOR THIS ITEM TO KEEP
EXPANDING THE NUMBER OF OPTIONS WE HAVE A BILL WHILE THE LEVERS
WE HAVE TO PULL ON TO DRIVE THE ECONOMIC REVITALIZATION SAN
FRANCISCO IS GOING TO COME BACK.
WE ARE COMING BACK BUT IT'S GOING TO TAKE ALL OF US WORKING
TOGETHER. IT'S GOING TO TAKE EVERY TOOL
IN OUR TOOLBOX AND I'M VERY EXCITED TO PUSH THIS FORWARD
AND TO HAVE THE MAYOR INTRODUCING THIS.
YOU KNOW, WHEN WE LOOK AT TOURISM HOTEL ROOMS FROM
CONVENTIONS ARE UP MORE THAN 60% BUT THEY'RE STILL DOWN FROM
PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS. AIR TOURISM UP 7.5% FROM LAST
YEAR BUT STILL DOWN FROM PRE-PANDEMIC LEVELS.
THIS IS GOING TO TAKE A LOT OF WORK.
I THINK THIS IS ONE TOOL. THIS IS NOT EVERYTHING BUT I'M
EXCITED TO BE A CO-SPONSOR ON THIS AND I HOPE WE CAN ALL HAVE
YOUR I CAN HAVE YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS MEASURE TODAY.
>> SUPERVISOR JEN THANK YOU PRESENT AMENDMENT AND I WANT TO
THANK CHAIR OUR GAIL CHAIR FIELDER FOR HER WORK IN HER
QUESTIONING ON THIS I THINK ABSOLUTELY IT'S NOT JUST FOR
THIS BE HAS WAIVER BUT ALL BE HAS WAIVER BECAUSE PAYMENT
WAIVER SHOULD REALLY COME UNDER SCRUTINY AND IT'S NOT JUST FOR
THE MAYOR BUT ALL CITY DEPARTMENTS.
WE HAVE LEARNED OUR LESSONS FROM PREVIOUS YEARS THAT YOU
KNOW IF WE DON'T RANK IN THAT PAY TO PLAY CULTURE IS
PROBLEMATIC FOR GOOD GOVERNMENT.
AND SO I JUST WANT TO EXPRESS MY THANKS TO CHAIR FIELDER FOR
HER WORK IN QUESTIONING I ALSO BEING IN THIS SPACE I HAVE
APPROVE THE BE HAS WAIVER BE HAS PAYMENT WAIVER PARTICULARLY
FROM DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF HOUSING I KNOW
IT'S OUR NEXT AGENDA ITEM IN IS NOT CALL AT THIS MOMENT BUT I
WANT TO DO SPEAK ON WAIVER ACROSS IN GENERAL THAT YOU KNOW
I DO LOOK FORWARD TO SEEING MORE INFORMATION BOTH TO
SOLICIT AT PARTIES AS WELL AS THE DOLLAR AMOUNT AND REALLY
WHAT THE RESULTS AND THEN COME TO IT AND THE REASONING BEING
WHY WE NEED TO CONTINUE TO RENEW THESE BE HAS PAYMENT
WAIVER. >> I WILL BE IN SUPPORT OF OF
THIS ONE AS WELL AS THE NEXT ONE FOR ONLY THE REASON BEING
IS THAT I THINK THAT THE MEMO THAT WHILE WE RECEIVE I WOULD
CONSIDER LATE BUT STILL TRANSPARENCY INFORMATION ALLOW
US TO UNDERSTAND WHO ARE THE POTENTIAL INTERESTED PARTIES
BUT I AM NOT IN COMMITMENT THAT I WILL CONTINUE TO SUPPORT NEXT
ROUND OF THE BEHEST PAYMENT WAIVERS AND THE REASON BEING IS
I THINK AT SOME POINT WE NEED TO GO BACK I THINK COMMISSION
TO UNDERSTAND THE BEST PART IS WHEN IT COMES TO BEHEST PAYMENT
WAIVER AND I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO GET A BIT MORE UNDERSTANDING
FROM BOTH THE ETHICS COMMISSION AS WELL AS POTENTIALLY OUR
COMPTROLLER OR WHOEVER THAT WE CAN ACTUALLY GET OR MAYBE OUR
BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST TO START EVALUATING BEST
PRACTICE FOR CITY GOVERNMENTS TO IDENTIFY RESOURCES REVENUES
AND HOW THAT IMPACT OF GOOD GOVERNMENT.
I THINK THOSE THINGS I WOULD LIKE TO LEARN MORE ABOUT
AND UNDERSTAND AND HAVING GUIDANCE AND DATA TELL US HOW
MUCH MONEY THAT WE ACTUALLY BRING IN, WHO IS IT THAT WE'RE
GETTING IT FROM AND WHAT KIND OF RELATIONSHIP BOTH NOT JUST
THE MAYOR BUT ALSO ALL ACROSS BECAUSE ARE GRANTING THESE BE
HAS PAYMENT WAIVERS BEYOND THE MAYOR AND AND AND
ADMINISTRATION AND WE CITY ATTORNEY DISTRICT ATTORNEY
ASSESSOR RECORDER WE HAVE GRANTED A WHOLE LIST OF
ELECTEDS ACROSS THE CITY FOR THEM TO ACTUALLY ENGAGE IN THIS
PART. THERE'S SO WHILE TODAY I'M
SUPPORTIVE I WANT DEFINITELY ANSWERS AND I AGAIN WANT TO
THANK CHAIR CHAIR FELDER FOR YOUR WORK AND I LOOK FORWARD TO
SEEING MORE THOSE DIALOG HAPPENING AT OUR GOVERNMENT
AUDIT OVERSIGHTS COMMITTEE. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER
THANK YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN I WILL BE IN SUPPORT OF THIS
TODAY AS I WAS AT OUR GIO COMMITTEE I DON'T THINK THIS
NEEDS TO BE A CHOICE BETWEEN DOWNTOWN OR NEIGHBORHOODS AND I
THINK THEY DEPEND ON ONE ANOTHER AND IN FACT WE HAVE
COUNTLESS WAIVERS THAT SPEAK TO THE WORK WE'RE DOING
IN DIFFERENT COMMUNITIES AND IN DIFFERENT NEIGHBORHOODS AND I
CERTAINLY HEAR SUPERVISOR FIELDER'S FRUSTRATION WITH SOME
OF THE QUESTIONS THAT WERE NOT ANSWERED.
AND I YOU KNOW, I THINK THAT THOSE PARTICULAR QUESTIONS
AND THAT OVERSIGHT SHOULD BE PUT INTO FUTURE BLESSED WAIVERS
IF WE'RE LOOKING FOR THAT OVERSIGHT, LET'S PUT THAT
IN THE IN THE LEGISLATION ITSELF SO THAT WE HAVE THAT AS
A YOU KNOW, KIND OF AS A BLANKET STATEMENT OF WHAT WE'RE
LOOKING FOR IN TERMS OF THE OVERSIGHT.
BUT FOR THIS TODAY I'LL BE SUPPORTING THIS I THINK IT
CONTRIBUTES TO THE WORK THAT WE'RE DOING FOR ALL OF SAN
FRANCISCO, PARTICULARLY FOR DOWNTOWN.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 24
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MAN MY AMENDMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR NO MELGAR NO
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES AND THREE
NOSE WITH SUPERVISOR FIELDER MELGAR IN WALTON VOTING NO THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 25.
ITEM NUMBER 25 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF
HOMELESSNESS IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR,
CHIEF DEPUTIES, DEPUTY DIRECTORS AND PROGRAM DIRECTORS
TO LISTEN TO SOLICIT DONATIONS FROM VARIOUS PRIVATE ENTITIES
AND ORGANIZATIONS TO SUPPORT THE EXPANSION OF TEMPORARY
SHELTER AND OTHER HOMELESS SERVICES TO SUPPORT PEOPLE
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS NOTWITHSTANDING THE BE HOSTED
PAYMENT ORDINANCE SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT,
MADAM AND COLLEAGUES. >> AS WE ALL KNOW THE MAYOR HAS
A HORRIBLE TRACK RECORD WITH HIS KING MAKING POLICIES TO
OVERSATURATE DISTRICT TEN AND OTHER DISTRICTS WITH ALL
ISSUES AROUND HOMELESSNESS. SO THERE'S NO WAY I WOULD
SUPPORT HIM SOLICITING RESOURCES TO CONTINUE TO
STEAMROLL MY DISTRICT. SO I DEFINITELY WILL NOT BE
SUPPORTING THIS KING MAKING DECISION SURPRISE, SURPRISE.
>> FIELDING CHAIR FIELDING THANKS PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
IN CONTRAST TO THE PREVIOUS WAIVER THAT WE JUST APPROVED, I
JUST SAGE WAS ABLE TO VERY EASILY ANSWER MY QUESTIONS
ABOUT THE PARTIES ELICITED UNDER THIS WAIVER AND HOW THEY
MIGHT BE POTENTIALLY INTERESTED AND I HAD NO CONCERNS ABOUT
THEM SO I WILL BE SUPPORTING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEM 25 SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO SUPERVISOR WANG WANG
I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THEIR ATTORNEYS AND ONE NO WITH
SUPERVISOR WALTON VOTING NO THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 20 SIX ITEM NUMBER 26 IS A RESOLUTION
TO APPROVE AN AGREEMENT WITH THE NONPROFIT OWNERS
ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADMINISTRATION AND MANAGEMENT
OF THE PROPERTY BASED BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT DISTRICT KNOWN AS A
DOGPATCH IN NORTHWEST POTRERO HILL GREEN BENEFIT DISTRICT FOR
A PERIOD COMMENCING JANUARY 1ST, 2026 THROUGH JANUARY
THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST, 2014. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM
26 SUPERVISOR FILTER FILTER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR AMENDMENT I AMENDMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR HUANG HUANG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 27 ITEM NUMBER 27 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE POLICE
CODE TO INCREASE THE FINE FOR MISDEMEANOR CONVICTIONS FOR
SIDESHOW OFFENSES FROM A MAXIMUM OF $500 TO A MAXIMUM OF
$1,000. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM AND I AM GOING TO SUPPORT THIS ITEM.
I THINK WE HAVE TO DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO KEEP OUR
COMMUNITY SAFE AND THESE SIDESHOWS ARE VERY DANGEROUS.
BUT I JUST WANT TO CAUTION THE FACT THAT I'M SEEING A LOT OF
POLICIES THAT ARE PROVIDING ATTACKS ON PEOPLE OF COLOR
AND PROVIDING ATTACKS ON THE MOST VULNERABLE.
THIS IS MOST SOMETHING DEFINITELY SOMETHING THAT WOULD
DISPROPORTIONATELY AFFECT PEOPLE OF COLOR.
BUT SAFETY OF COURSE COMES FIRST.
BUT WE HAVE TO BE CAREFUL ABOUT THE POLICIES THAT WE PUT
IN PLACE AND THINK ABOUT THE UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES.
SO I HAVE TO MAKE SURE THAT I STATE THAT ON RECORD.
I THINK THOUGH WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 28.
>> ITEM NUMBER 28 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PUBLIC
WORKS CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE ENFORCEMENT OF VENDING PERMIT
REQUIREMENTS THROUGH WARNINGS INFRACTIONS, MISDEMEANORS
AND FINES UP TO $1,000 FOR VENDING CERTAIN TYPES OF
MERCHANDISE THAT ARE CARMEN COMMON TARGETS OF RETAIL THEFT
ON CITY PROPERTY WITHOUT A PERMIT AND AMENDING THE PORT
CODE TO CONFORM THOSE AMENDMENTS.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN, I'D LIKE
TO EXPRESS MY APPRECIATION FOR THE WORK UNDERTAKEN ON THIS
LEGISLATION IN COLLABORATION WITH THE MISSION STREET VENDORS
ASSOCIATION. THE ASSOCIATION HAS BEEN
ADVOCATING FOR THIS MEASURE SINCE ITS INCEPTION.
STREET VENDORS ARE A VITAL COMPONENT OF THE MISSION SMALL
BUSINESS COMMUNITY AND VIBRANCY AND SO I'M CASTING MY VOTE
TODAY IN SUPPORT OF THEM. >> I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 20
NINE. >> ITEM NUMBER 29 IS A
RESOLUTION TO URGE THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT TO
DEVELOP AND IMPLEMENT A COMPREHENSIVE OF ENFORCEMENT
AND INTERVENTION PLAN TO ADDRESS DRUG USE OR SUSPECTED
DRUG ACTIVITY ESPECIALLY WITHIN 250FT OF PARKS, PLAYGROUNDS,
SCHOOLS AND YOUTH CENTERS. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER I JUST
WANTED TO THANKS ADVISOR CHERYL AND MAHMOOD FOR TAKING THE
AMENDMENTS TO THIS RESOLUTION AND FOR INCORPORATING A
RESPONSE FOCUSED ON LAW ENFORCEMENT AS WELL AS A WHOLE
OF GOVERNMENT APPROACH THAT INCLUDES DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT, DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO
REFER AND CONNECT INDIVIDUALS TO SERVICES LIKE DETOX CRISIS
STABILIZATION AND TREATMENT. AND FOR THAT REASON I'LL BE
VOTING YES TODAY AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM SAME HOUSE,
SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 30 ITEM NUMBER 30 IS A
RESOLUTION TO DETERMINE THAT THE ISSUANCE OF A TYPE 69
SPECIAL ON SALE BEER AND WINE THEATER LIQUOR LICENSE TO THE
ROXY THEATER DOING TO DO BUSINESS AS ROXY THEATER
LOCATED AT 3117 16TH STREET WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC
CONVENIENCE OR NECESSITY OF THE CITY AND REQUEST THAT THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE CONTROL
IMPOSE CONDITIONS ON THE ISSUANCE OF THE LICENSE.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS
31 THROUGH 33 TOGETHER. >> ITEM 31 IS A MOTION TO
APPOINT JEFFREY JONATHAN MORRIS AND NICHOLAS GOLDMAN TO THE
ASSESSMENT APPEALS BOARD. NUMBER ONE TERMS ENDING
SEPTEMBER 4TH 2028. ITEM NUMBER 332 IS A MOTION TO
REAPPOINT JOHN LEE MERVYN CONLIN AND SUSAN ELIZABETH
MILLER TO THE ASSESSMENT APPEALS BOARD.
NUMBER TWO TERMS ENDING SEPTEMBER 4TH, 2028 AND ITEM 23
IS A MOTION TO APPOINT FRANCO CIRELLI JAMES REYNOLDS
AND CHRISTINE NELSON TO THE ASSESSMENT APPEALS BOARD NUMBER
THREE. TERMS ENDING SEPTEMBER 4TH,
2028. WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTIONS ARE
APPROVED. >> NOW MADAM CLERK I AM
CONCERNED THAT IF WE GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS AT 227 WE
WILL SIGNIFICANTLY DELAY OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDERS.
ANY REASON WE CAN'T GO TO A ROLL CALL RIGHT NOW AND THEN
COME BACK? ANYBODY HAVE ANY THAT'S AN OKAY
THING TO DO, RIGHT? >> LET'S GET A ROLL CALL FIRST
UP ON ROLL CALL TODAY IS SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M THRILLED
TO INTRODUCE A RESOLUTION AFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO'S
COMMITMENT TO ADVANCING EQUITABLE BUILDING
DECARBONIZATION EFFORTS THAT CENTER ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE.
THIS RESOLUTION FURTHER URGES THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO CLIMATE ACTION PLAN TO ENSURE THAT SAN FRANCISCO
REMAINS A CLEAN CITY THAT PROTECTS ITS MOST AT RISK
MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES FROM THE EFFECTS OF GREENHOUSE GAS
EMISSIONS. >> I HOPE THAT IN PASSING THIS
RESOLUTION WE ARE EXPRESSING A COMMITMENT TO SUPPORTING CITY
AND COMMUNITY PARTNERSHIPS WITH ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE
ORGANIZATIONS TO SCALE EQUITABLE BUILDING
DECARBONIZATION PROJECTS IN NEIGHBORHOODS THROUGHOUT SAN
FRANCISCO AND IN PARTICULAR CALLING OUT DEFINED ZONES ON
THE ENVIRONMENTAL JUSTICE COMMUNITY MAP WHO ARE THE MOST
VULNERABLE TO THE IMPACTS OF FOSSIL FUEL EMISSIONS.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU .
SUPERVISOR FILTER SUPERVISOR MAHMUD.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MANS WHEN I HAVE IT
IN MEMORIAM TODAY COLLEAGUES I ASK THAT WE ADJOURN ADJOURN OUR
MEETING IN MEMORY OF WHAT'S ON US SAP WHO PASSED AWAY
IN STOCKTON, CALIFORNIA ON NOVEMBER 5TH WITH HANA WAS BORN
IN BATTAMBANG, CAMBODIA ON JANUARY 25TH, 1970.
THE YOUNGEST OF EIGHT SIBLINGS. FOLLOWING THE RISE OF THE KHMER
ROUGE AND THE BEGINNING OF THE CAMBODIAN GENOCIDE, SHE AND HER
FAMILY FLED TO A REFUGEE CAMP IN THAILAND.
THEY LATER MIGRATED TO THE PHILIPPINES BEFORE FINDING
REFUGE IN SAN FRANCISCO WITH HANA ATTENDED AN ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL HERE BEFORE HER FAMILY FOUND A PERMANENT HOME
IN STOCKTON. EDUCATION WAS A PRIORITY FOR
HER FAMILY. HER FATHER OFTEN TOLD HIS
CHILDREN AND LATER GRANDCHILDREN THAT EDUCATION IS
THE ONE THING IN THIS WORLD THAT CANNOT BE TAKEN FROM YOU.
WITH HANA TOOK THE SAME TO HEART AND PURSUED A CAREER AS
AN EDUCATOR. SHE EARNED HER ASSOCIATE'S
DEGREE IN EDUCATION BEFORE BECOMING A TEACHER'S ASSISTANT
AT MANILA SILVA ELEMENTARY SCHOOL.
FOR THE NEXT TWO DECADES SHE PROVIDED ONE ON ONE SUPPORT TO
STUDENTS WITH SPECIAL NEEDS. IN HER FREE TIME SHE READ BOOKS
ON HOW TO CARE FOR STUDENTS WITH DISABILITIES AND EVEN
LEARNED SPANISH. >> SHE SPENT EXTRA TIME
STUDYING HER STUDENTS SCIENCE AND HISTORY MATERIALS TO BETTER
HELP THEM MASTER THEIR STUDIES OUTSIDE OF WORK.
SHE LOVED TO TRAVEL. SHE'D RECENTLY VISITED SEVERAL
STATES INCLUDING ALASKA AND NEW YORK BEFORE TAKING HER FAMILY
ACROSS THE BORDER TO CANADA. SHE LOVED TO HIKE AND TOOK ANY
OPPORTUNITY TO WALK WHENEVER AND WHEREVER SHE COULD.
>> SHE LOVED TO COOK. NO FAMILY PARTY WAS COMPLETE
WITHOUT ONE OF HER SIGNATURE CAMBODIAN DESSERTS SERVED
IN PYREX BAKEWARE. WHETHER SHE BROUGHT FRIED
BANANAS, COCONUT PANDAN PUDDING OR WHATEVER EXPERIMENTAL DISH
THAT SHE MIGHT MAKE FOR THE FIRST TIME USING WHATEVER WAS
AVAILABLE AT THE CAMBODIAN MARKET SHE MADE SURE THAT
EVERYONE AND EVERYONE AROUND HER WAS WELL FED.
>> WITH HONOR SUFFERED A MAJOR HEART ATTACK AND WAS
HOSPITALIZED THE WEEK BEFORE SHE DIED.
SHE WAS SO OPTIMISTIC ABOUT HER RECOVERY THAT SHE ASKED HER
DAUGHTER TO HELP HER PLAN A TRIP TO SWITZERLAND FOR THE
COMING YEAR. SADLY SHE SUFFERED ANOTHER
HEART ATTACK A WEEK LATER AND THIS ONE WAS FATAL.
SHE IS SURVIVED BY HER HUSBAND KAO DAUGHTER MAI LILA SON CHING
LUNG, HER SISTERS AND DOZENS OF NIECES AND NEPHEWS INCLUDING
CALVIN. FROM MY OFFICE.
REST IN PEACE AND POWER WITH HONOR STOP ME OR A MEMORY BE A
BLESSING AND THE REST I SUBMITS.
THANK YOU. WE SHOULD PROBABLY GO TO OUR
230 SPECIAL ORDER OUR 230 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER IS THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS AND WE WILL BEGIN WITH DISTRICT
11 SUPERVISOR CHEN. >> THANK YOU, BOB.
AND DR. JAO, MAY I ASK YOU TO THE GO TO THE PODIUM?
>> YEAH. KHALID IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TO
COME DR. CHEN CHONG FOR OVER THREE DECADES OF SERVICE
AND LEADERSHIP AT CHINESE HOSPITAL.
>> DR. ZHANG FIRST JOINT CHINESE HOSPITAL IN 1991 AS A
UCSF INTERNATIONAL STUDENT IN 2017, SUE WAS APPOINTED
CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER DURING A CRITICAL PERIOD AND TIME OF
TRANSITION FOR THE HOSPITAL. >> UNDER HER LEADERSHIP SHE HAS
BUILT A HOSPITAL CENTER AROUND COMMUNITY BASED CARE DURING THE
PANDEMIC. SUE FORM OUR MULTI-LINGUAL
COMMUNITY CENTRIC PUBLIC HEALTH RESPONSE THAT HELPS SAN
FRANCISCO'S CHINATOWN MAINTAIN ONE OF THE LOWEST INFECTION
AND MORTALITY RATES DESPITE BEING ONE OF THE MOST DENSELY
POPULATED AREA IN THE NATION. >> THIS OPERATIONAL SUCCESS WAS
WIDELY PRAISED BY PUBLIC HEALTH AUTHORITIES AND NATIONAL MEDIA
. >> DR. JONES IMPACT IS
IMMEASURABLE. HOW AWARDS IS ACTUALLY THAT ARE
TOO MANY TO LIST HERE. >> SHE IS A MEMBER OF THE
COMMITTEE OF 100 AND IN 2023 SHE WAS ALSO FEATURE ON FORBES
50 OVER 50 INNOVATION LIST. JUST TO NAME A FEW.
>> DELICIOUS. SO LONG.
SUE LEAVES BEHIND A STRONG FOUNDATION BUILT ON COMPASSION
EXCELLENCE AND CULTURAL INTEGRITY.
>> PATIENT CARE HAS CENTER AROUND LANGUAGE ACCESS
AND CULTURALLY COMPETENT SERVICES REPORTING PUBLIC TRUST
IN HEALTH CARE. DR. JIANG, YOUR DECADES OF
COMMITMENT CARE, LEADERSHIP INCREDIBLE WORK AND INVALUABLE
KNOWLEDGE WILL NO DOUBT BE MISSED BY YOUR COLLEAGUES
AND OUR COMMUNITY. AND I WISH YOU ALL THE BEST
IN YOUR NEXT JOURNEY. AND I KNOW BEFORE YOU SPEAK WE
HAVE A LIST OF MY COLLEAGUES ALSO WANT TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> YOU. SUPERVISORS ORDER.
DR. ZHANG, SO GOOD TO HAVE YOU IN THIS CHAMBERS.
AND YOU DESERVE ALL THIS RECOGNITION AND MUCH MORE.
THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND FOR CHINATOWN
IS IMMEASURABLE. AND AS MY COLLEAGUE SHARED YOU
KNOW IN PARTICULAR YOU STEPPED UP BIG DURING THE PANDEMIC
AND YOU KEPT THAT COMMUNITY AND THIS ENTIRE CITY SAFE.
THANK YOU FOR THAT. I KNOW THAT CHINESE HOSPITAL
MEANS SO MUCH TO SO MANY PEOPLE SPEAK OF PRIDE WHEN THEY SPEAK
OF WORKING THERE OR BEING BORN THERE AND IT'S SOMETHING
EXTREMELY RARE AND IT DOESN'T IT DOESN'T HAPPEN BY ACCIDENT.
IT TAKES FOSTERING YEAR AFTER YEAR TO BUILD A LEGACY THAT YOU
HAVE BUILT AND THAT YOU ARE BUILDING WITH YOUR TEAM
AND YOUR STAFF AND YOUR BOARD. PLEASE DON'T GO FAR.
SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS YOU AND I JUST WANT TO APPRECIATE ALL OF
YOUR WORK AND THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR CONTRIBUTIONS.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG THANK YOU PRESIDENT MELO.
AND I JUST WANT TO LEND MY CONGRATULATIONS AS WELL YOUR
WORK TO ENSURE THAT THE CHINESE HOSPITAL REMAINS A CULTURALLY
APPROPRIATE PLACE FOR HEALING AND ALSO A TOP NOTCH MEDICAL
FACILITY AT THE SAME TIME. >> IT'S JUST SOMETHING THAT I
ADMIRE AND IT PROVES THAT YOU CAN LEAD WITH CLASS
AND INTEGRITY AND WITH PURPOSE FOR A AND FOR AN ENTIRE
COMMUNITY AND DO IT IN A MANNER THAT ALSO BENEFITS THE ENTIRE
CITY. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR
WORK. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM AND DOCTOR. I JUST WANT TO SAY CONGRATULATE
ASIANS AND I AM GRATEFUL FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE DONE
WORK NOT JUST AS A MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS BUT
GOING BACK. IT'S HARD TO BELIEVE IT'S
ALMOST 20 YEARS WHEN I WAS WORKING IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE WHEN THERE WAS A MEDICAL GROUP THAT WAS USING ITS MARKET
POSITION IN A WAY THAT THEN CITY ATTORNEY DENNIS HERRERA
FELT IT WAS UNLAWFUL. I WENT SHOULDER TO SHOULDER
WITH CHINESE HOSPITAL AND I WAS REALLY PROUD TO BE A PART OF
THE TEAM ON THAT CASE AND IT WAS AN HONOR TO TO WORK WITH
THAT INSTITUTION THEN. AND IT'S JUST GREAT TO SEE YOU
HONORED TODAY. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU. PRESIDENT MANDO MAN.
DOCTOR ZHANG, I THINK YOU BROUGHT SOME REALLY GREAT GUEST
OF HONOR HERE INCLUDING I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE OUR MAYOR, MR.
WILLIE BROWN THAT IS IN THE CHAMBER.
I MY SUBMISSION IS BECAUSE OF YOU THAT WE ALL GATHER HERE TO
HONOR YOU AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR ACCOMPLISHMENTS FOR OUR
COMMUNITY AND I'M JUST SO GRATEFUL YOU'VE BEEN WORKING
OUR COMMUNITY LONG BEFORE YOU BECAME A LEADER OF CHINESE
HOSPITAL BECAUSE OF YOUR LEADERSHIP.
I REALLY FIRMLY BELIEVE THAT CHINATOWN WAS AT ITS LOWEST OF
INFECTION RATES FOR DURING COVID.
WE HAVE MASK WE WERE ABLE TO INTRODUCE VACCINATION IN THE
MOST IMMEDIATE SENSE FOR ALL THOSE THAT ESPECIALLY THOSE
LIVING IN AS WE ARE ALL THANKS TO YOU AND YOUR LEADERSHIP AT
THE CHINESE HOSPITAL. YOU SAVE LIVES AND THAT WE ARE
GRATEFUL. I DO FIRMLY BELIEVE THAT IT'S
NOT JUST NOW THAT THIS IS THE YET THE BEST HAS YET TO COME
FOR YOU AND FOR US BECAUSE OF YOU.
SO THANK YOU SO MUCH DR. ZHANG FOR ALL THE WORK THAT YOU HAVE
DONE. I LOOK FORWARD TO MORE OF WHAT
YOU WILL ACCOMPLISH. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WANG,
CONGRATULATIONS. >> AND OF AN INTERESTING STORY
OF HOW I FIRST MET DR. ZHANG SO I WAS THE UNION REP FOR SEIU
EMPLOYEES AT CHINESE HOSPITAL FOR FOUR YEARS SO I WOULD BE ON
THE OTHER SIDE PUSHING GRIEVANCES, FIGHTING FOR
WORKERS AND WORKING ON NEGOTIATING DIFFERENT WORKER'S
RIGHTS ISSUES. AND SO DR. ZHANG ALWAYS TELLS
ME WHENEVER I GO INTO HEY, THE NEW UNION REP IS SO MEAN YOU
ALL WERE ALWAYS THE NICEST ONE .
>> HE REALLY WAS. YEAH.
SO AND SINCE THEN I'VE KNOWN YOU IN A DIFFERENT CAPACITY
IN THE COMMUNITY AND JUST RECOGNIZING THAT CHINESE
HOSPITALS I THINK ONE OF THE PRIDES OF OF OUR COMMUNITY MY
MY DAD GOES TO WHAT WHAT IS THE CCP AND AND IT'S SOMETHING THAT
AS A KID I WENT TO THE NORIEGA CLINIC FOR CHP FOR FOR MY FOR
MY MEDICAL SUPPORT SO CHINESE HOSPITAL IS REALLY ONE OF THE
PRIDES OF THE CHINESE COMMUNITY AND I'M JUST SO GLAD THAT WE'RE
ABLE TO TO HONOR YOU. I THINK THAT YOU'VE ALSO BEEN
VERY VISIBLE IN THE COMMUNITY, ESPECIALLY CHINESE COMMUNITY
AND YOU'VE REALLY PUT CHINESE HOSPITAL OUT THERE SO THAT
YOU'RE INVISIBLE AND PEOPLE SEE THE WORK OF CHINESE HOSPITAL.
>> SO THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
AND WE HAVE INDEED BEEN JOINED BY MAYOR BROWN WHO I BELIEVE
MAY HAVE SOME THINGS TO SAY ABOUT DR. ZHONG.
MAYOR BROWN, YOU'RE THERE. >> HOW NICE.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT AND THE BOARD MEMBERS OF OUR
LEGISLATIVE BODY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR GIVING ME AN OPPORTUNITY TO SAY
SOMETHING ABOUT THIS EXTRAORDINARY PERSON WHOM YOU
ARE BEING ASKED TO HONOR IN AMERICA.
INDEPENDENT HOSPITALS WERE AT ONE TIME THE CORNERSTONE OF THE
PEOPLE'S DELIVERY SYSTEM. OVER THE YEARS THOSE HOSPITALS
HAVE FARED ONE WAY OR ANOTHER IN SOMETIMES TO THE DETRIMENT
OF THE PEOPLE THEY PREVIOUSLY SERVED.
THE CHINESE HOSPITAL HAS BEEN DRAMATICALLY DIFFERENT MANY OF
US WHO HAVE HELD PUBLIC OFFICE ARE HOLDING PUBLIC OFFICE OR
ASSOCIATED WHEN ONE FASHION OR ANOTHER HAVE ALWAYS HAD NOTHING
EXCEPT THE HIGHEST INTEGRITY RESPECT FOR THE CHINESE
HOSPITAL. >> AND FOR MORE THAN 30 YEARS
THIS WOMAN HAS BEEN THE SYMBOL OF THAT RESPECT IN THAT EFFORT
AND YOU'RE ACKNOWLEDGING HER CONTRIBUTIONS SPEAKS VOLUMES
FOR THE CONCEPT OF INDEPENDENT HOSPITALS.
>> YOU MAY OR MAY NOT KNOW BUT OVER MANY MONTHS DURING THE
COURSE OF HER 31 YEARS SHE HAS BEEN CALLED UPON BY HOSPITALS
BEING CHALLENGED SIMILARLY TO THE CHINESE HOSPITAL IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND SHE HAS BEEN AS RESPONSIVE AS YOU POSSIBLY TO
BE AND THERE HAVE BEEN ACKNOWLEDGMENTS OF THAT FROM
HOSPITAL ORGANIZATIONS AND INDIVIDUAL ROLES ALL OVER
THE COUNTRY. >> I HAPPENED TO GO TO THE
CHINESE HOSPITAL TO GET HELP WHENEVER I NEEDED, ESPECIALLY
DURING THE PANDEMIC AND THERE CLEARLY WAS A STATIONARY
FOUNDATION FOR THE HEALTH DELIVERY SYSTEM HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO IN THAT TIME PERIOD SUCH THAT OUR OWN HOSPITAL
SYSTEMS PARTICULARLY THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA'S
MEDICAL CENTER DEVELOPED AND EXECUTED A GREAT RESPECT
AND THE UTILIZATION OF THE CHINESE HOSPITAL ALL UNDER THIS
WOMAN'S LEADERSHIP. HER LEAVING IS A GREAT LOSS TO
US IN SAN FRANCISCO TO ALL THESE YEARS SHE HAS AT EVERY
CORNER OF THE OLD DELIVERY SYSTEM BEEN A CORNERSTONE DOING
WHAT SHE NEEDED TO DO TO MAKE THE HEALTH DELIVERY SYSTEM
IN OUR CITY BUT PARTICULARLY THROUGH THE CHINESE HOSPITAL'S
EFFORTS A CONTRIBUTOR. AND SO I REALLY URGE YOU
IN EVERY WAY TO APPROVE THIS RESOLUTE ATION AND TO DO SO
WITH THE GREATEST DEGREE OF RESPECT FOR A CORNERSTONE OF
OUR HEALTH DELIVERY SYSTEM. >> AND I'M REALLY SORRY WE WERE
LOSING HER BECAUSE NOW I CAN'T CALL IF I'M IN LOS ANGELES
AND SAY IS THERE ANYBODY THERE WHEN I GET OFF THE AIRPLANE
COMING IN TO SAN FRANCISCO I CAN STOP BY.
>> I DON'T FEEL WELL. >> I CAN'T DO THAT IF SHE
LEAVES. AND SO I REALLY AM PERSONALLY
HORRIFIED AND I'M GOING TO CALL AND GET TURNED DOWN FOR
ASSISTANCE AND I SUSPECT THAT THERE ARE TON OF PEOPLE AS
NOTHING I LOVE MORE FRANKLY THAN BEING AT SOME EVENT IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND THE QUESTION IS ASKED HOW MANY OF YOU KNOW
ABOUT THE CHINESE HOSPITAL? AND THEN THE QUESTION IS HOW
MANY OF YOU WERE BORN AT THE CHINESE HOSPITAL BEING FROM
TEXAS? >> I WAS NOT BORN IN THE
CHINESE HOSPITAL OBVIOUSLY, BUT I OCCASIONALLY WILL LIE
AND RAISE MY HAND BECAUSE I WANT EVERYBODY TO KNOW HOW MUCH
I THINK OF WHAT THIS LADY HAS DONE SINCE 1991 OF THEREABOUTS
TO MAKE THE CHINESE HOSPITAL WHAT IT IS NOW AND WHAT IT WILL
BE IN THE FUTURE. AND I WANT TO PERSONALLY
CONGRATULATE HER AND I'M SORRY I'M NOT THE MAYOR BECAUSE I'D
LIKE TO BE DOING IT IN MY CAPACITY SOMEWHERE BUT I'M
DOING IT IN MY CAPACITY AS A FRIEND OF THE CHINESE HOSPITAL
AND ADMIRE OF THIS WOMAN WHO HAS SO LED THE CHINESE HOSPITAL
AND I DO SO ON BEHALF OF A COLLECTION OF OTHER ELECTED
OFFICIALS IN PARTICULAR OTHER MAYORS WHO HAVE HAD THE GREAT
PLEASURE AND THE GREAT HONOR OF INTERACTING WITH HER AND HER
LEADERSHIP AS SHE ADVOCATE IT FOR THE QUEST FOR THE RESOURCES
IT WILL MAKE THAT HOSPITAL CONTINUOUSLY SUCCESSFUL AND SO
PLEASE UNANIMOUSLY PASS THIS RESOLUTION.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
>> I WOULD NOTE WE HAVE ALSO BEEN JOINED BY OUR DIRECTOR OF
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH, DANIEL SY.
HELLO. HELLO.
DIRECTOR SY THANK YOU FOR COMING BY.
AND WITH THAT WOULD YOU AND WOULD YOU LIKE TO SAY A FEW
WORDS? >> YOU ARE WELCOME TO SAY A FEW
WORDS. THANK YOU SO THANK YOU.
>> I JUST WANT TO SAY CONGRATULATIONS TO TO DR. ZHENG
AND CHINESE HOSPITAL IS IT HUNDRED 76 IT 102 I ALWAYS ADD
50 BECAUSE I'M VERY OPTIMISTIC 126 YEARS OF BEING HERE SERVING
THE COMMUNITY. MANY PEOPLE THAT WE WORK WITH
WERE BORN IN CHINESE HOSPITAL AND WHAT IT MEANS TO THE
COMMUNITY IS HARD TO PUT WORDS INTO.
SO THANK YOU MAYOR BROWN FOR FOR NOTING THAT AND WE HAVE
DEEP PRIDE AT THE DEPARTMENT FOR BEING ABLE TO WORK WITH JEN
AND THE ENTIRE TEAM AT CHINESE HOSPITAL AND FOR EVERYTHING
THEY'VE DONE IN OUR DELIVERY SYSTEM AND HOW CORE CHINESE
HOSPITAL IS SO WE ARE HERE TO CONTINUE STANDING WITH CHINESE
HOSPITAL IN PARTNERSHIP AND I WANT TO CONGRATULATE DR. ZHENG
AND I KNOW SHE WON'T GO FAR AS AS MICHAEL AND OTHERS TAKE THE
HELM SO CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK YOU TO THE BOARD FOR
RECOGNIZING HER. I'M SORRY I DON'T HAVE MY
JACKET ON BUT THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> I THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> DIRECTOR SYED DR. JANG, ALMOST ANYTHING THAT COULD BE
SAID ABOUT YOU HAS BEEN SAID ABOUT YOU.
BUT I WANT TO ECHO MY COLLEAGUES APPRECIATION FOR YOU
AND CONGRATULATE YOU AND THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR
OFFERING THIS COMMENDATION AND WITH THAT THE FLOOR IS
YOURS AND WHEN YOU'RE DONE WE'RE GOING TO INVITE YOU INTO
THE WELL TO GET A PHOTOGRAPH WITH ALL OF US.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENDHAM AND SUPERVISORS.
>> MAYOR BROWN, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR COMING AND THEN
AND HE'S ACTUALLY IN A MEETING HE JUST GOT OUT OF THE MEETING
FOR THIS. >> I'M REALLY TOUCHED.
AND COMMUNITY LEADERS, COLLEAGUES, FAMILY AND FRIENDS
THANK YOU FOR THIS. >> IT'S JOHN MURRAY HONOR
STANDING HERE TODAY. >> I FEEL DEEPLY HUMBLED
BECAUSE OF THIS RECOGNITION. IT'S NOT ABOUT ONE PERSON.
IT IS ABOUT A COMMUNITY, A HOSPITAL AND A CITY THAT HAVE
SHAPED THE WORK OF MY ENTIRE LIFE.
I FIRST STEP INTO CHINESE HOSPITAL AS AN INTERNATIONAL
STUDENT FROM UCSF DURING MY CLINICAL ROTATION.
MAYOR BROWN IS RIGHT THAT'S 1991.
SO IF YOU COME THE TWO YEARS AS A STUDENT IS ACTUALLY 34 YEARS
INSTEAD OF 32. >> I REMEMBER SEEING A WOMAN
WITH NO INSURANCE WHO COULD NOT AFFORD A MAMMOGRAM AT THAT TIME
MANY WERE FRIGHTENED. MANY WAITED TOO LONG AND TOO
LATE. >> MANY DID NOT KNOW HOW TO
NAVIGATE THE HEALTH CARE SYSTEM THAT DID NOT SPEAK THEIR
LANGUAGE. SO THAT EXPERIENCE CHANGED ME.
>> I BEGAN TEACHING SELF-EXAM CLASSES.
SO YEAH, I STARTED I HAVE DONE MANY OTHER THINGS THAT BECOME
BEFORE I BECAME THE CEO AND WRITING GRANTS SO LOW
INCOME WOMEN COULD GET THE FREE SCREENINGS.
>> I DIDN'T STOP WRITING GRANTS UNTIL I BROUGHT THE I DON'T
KNOW SOME OF YOU PROBABLY REMEMBER THE CANCER EARLY
DETECTION PROGRAM WHICH IT WHICH IS A STAPLE PROGRAM
AND LATER KNOWN AS THE EVERY COUNTS AND WE STILL HAVE TO
PROGRAM AND EDIT CLINICS TO ENSURE THAT EVERY WOMAN
REGARDLESS OF INCOME IMMIGRATION STATUS OR LANGUAGE
HAD ACCESS TO LIFESAVING CARE. >> THAT WAS THE FIRST LESSON I
LEARNED FROM CHINATOWN. >> THEN WHEN YOU SEE A NEED YOU
STEP FORWARD. >> WHEN YOU SEE FEAR YOU BRING
HOPE. >> OVER THE DECADES I HAVE
SERVED ALONGSIDE GENERATIONS OF DEDICATED NURSES THE PHYSICIANS
BOARD MEMBERS AND MANY OF OUR PARTNERS AND THEN OUR OUR STAFF
WE LIVE TO THROUGH MOMENTS THAT TESTED EVERY PART OF US.
>> FINANCIAL INSTABILITY, POLITICAL TABULA NS AND A COVID
PANDEMIC THAT'S THREATENED OUR COMMUNITY.
YET THROUGH IT ALL CHINESE HOSPITAL IT MEANT WHAT IT HAS
BEEN FOR 126 YEARS A PLACE OF SAFETY, DIGNITY
AND UNCONDITIONAL CARE. WE STOOD FIRM.
WE TOOK CARE OF A COMMUNITY AND WE NEVER CLOSED OUR DOORS.
>> WHEN I WAS APPOINTED CEO IN 2017 THE HOSPITAL WAS AT A
CRITICAL TURNING POINT. >> MANY BELIEVED THAT THE LAST
INDEPENDENT COMMUNITY A HOSPITAL IN THE ENTIRE SAN
FRANCISCO BAY AREA COULD NOT SURVIVE DUE TO THE BREAK UP
BETWEEN THE HEALTH PLAN AND A MEDICAL GROUP.
>> BUT THE UNDER ESTIMATE IS SOMETHING IMPORTANT THE
STRENGTH OF THIS COMMUNITY AND THE RESILIENCE OF THIS
HOSPITAL TODAY CHINESE HOSPITAL HAS BEEN RECOGNIZED BY NEWSWEEK
THREE YEARS IN A ROW AS THE US ONE OF THE BEST IN STAY
HOSPITALS KNOWN FOR QUALITY, SAFETY AND CULTURALLY
RESPONSIVE CARE. BUT WE CANNOT STAY STAY STILL.
HEALTH CARE IS CHANGING AND CHINESE HOSPITAL MUST
CONTINUE TO ADAPT TO INNOVATE AND TO EVOLVE SO THAT IT CAN
KEEP SERVING THE MOST VULNERABLE AMONG US.
THIS HONOR TODAY REMINDS US THAT OUR WORK IS NOT DONE.
>> OUR MISSION CONTINUES THE STORY OF CHINESE HOSPITAL ITS
IN SEPARABLE FROM THE STORY OF SAN FRANCISCO ITSELF A CITY
BUILT BY IMMIGRANTS, A CITY THAT WELCOMES THE VULNERABLE, A
CITY THAT BELIEVES IN COMMUNITY HEALTH IS THE SHARED
RESPONSIBILITY AS THE CITY I GUESS MAYOR MAY LIKE ME A
BRONZE SAY BY SUPERVISOR CHEN DECLARES THAT DECEMBER SECOND
US ADAPTOGENS SAME DAY I WANT TO SAY CLEARLY NO INDIVIDUAL
SUCCEEDS ALONG I SHARED THIS HONOR WITH OUR BOARD OF
TRUSTEES AND OUR PHYSICIAN JOINS OUR NURSES, OUR STAFF
AND WHOSE SONG DEDICATIONS IS UNMATCHED.
>> I'LL COMMUNITY PARTNERS AND ELECTED OFFICIALS YOU KNOW
THAT ALL OF YOU I HAVE PROBABLY HAVE GONE TO YOU ALL OF YOU FOR
HELP AND AND OUR COMMUNITY WHO PLACED THEIR TRUST IN US EVERY
DAY MOST IMPORTANTLY I SHARED WITH EVERY IMMIGRANT WHO
WONDERS US IF THEY BELONG AND EVERY YOUNG WOMAN WHO
DREAMS OF LEADING BUT FEARS SHE MIGHT NOT BE SEEN.
>> I HOPE THIS RECOGNITION TELLS THEM YES, YOU BELONG.
YES YOU YOUR WORK MATTERS AND YES LEADERSHIP CAN LOOK
LIKE YOU EVERY SINGLE ONE OF YOU.
>> AS I PREPARE FOR THE NEXT CHAPTER OF MY LIFE I CARRY
FORWARD THE BELIEF THAT LEADERSHIP IS NOT ABOUT HOLDING
THE POSITION. IT IS ABOUT LIFE IN THE PAST
FOR OTHERS. >> I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING
TO SERVE THIS CITY IN NEW WAYS SUPPORTING THE NEXT GENERATION
LEADERS WHO WILL CARRY THIS MISSION FORWARD FROM THE BOTTOM
OF MY HEART. THANK YOU FOR THIS HONOR FOR
YOUR PARTNERSHIP FOR BELIEVING IN CHINESE HOSPITAL A SMALL
HOSPITAL WITH A BIT MISSION STILL STANDING, STILL SERVING
AND STILL ESSENTIAL AFTER 126 YEARS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. I CAN I GET ONE MORE
? LET'S GO OUTSIDE.
SAYING YES. YEAH.
>> ALL RIGHT. DISTRICT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY
THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN. COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY PROFOUND
HONOR TO RECOGNIZE MARK MAZUR TODAY.
MARK TO APPROACH THE LECTERN. >> MARK IS A UNIVERSALLY
RESPECTED FORCE WITHIN SAN FRANCISCO'S DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AND SOMEONE WHOSE ENGAGEMENT IS
FREQUENTLY SOUGHT AFTER USUALLY TO SOLVE NEIGHBORHOOD PROBLEMS
OTHERS MIGHT FIND INTRACTABLE. BUT FROM MY PERSPECTIVE AS A
POLICYMAKER, I'VE COME TO RECOGNIZE TO THE EXTENT TO
WHICH HE IS SOUGHT AFTER FOR HIS HIGHLY WELL INFORMED
PERSPECTIVE, HIS HEART AND HIS WILLINGNESS TO OFFER HIS
UNVARNISHED VIEWPOINT ON WHAT WE AS A CITY SHOULD BE DOING TO
BETTER SOLVE AND SERVE OUR MOST VULNERABLE.
AS NEIGHBORHOOD STREET TEAM MANAGER, MARK DOES NOT SIMPLY
COORDINATE LOGISTICS. HE WALKS THE NEIGHBORHOOD
SOMETIMES 50 MILES A WEEK MEETING PEOPLE WHERE THEY ARE
EARNING A LEVEL OF TRUST FEW OTHERS CAN.
OFTEN SEEING ME ON MY BIKE SHARE RIDES AROUND THE DISTRICT
IN A NEIGHBORING AREAS. MARK'S ROLE IS EMBLEMATIC OF
THE OEM'S MISSION TO ANCHOR EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT NOT JUST
TO BUILDINGS AND PLANS BUT IN LIVED EXPERIENCE AND IN
HUMAN RELATIONSHIPS. HIS DEDICATION IS ROOTED
IN WHAT I CONSIDER TO BE A UNIQUELY SAN FRANCISCAN CIVIC
VALUE THAT BALANCES PRAGMATISM AND WITH COMPASSION.
HE UNDERSTANDS THAT CHANGE ON THE STREET DOESN'T COME
OVERNIGHT BUT IT DOES COME PERSON BY PERSON AND OFTEN ONE
STEP AT A TIME. AFTER THE TENDERLOIN, LINCOLN
CENTER CLOSED HIS TEAM REORGANIZED THE NEIGHBORHOOD
INTO FOUR ZONES AND COMMITTED TO WORKING EACH AREA SEVEN DAYS
A WEEK NOT TO DISPLACE PEOPLE BUT TO OFFER REPEATED OUTREACH
WELLNESS CHECKS AND SHELTERED CONNECTIONS IN THE FACE OF AN
UNSHELTERED POPULATION OF THOUSANDS.
HIS STEADY PRESENCE MAKES A DIFFERENCE IN WORK THAT IS
OFTEN GRUELING AND UNDER-APPRECIATED.
BUT HE KNOWS THERE IS PROGRESS THROUGH PERSISTENCE.
WHAT MAKES MARK TRULY REMARKABLE IS HOW HE BEARS HIS
RESPONSIBILITIES WITH HUMILITY. HE'S NOT SOMEONE WHO SEEKS
HEADLINES BUT WHETHER IT'S IN INTERVIEWS, IN PUBLIC
PRESENTATIONS, IN PRIVATE CONVERSATIONS OR EVEN
IN DEPOSITIONS AND CIVIL LITIGATION HE DOESN'T SHY AWAY
FROM THE HARD TRUTHS. HE RECOGNIZES THE SCALE OF THE
CHALLENGE AND ACKNOWLEDGES THE TRUTH.
ALL OF US NEED TO HEAR AND I QUOTE THERE'S SO MUCH NEED OUT
HERE AND NOT ENOUGH OF US TO HELP.
MARK IS THE KIND OF DEDICATED PUBLIC SERVANT WE NEED MANY
MORE OF. SOMEONE WHO BELIEVES THAT
MEANINGFUL CHANGE ISN'T ABOUT TICKING BOXES BUT BUILDING
BRIDGES OVER TIME. TODAY AS WE HONOR MARK WE
CELEBRATE MORE THAN HIS ROLE OR HIS TITLE.
WE CELEBRATE HIS SPIRIT OF SERVICE ROOTED IN PRAGMATISM
AND GENUINE COMPASSION. SOMEONE WHO DOESN'T JUST
COORDINATE EMERGENCY OPERATIONS BUT SUSTAINS HEALING WORK
IN THE TOUGHEST PARTS OF OUR CITY.
SAN FRANCISCO IS BETTER AND MORE RESILIENT BECAUSE OF
MARK MOSES TIRELESS COMMITMENT HIS EMPATHY UNDER PRESSURE.
HIS COURAGE TO SHOW UP DAY AFTER DAY FOR THOSE WHO NEED IT
MOST. CONGRATULATE MARK.
WE ARE BLESSED TO HAVE YOU AS OUR FELLOW PUBLIC SERVANT
AND WE THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE AND YOUR
PROFESSIONALISM. >> AND I HAVE A COUPLE WE HAVE
A COUPLE OF COLLEAGUES WHO WANT TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL I WILL FIRST SUPERVISOR DORSEY, THANK
YOU SO MUCH FOR FOR RECOGNIZING SOMEONE THAT I CONSIDER TO BE A
HERO OF SAN FRANCISCO. MARK YOU'VE BEEN A GREAT FRIEND
TO ME SINCE I STARTED WORKING WITH THE CITY THREE YEARS AGO.
YOU HAVE BEEN ONE OF THE MOST GENEROUS PEOPLE TO ME ON A
PERSONAL LEVEL BUT REALLY WHERE I SEE YOUR VALUE IS ON THE
STREET. YOU ARE COMPASSIONATE, YOU ARE
AGGRESSIVE, YOU ARE THOUGHTFUL, YOU ARE REALISTIC AND YOU NEVER
NEVER STOP. YOU ARE EXACTLY THE KIND OF
PERSON THAT THIS CITY AND EVERY PERSON NEEDS FIGHTING FOR EVERY
ONE OF US. I AM SO GRATEFUL TO CALL YOU A
FRIEND, TO CALL YOU A COLLEAGUE TO HAVE BEEN ABLE TO WORK
ALONGSIDE YOU AND HOPEFULLY TO BE IN A POSITION TO SUPPORT YOU
BECAUSE YOU SUPPORT ALL OF US SO SO MUCH.
NOW I ALSO KNOW THAT YOU'RE NOT ALONE.
I SEE A TON OF YOUR COLLEAGUES HERE.
>> COULD EVERYONE WHO CONSIDERS MARC A COLLEAGUE PLEASE STAND
UP AND BE RECOGNIZED IF YOU WILL?
>> I'M LUCKY ENOUGH TO HAVE SAT IN A LOT OF MEETINGS AND A LOT
OF ZOOMS WITH ALL OF YOU AND I THINK YOU ALL FEEL THE SAME WAY
ABOUT MARK THAT I DO. SO TO ALL OF YOU AND TO MARK I
JUST WANT TO THANK YOU ALL FOR FIGHTING SO HARD FOR OUR CITY.
>> CONGRATULATIONS, MARK. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
CONGRATULATIONS, MARK. >> I JUST WANTED TO THANK YOU
IN THIS LAST YEAR OF GETTING TO KNOW YOU WALKING THE STREETS OF
THE TENDERLOIN WITH THE HOT TEAMS.
I WILL SEE YOU WHEN I'M NOT EXPECTING TO AND WHEN I AM
EXPECTING TO. AND I THINK IT JUST SPEAKS TO
THE DEEP ROOTED COMMITMENT YOU HAVE TO THIS NEIGHBORHOOD
AND OF DOING THE WORK AND DOING THE WORK IS IS HARD WORK
IN THIS NEIGHBORHOOD ON YOUR JOB.
>> AND I THINK ONE OF THE THINGS I REALLY APPRECIATE
ABOUT YOU IS YOUR PERSONAL TOUCH ON ONE OF THE MOST
DIFFICULT CRISES IN SAN FRANCISCO AND IT'S THAT FROM MY
UNDERSTANDING YOU HAVE FIRSTHAND KNOWLEDGE OF SOME OF
THINGS THAT MATTER MOST ON THE STREETS WHICH IS PEOPLE'S NAMES
,THEIR BACKGROUNDS, THEIR HISTORIES.
YOU DEVELOP A PERSONAL RELATIONSHIP WITH THE PEOPLE
WHO ARE ON THE GROUND TO HELP THEM GET TO A BETTER LIFE.
AND I THINK THAT LEVEL OF EMPATHY AND CARE AND RESILIENCE
IS WHAT WE NEED FROM CITY OFFICIALS AND YOU EXEMPLIFY
THAT. YOU ARE THE BEST FIT FOR THEM
ONE OF THE MOST DIFFICULT JOBS .
IT'S ALMOST LIKE THE JOB WAS CREATED FOR YOU BUT WE ARE VERY
FORTUNATE TO HAVE YOU LEADING ON THIS EFFORT EVERY DAY
AND WE'RE VERY THANKFUL FOR YOUR SERVICE.
>> SO THANK YOU. >> YEAH.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
AND JUST QUICKLY ADD TO THE PRAISE FOR YOU MARK.
YOU ARE THE PERSON THAT SO MANY OF US CALL WHEN WE NEED HELP
AND WHEN WE SEE PEOPLE THAT NEED HELP AND I KNOW THAT IT'S
A HEAVY BURDEN AND IT'S A LOT THAT YOU TAKE ON AND I WANT TO
RECOGNIZE THAT. YOU KNOW, A FEW MONTHS INTO MY
TERM YOU AND I HADN'T MET IN PERSON YET BUT YOU WERE KIND
OF THAT ONE PERSON THAT I KEPT HEARING THE NAME OF.
AND I WAS LIKE WHO IS THIS MARK?
BECAUSE EVERYONE SPEAKS SO HIGHLY OF YOU AND EVERYONE'S
ALWAYS SAYING, YOU KNOW, MARK AND I CAN TAKE CARE OF THIS
MARK AND HELP WITH THIS AND WE GET TO TALK TO HIM ABOUT THIS.
SO IT'S BEEN GOOD TO GET TO KNOW YOU MORE.
I KNOW WE'LL KEEP GETTING TO KNOW EACH OTHER AND I WANT TO
IN PARTICULAR I APPRECIATE YOUR YOUR WORK IN LEADERSHIP ON I
THINK A MODEL THAT WE'RE ALL REALLY ROOTING FOR AND A MODEL
THAT WE'RE ALL INVESTED IN THE SUCCESS OF WITH THE
NEIGHBORHOOD STREET TEAMS. WE KNOW THAT THERE'S A LOT OF
PROMISE THERE AND WE NEED TO KEEP IMPROVING IT BECAUSE IT IS
YOU KNOW, THE MODEL AND THE TEAM AND THE FRAMEWORK THAT IS
GOING TO GET PEOPLE INTO CARE AND GET PEOPLE INTO SERVICES.
>> SO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOUR LEADERSHIP AND THANK YOU FOR
ALL YOUR WORK. >> YOU HAVE A LOT OF FRIENDS
AND A LOT OF OFFICES. DISTRICT EIGHT OFFICE IS VERY
FOND OF MARK MESA. >> I KNOW SOME NUMBER OF YEARS
AGO I HEARD IT SAID THAT SAN FRANCISCO IS THE CITY THAT
MEETS PEOPLE WHERE THEY ARE AND LEAVES THEM THERE.
AND I THINK THAT THAT HAS BEGUN TO CHANGE AND OVER THE LAST
SEVERAL YEARS AND A LOT OF IT IS YOUR WORK AND OF COURSE THE
WORK OF YOUR COLLEAGUES AS WELL.
HEY, SAM DODSON, SANTI AND ALL OF YOU WHO WHO DO THIS WORK
IT'S REALLY HARD BUT I'VE SEEN DRAMATIC TRANSFORMATION IN THE
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT I REPRESENT .
I KNOW THE STORIES OF PEOPLE WHO HAD BEEN ON THE STREETS FOR
A VERY, VERY LONG TIME AND WHO ARE NOW NOT ON THE STREETS.
I SEE THE CARE THAT YOU HAVE FOR INDIVIDUALS AND ALSO THE
CARE YOU HAVE FOR COMMUNITIES. AND WE ARE NOT CLOSE TO WHERE
WE NEED TO BE BUT WE HAVE MADE LOTS AND LOTS OF PROGRESS AND A
LOT OF THAT IS ABOUT YOU, MARK. SO THANK YOU.
AND IF I HAVE SPOKEN THAT MEANS YOU GET TO SPEAK.
>> THIS IS NOT MY NORMAL WORK ENVIRONMENT.
IT'S WE APOLOGIZE. >> THOSE OF YOU WHO KNOW ME I
NORMALLY CAN'T HAVE ME STOP TALKING BUT I'LL BE I'LL BE
BRIEF TODAY. FIRST, I TRULY AM HUMBLED JUST
TO BE HERE AND HEAR ALL OF THESE GREAT THINGS AND WITH ALL
OF THE NEW STREET TEAMS AND THE COORDINATION WE'RE DOING
IN TEAM I'M VERY PROUD OF IT. EVEN AT THE MEETING LAST NIGHT
I FEEL LIKE WE'RE HEARING CITY LEADERS TALKING ABOUT HOW
THEY'VE NEVER SEEN THE WORK COORDINATED AND I AGREE SO WELL
. WORKING AS A SOCIAL WORKER
CLOSELY WITH LAW ENFORCEMENT AND MAKING IT WORK IS VERY
DIFFERENT AND IT'S VERY NECESSARY.
I THINK THAT IT'S BEEN MADE CLEAR THAT WE ARE NO LONGER A
TEAM JUST WORKING TO END HOMELESSNESS.
WE ARE WORKING TO END HOMELESSNESS, CRIME
AND ADDICTION. AND I THANK YOU FOR GIVING US
THE TOOLS THAT WE NEED TO DO MORE BECAUSE IT DOES FEEL AT
TIMES LIKE WE'VE GONE AS FAR AS WE CAN WITH THE TOOLS THAT WE
HAVE. AND I JUST YOU KNOW, I'M A
SOCIAL WORKER. I THINK ABOUT THE PEOPLE WE'RE
HELPING. BUT I ALSO I WANT TO TALK A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT THE STAFF. I'M VERY LUCKY TO WORK WITH
STAFF FROM ALL WALKS OF LIFE AND EVERYONE'S TIRED
AND THERE'S THERE'S A COMMON THREAD.
PEOPLE CLEANING THE STREET DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS THEY
WORK VERY HARD TO SHOW UP THE NEXT DAY LIKE THEY WERE NEVER
THERE. OUTREACH WORKERS CELEBRATE
GETTING PEOPLE IN THE SHELTER AND HOUSING TO SEE THEM BACK
WHERE THEY WERE THE DAY BEFORE I OUR FIRE DEPARTMENT
PARAMEDICS TAKE PEOPLE TO THE EMERGENCY ROOM TO SEE THEM
WHERE THEY WERE WHEN THEY PICKED THEM UP.
OUR AMBASSADORS AND PRACTITIONERS ARE LITERALLY
BRINGING PEOPLE BACK TO LIFE REVERSING OVERDOSES TO FIND
THEM WHERE THEY WERE YESTERDAY .
OUR STREET BASED MEDICAL PROVIDERS ARE SENDING PEOPLE TO
THE HOSPITAL SOMETIMES VOLUNTARILY AND SOMETIMES
AGAINST THEIR WILL TO FIND THEM WHERE THEY WERE YESTERDAY.
OUR POLICE OFFICERS ARRESTING PEOPLE FOR CRIME TO FIND THEM
BACK WHERE THEY WERE. SO IN SHORT YOU STOLE MY
THUNDER A LITTLE BIT BUT THEY'VE HEARD IT TOO WAY TOO
MANY TIMES. BUT THE MOTTO FOR OUR STREET
TEAMS OFTEN IS THAT WE'RE GOING TO BE COMPASSIONATE AND MEET
PEOPLE WHERE THEY ARE AT BUT WE CAN NO LONGER LEAVE THEM WHERE
THEY ARE. >> SO THAT'S IT FOR ME.
SMILE
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 34. ITEM NUMBER 34 IS A HEARING AT
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE TO HEAR AND RECEIVE UPDATES ON THE PROGRESS
AND IMPLEMENTATION STATUS OF THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF
JUSTICE RECOMMENDATIONS REGARDING REFORMS WITHIN THE
POLICE DEPARTMENT. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
THE LAW CAN I SPEAK FOR EVERYBODY?
OH ACTUALLY I GUESS I DO HAVE SOME SOME WORDS.
SUPERVISOR WELL I'M JUST WORDS THAT PERHAPS YEAH WE COLLEAGUES
WERE NOW SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TO RECEIVE ANOTHER
UPDATE ON THESE FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS AND I
BELIEVE SUPERVISOR WONG HAS SOME REMARKS.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND I WANT TO THANK
THE DEPARTMENT FOR BEING HERE THIS AFTERNOON JUST TO GIVE A
BRIEF HISTORY S.F. PD REQUESTED THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE
TO COME IN AND ASSESS ITS PRACTICES AND IN 2016 THEY
PROVIDED A REPORT WITH SEVERAL FINDINGS AND 272
RECOMMENDATIONS FOR THE DEPARTMENT THE U.S. DEPARTMENT
OF JUSTICE ENDED ITS PARTNERSHIP WITH S.F. PD
IN 2017 AND THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE AGREED TO
WORK WITH S.F. PD IN 2018 ALONG WITH CONSULTING FIRM JENSEN
HUGHES TO ADDRESS THE REFORMS. THE 272 DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE
RECOMMENDATIONS FOR S.F. PD HAVE LED TO SOME CHANGES
AND IMPROVEMENTS FOR THE DEPARTMENT BUT THERE ARE STILL
MORE WORK TO DO TO GAIN THE TRUST AND IMPROVE RELATIONSHIPS
BETWEEN COMMUNITIES OF COLOR AND LAW ENFORCEMENT.
TODAY'S COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE IS AN UPDATE ON WHERE THE
DEPARTMENT IS IN REGARD TO THOSE 272 RECOMMENDATIONS
AND NEXT STEPS. >> I KNOW WE WILL HEAR FROM
ASIA STEPHENS POLICY DEVELOPMENT DIVISION MANAGER
AND I BELIEVE NICOLE JONES, DEPUTY CHIEF OF ADMINISTRATION
. THEN OF COURSE WE WILL HEAR
FROM COLLEAGUES WITH ANY STATEMENTS OR QUESTIONS AND GO
ON TO PUBLIC COMMENT. >> YOU HAVE THE FLOOR.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. MY NAME IS R.J. STEEVES.
I AM THE MANAGER OF THE POLICY DEVELOPMENT DIVISION WITH SAN
FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT. I CAN JUST GET RIGHT INTO THE
SLIDES AND KEEP IT VERY BRIEF. SUPERVISOR WALTON BASICALLY DID
MY FIRST SLIDE FOR ME SO THAT'S LOVELY.
THE OVERVIEW WHY WE'RE HERE AGAIN WE DID REQUEST THIS WAS A
VOLUNTARY EFFORT. THIS WAS NOT A CONSENT DECREE
TO GET INTO THE ASSESSMENT OF LAW ENFORCEMENT PRACTICES HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. OF THE 272 RECOMMENDATIONS
ISSUED IN 220 16. WE HAVE REACHED 263 IN SUCH
SUBSTANTIAL COMPLIANCE. >> SO WE DO HAVE NINE PENDING
IF WE CAN GET THE PRESENTATION UP FOR EVERYONE TO SEE.
THANK YOU. >> WE WERE HERE IN MAY SO MAY
6TH WE DID PROVIDE A COMPREHENSIVE OVERVIEW WITH
PHASE TIMELINES REFORM HIGHLIGHTS AND REVIEW OF THE
CAL DOJ FINAL REPORT AND NEXT STEPS SO WE CAN GO TO THE NEXT
SLIDE. OF THE REMAINING NINE ALL OF
ACTUALLY EIGHT OF THEM DIRECTLY LINK TO THE IMPLEMENTATION OF A
DATA DASHBOARD ONE INDIRECTLY LINKS TO THAT DASHBOARD.
>> SO AS YOU CAN SEE AGAIN THERE'S A PERFORMANCE
EVALUATION PROCESS DATA DRIVEN DASHBOARD SUPERVISORY
ACCOUNTABILITY THAT RELIES ON DATA INDICATORS, EVALUATION
METRICS THAT ALSO RELIES ON DATA TRENDS, PROMOTIONAL POLICY
THAT INDIRECTLY RELIES WITH A DATA DASHBOARD TRAINING
SUPERVISORS. >> AGAIN TARGETED TRAINING TO
INTERPRET THE DASHBOARD. SO ALL OF THESE NINE REALLY DO
RELY ON A SYSTEM THAT WE DO NOT HAVE IN PLACE RIGHT NOW.
>> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE. >> SO I KNOW THE LAST
PRESENTATION WE CAME IN MAY WE DID HEAR QUITE A FEW CONCERNS
FROM SUPERVISORS ABOUT DATA, ABOUT DATA INTEGRITY, ABOUT OUR
SYSTEM SPEAKING TO EACH OTHER, HOW WE CAN MAKE RELIABLE
DECISIONS BASED ON DATA. AND SO WE WANT TO TALK ABOUT
THE THINGS THAT WE ARE DOING AND ARE PLANNING TO DO MOVING
FORWARD TO MAKE SURE THAT WE CAN MEET THOSE LAST NINE
COMPLIANCE MEASURES AND ALSO JUST HELP US AS AN AGENCY
MOVING FORWARD TO MAKE THESE DATA DRIVEN AND DATA INFORMED
DECISIONS FOR POLICY SUPERVISING TRAINING AND GOING
FORWARD. SO BIG THING THAT WE DID IS WE
RESTRUCTURED AND CENTRALIZED OUR S.F. PD DATA TEAMS.
THIS HAPPENED IN JULY OR AUGUST.
WE ALL OF OUR DATA TEAMS WE HAD SEVERAL THAT WERE ACTUALLY
SEGREGATED AND HAD DIFFERENT REPORTING STRUCTURES.
NOW THEY ALL REPORT UNDER THE DIRECTOR OF CRIME STRATEGIES.
THIS IS KEY. THIS BUILDS INFRASTRUCTURE SO
THAT ALL OF OUR DATA TEAMS KNOW WHAT THE OTHER IS DOING.
THERE IS ONE CENTRAL MANAGEMENT TEAM OVER THOSE DATA TEAMS SO
THAT THEY CAN HAVE ALL SIT UNDER THE SAME UMBRELLA THAT
TIES ACTUALLY TO DRAFTING AND ISSUING A NEW DEPARTMENT
GENERAL ORDER REGARDING DATA MANAGEMENT.
THIS ALSO WAS AT THE REQUEST OF THE POLICE COMMISSION BUT ALSO
JUST AN INTERNAL LEAD. THIS WILL ESTABLISH AND CODIFY
STANDARDS USED TO MANAGE DATA THROUGH ITS LIFECYCLE.
RIGHT? AND SO THIS ENSURES THAT THE
DATA IS SECURE, THAT IT'S ACCURATE AND IT'S RELIABLE
AND IT'S USABLE AGAIN. SO THIS CAN BE USED TO MAKE
POLICY DECISIONS, MAKE SUPERVISORS ALL DECISIONS TO
MAKE TRAINING DECISIONS. SO THAT IS IN THE WORKS THAT'LL
START IN ACTUALLY IT'S BEEN STARTED THIS YEAR BUT IT'LL
PROBABLY FINISH IN 2027. OUR CYCLE TO UPDATE DEPARTMENT
GENERAL ORDERS IS QUITE LONG. IT TAKES ABOUT 225 TO 445
BUSINESS DAYS TO UPDATE A DIGITAL THAT THAT'S BEFORE IT
GOES TO MEETING CONFER. AND ALSO WITH PROPERTY THERE IS
A COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT 90 DAY CYCLE THAT MAY KICK IN.
SO CREATING A DEJO IS LENGTHY BUT IT IS AN UNDERTAKING THAT
IS NECESSARY. WE'VE ALSO RESTRUCTURED THE CRC
SUSTAINABILITY SO THAT IT IS UNDER THE POLICY DEVELOPMENT
DIVISION. WE BELIEVE WITH ALL OF THE
SUSTAINABILITY EFFORTS IT ALL TIES TO POLICY.
SO TO HAVE AN EYE ON WHAT'S BEING UPDATED WHEN IT'S BEING
UPDATED, HOW AN UPDATE OF A POLICY COULD IMPACT SOMETHING
THAT WE'VE ALREADY AGREED TO DO, WE FEEL THAT HAVING IT
UNDER THIS UMBRELLA WILL ACTUALLY CONTINUE THE
SUSTAINABLE SUSTAINABILITY EFFORTS.
>> WE'RE ALSO UPDATING DINGOS RELATED TO PERFORMANCE
IMPROVEMENT AND EARLY INTERVENTION SYSTEMS TO ALIGN
WITH THE CRC COMPLIANCE MEASURES.
AGAIN THAT'LL BE A 2027 PROJECT BUT THAT AGAIN ALIGNS WITH
THESE NINE THAT ARE REMAINING. A BIG ONE IS RECRUITING
AND HIRING A CIO WITH INDUSTRY WIDE EXPERTISE.
SO WE NEED THIS IT ENSURES OUR STAFFING RESOURCE
INFRASTRUCTURE THAT WE HAVE NEEDED FOR DATA MANAGEMENT
AND INTEGRITY AND DATA SYSTEMS AND ALSO SEEKING A NEW DATA
DASHBOARD VENDOR. I KNOW IN THE PAST WE'VE COME
AND WE'VE SPOKEN TO THIS BODY AND SAID THAT WE HAVE BEEN
WORKING WITH A VENDOR. WE DID CONTRACT WITH ONE
AND WE'RE FINDING THAT OUR NEEDS ACTUALLY JUST EXCEED
THEIR CAPABILITIES. WE HAVE EVALUATED IT AND WE'RE
REALLY SEEKING A VENDOR THAT CAN GIVE US THE THINGS THAT WE
NEED MOVING FORWARD. >> NEXT SLIDE PLEASE.
SO IN CLOSING WE WILL CONTINUE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE FOUNDATION
OF REFORM WORK. IT REALLY IS THE FOUNDATION OF
EVERYTHING ACCOUNTABILITY AND SAFETY WITH RESPECT.
THESE ARE THINGS THAT ARE INGRAINED INTO ALL OF OUR
POLICIES AND INTO OUR TRAINING NETWORKS SUSTAINABLE DOES
DEPEND ON A FULLY STAFFED DEPARTMENT.
WE DO NOT HAVE THAT NOW. IT'S ALWAYS LOVELY TO WORK ON
PROJECTS IF YOU ARE FULLY STAFFED.
WE ARE NOT. SO WE ARE WORKING ON THAT.
THAT IS PART OF ONE OF THE SECRET CRC BUCKETS IS
RECRUITMENT SO THAT IS TAKING A FOREFRONT ON OUR ACTIVITIES.
BUT OUR PRIMARY FOCUS IS ON PUBLIC SAFETY AND THE NEEDS OF
SAN FRANCISCO. SO OVERALL GOAL IS TO APPLY
LESSONS LEARNED FROM REFORM TO INNOVATE UPDATE POLICIES
AND RECRUIT AND RETAIN TALENT TO BETTER ADDRESS CRIME AND THE
ISSUES THAT WERE REALLY BIG IN 2016.
>> STILL, THE CORE OF WHAT WE WANT TO DO AND HOW WE WANT TO
POLICE BUT WE'RE FACING NEW ISSUES THAT WE WILL USE ALL OF
THE LESSONS THAT WE'VE LEARNED FROM THE CIA PROCESS TO MOVE
FORWARD AND ADDRESS ISSUES THAT ARE BIG IN 2026, 2027, IN 2028
MOVING FORWARD. SO THAT'S THE BRIEF UPDATE THAT
I HAVE. I'M AGAIN I AM I'M HERE WITH DC
JONES SO WE CAN ANSWER QUESTIONS THAT YOU MAY HAVE.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU TO EVERYONE.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENEM AND THANK YOU FOR THE
PRESENTATION AND I DO HAVE A FEW QUESTIONS.
>> ONE OF THE MAJOR ISSUES THAT WE'VE SEEN HERE IN THE CITY
AND WE CONTINUE TO SEE IS THE DISPROPORTIONALITY OF POLICE
STOPS AND BIAS AROUND VEHICLE POLICE STOPS PARTICULARLY
IN REFERENCE TO RACE. HAS THAT DATA IMPROVED
SUPERVISED OR CAN YOU CLARIFY YOU SAID PARTICULARLY AS IT
RELATES TO BIAS BIAS WHEN IT COMES TO WHO POLICE ARE
STOPPING ON THE STREETS? >> I THINK YOU SAID RATES RACE,
RACE, RACE. >> OKAY.
I HEARD SOMETHING DIFFERENT AND IT WAS NOT A GOOD WORD.
>> YES. >> SO WE HAVE DONE A LOT OF
WORK IN THIS ARENA RIGHT NOW. THE SYSTEM THAT WE ARE SPEAKING
ABOUT THAT WE ARE MOVING AWAY FROM THAT DATA VENDOR, WE ARE
MOVING TO A DIFFERENT VENDOR. >> I THINK THAT THE ADDITIONAL
INFORMATION THAT WE ARE CAPTURING RIGHT NOW ENABLES US
TO HAVE A FAR BETTER ANALYSIS OF WHAT OUR STOPS ARE ACTUALLY
TELLING US. SO STATE LEGISLATION REQUIRES
THAT WE COLLECT CERTAIN FIELDS. IT'S ALL BASED ON PERCEPTION
WHAT THE OFFICERS PERCEPTION WAS AS IT RELATES TO RACE AND A
HOST OF OTHER THINGS. >> AND THE DEPARTMENT HAS
ELECTED TO BRING ADDITIONAL FACTORS IN AND COLLECT MORE
INFORMATION THAN IS NECESSARY SO WE CAN COMPLETE THESE
ANALYZES. WE'VE BEEN DOING A LOT OF WORK.
>> EVERYBODY I THINK IS PROBABLY FAMILIAR WITH HER.
OUR REPORT THAT WE PUBLISH THAT GIVES THE RATES AS IT RELATES
TO THESE TRAFFIC STOPS BUT WE'VE BEEN EXPLORING A LOT WITH
THIS VENDOR THAT WE CURRENTLY HAVE AS IT RELATES TO WHAT THE
DEMOGRAPHICS ARE LIKE IN THE DISTRICT INSTEAD OF JUST
OVERALL IN THE CITY. >> BUT WHAT THOSE DEMOGRAPHICS
ARE LIKE WHO YOU'RE LIKELY TO ENCOUNTER AT THOSE TIMES.
SO REALLY DIVING IN A LITTLE BIT MORE.
>> BUT THERE SHOULDN'T BE A CONCERN THAT WE'RE MOVING AWAY
FROM THIS ORIGINAL DATA VENDOR. WE WILL NOT DO SO UNTIL WE HAVE
A NEW SYSTEM IN PLACE THAT COLLECTS THE INFORMATION THAT
WE NEED IT TO. SO WE CONTINUE AGAIN TO TO DO
MORE THAN IS NECESSARY TO TRY TO UNDERSTAND AS BEST AS
POSSIBLE WHAT'S HAPPENING. >> BUT HAS THE DATA IMPROVED?
I THINK THE IT DEPENDS ON WHAT YOU WOULD CONSIDER IMPROVEMENT.
>> ARE THERE LESS ARE THERE LESS WAS DISPROPORTIONALITY GAP
. >> I WOULD HAVE TO GO BACK
AND CHECK WHAT THE MOST RECENT REPORT STATES.
>> BUT I THINK THAT IT'S REALLY HARD TO DETERMINE WHETHER OR
NOT THAT'S LESS EVEN JUST BASED ON THE DATA THAT WE HAVE THAT
COMES OUT AND THE ADR REPORT. >> SO SO I KNOW AND AGAIN
AND THANK YOU DC JONES FOR BEING HERE.
I KNOW THAT'S BEEN A MAJOR ISSUE THE DISPROPORTIONALITY OF
LESS THAN 5% OF THE POPULATION OF SAN FRANCISCO RECEIVING MOST
OF THE VEHICLE POLICE STOPS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I THINK THAT'S A TREND THAT WE DEFINITELY ARE WORKING HARD TO
GET AWAY FROM. I DO WANT TO APOLOGIZE I DIDN'T
ASK FOR THAT SPECIFIC DATA AND I KNOW THERE'S BEEN
TURNOVER IN THE DEPARTMENT BUT THAT'S USUALLY THE TYPE OF DATA
WE GET WHEN WE HAVE THIS CONVERSATION IN THIS HEARING.
SO I KNOW WHEN WE COME BACK WE CAN TALK MORE ABOUT THAT
AND HOW ARE WE DOING ON THE EVALUATION OF OFFICERS BECAUSE
I KNOW THAT WAS SOMETHING THAT WAS IMPORTANT AND KEY AS WELL
IN THE RECOMMENDATIONS. >> YEAH.
SO IN TERMS OF EVALUATION WOULD YOU WANT ME TO COVER?
>> YEAH. IN TERMS OF EVALUATION OF
OFFICERS. >> SO WE'RE WE'RE TRYING TO
COMPLETELY REVAMP WHAT OUR PERFORMANCE APPRAISAL SYSTEM
LOOKS LIKE AND REALLY TRY TO UNDERSTAND NOT JUST HOW PEOPLE
ARE DOING BUT WHAT THOSE SPECIFIC STATS I THINK THAT YOU
ARE SPEAKING TO WHAT THEY MEAN AND WHAT THEY MEAN ABOUT OUR
OFFICERS. AND I THINK THAT THAT'S BEEN A
WORK IN PROGRESS FOR A WHILE. YOU JUST SPOKE TO THE FACT THAT
WE HAVE AN ENTIRELY NEW LEADERSHIP TEAM AND WE ARE
TRYING TO PUT IN PLACE A SYSTEM THAT'S NOT ONLY GOING TO TELL
US THE THINGS THAT I JUST SPOKE ABOUT BUT THAT'S GOING TO BE
SUSTAINABLE ALL BECAUSE SUSTAINABILITY HAS BEEN A HUGE
ISSUE FOR US AND MAKING SURE THAT PEOPLE ARE COMPLETING
THESE THAT ARE LOOKING AT THIS INFORMATION OR EARLY
INTERVENTION SYSTEM ALSO IS IN THE PROCESS.
IT WAS HOUSED IN THIS AND CONTINUES TO BE AT THIS
MOMENT HOUSED IN THIS OTHER DATA SYSTEM THAT WE ARE MOVING
AWAY FROM BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT WE CAN CAPTURE THE DATA
AGAIN BETTER AND MAKE IT MORE MEANINGFUL SO WE CAN UNDERSTAND
AND WHAT'S HAPPENING HERE BUT ALSO WORK IN PROGRESS.
>> SO THAT IS ONE OF THE REMAINING NINE THAT WE THAT'S
ON THE LIST. SO AGAIN IT'S NOT COMPLETED BUT
JUST TO FOLLOW UP ON EVERYTHING SHE'S SAYING, THAT IS ONE OF
THE REMAINING NINE THINGS THAT WE NEED TO ESTABLISH AND THAT
DOES GO HAND IN HAND WITH UPDATING INTERNAL POLICIES.
SO THE DEPARTMENT GENERAL ORDERS ALONG WITH THE DASHBOARD
AND THE TRAINING THE SUPERVISORS ON HOW TO EVALUATE
AS WELL. AND HAVE THERE BEEN ANY UPDATES
IN THE HIRING PRACTICES TO ENSURE THAT WE'RE HIRING
OFFICERS WITH INTEGRITY? OBVIOUSLY I KNOW THE WORK
IN THE FOCUS TO PROVIDE ADEQUATE TRAINING AND ACADEMY
IS SOMETHING THAT HAS BEEN PRIORITIZED.
BUT WHAT ABOUT EVEN BRINGING IN LATERAL OFFICERS TO THE
DEPARTMENT AND MAKING SURE THAT WE'RE NOT BRINGING IN OFFICERS
WHO HAVE HISTORY OF MISCONDUCT OF MISTREATMENT?
>> SO WE HAVE FAR MORE LATERAL OFFICERS THAT APPLY TO COME
OVER TO OUR DEPARTMENT THAN WE ACTUALLY END UP HIRING FOR THE
REASONS THAT YOU JUST SPOKE ABOUT.
>> SO LATERAL OFFICERS REALLY GIVES US A GLIMPSE INTO HOW
SOMEBODY ACTUALLY DOES THE JOB BECAUSE THESE ARE NOT PEOPLE
THAT WE'RE TRYING TO FIGURE OUT HOW THEY MIGHT BE A POLICE
OFFICER. LATERALS HAVE BEEN POLICE
OFFICERS BEFORE. SO THEIR BODY OF WORK AND ALL
OF THEIR ISSUES AND TRIUMPHS IS OBVIOUSLY OF MAJOR INTEREST TO
THE DEPARTMENT. WE ARE INCREDIBLY SELECTIVE
ABOUT THE ONES WE TAKE. >> WE ARE TRYING TO WORK WITH
LATERAL OFFICERS IN THE SENSE OF I DON'T WANT TO SAY
HEADHUNTING BUT I'M GOING TO HEADHUNTING ONES THAT ARE NOT
NECESSARILY LOOKING TO LEAVE THEIR AGENCY IS BECAUSE QUITE
FRANKLY THOSE ARE THE ONES THAT WE'RE INTERESTED IN.
THOSE ARE GOOD POLICE OFFICERS WHO THE THOUGHT HASN'T CROSSED
THEIR MIND TO GO ANYWHERE ELSE AND MANY OF THEM HAVE VERY
WELL-ESTABLISHED, EXCELLENT CAREERS.
THAT'S WHAT WE'RE AFTER. >> A LOT OF TIMES WHEN PEOPLE
ARE LOOKING AND THIS IS NOT A BLANKET STATEMENT BUT LOOKING
TO LEAVE AN AGENCY, WE REALLY HAVE TO LOOK, YOU KNOW, BEYOND
THE SURFACE OF THIS TO UNDERSTAND THE WHY FOR THAT
WHICH LEADS US TO A FAR GREATER NUMBER OF LATERAL APPLICANTS
THAN ACTUAL HIRES. >> ANOTHER DEPARTMENT HAS
REPORTED TO ADDRESSING A GOOD NUMBER OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS
IN FACT MOST OF THEM AND AS REPORTED NOW REMAINING AND I
KNOW ONE OF THE THINGS YOU SAID AROUND SUCCESS WAS NOT HAVING
ENOUGH OFFICERS TO BE ABLE TO ACHIEVE SUCCESS IN THOSE
REMAINING NINE AREAS. >> IF I'M INTERPRETING
CORRECTLY, YOU'RE SPEAKING ABOUT THAT BULLET POINT ON THE
LAST SLIDE. >> WILL YOU LIST SOME OF THE
REASONS AND ONE SAYS SUSTAINABILITY DEPENDS ON FULLY
STAFFED DEPARTMENT. >> I THINK SUSTAINABILITY ABOUT
THE ENTIRETY OF THE 272 RECOMMENDATIONS THE NINE ITSELF
REALLY DOES DEPEND ON A CIO THE DATA TEAMS WORKING TOGETHER DGO
ABOUT DATA INTEGRITY AND DATA GOVERNANCE.
SO THEY DO RELY ON ADDITIONAL ITEMS AND FACTORS BUT NOT
NECESSARILY SWORN MEMBERS. I THINK SUSTAINABILITY FOR ALL
OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS DO DEPEND ON ENSURING THAT NOT
ONLY WITH PATROL BUT ALSO CIVILIAN STAFF WHERE WE CAN
CAPITALIZE ON THEIR UNIQUE SKILL SETS TO GET THINGS DONE.
>> AND I'M JUST INTERESTED HOW THE DEPARTMENT CAN REPORT THIS
ACHIEVE SUCCESS WITH THE TEAM THAT YOU HAVE IN PLACE BUT
WOULDN'T BE ABLE TO SUSTAIN IT WITH THE SAME TEAM.
>> WE'RE NOT REPORTING ACHIEVED SUCCESS AS IT RELATES TO
SUSTAINABILITY AT THIS MOMENT. WE ARE SETTING UP A NEW SYSTEM
NOW THAT WE HAVE ESTABLISHED AND THIS HAPPENED IN AUGUST
AND THE DETERMINATION THAT SIERRA WOULDN'T FALL UNDER
POLICY. SO REALLY WE'RE AT THIS STAGE
KIND OF 4 OR 5 WHEN IT COMES TO PROJECT PHASES OF MONITORING
AND THEN PROJECT CLOSURE. SO ONCE WE DETERMINE HOW TO
MOVE FORWARD WE REALLY WANT TO MEASURE ALL OF EVERY SINGLE
RECOMMENDATION THAT HAS BEEN IMPLEMENTED.
THIS ISN'T JUST WITH THE NINE WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO GET A
SYSTEM IN PLACE TO REVIEW ALL OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS THAT
HAVE BEEN IMPLEMENTED AND THEN MEASURE WHETHER THEY ARE
SUCCESSFUL. SOME OF THEM ARE QUALITATIVE,
SOME OF THEM ARE QUANTITATIVE SO SOME CAN BE MEASURED QUITE
EASILY. SOME WILL BE MEASURED IN A
FLEXIBLE WAY. BUT NOW THAT WE HAVE WE KNOW
WHERE IT'S GOING TO LIVE NOW WE KNOW HOW TO MOVE FORWARD WITH
IT. >> AND WHAT'S THE OBSTACLE
IN HIRING THE CIO THAT IS REALLY STAFFING IS ENSURING
THAT WE HAVE THE STAFF TO DETERMINE THAT THEY CAN LOOK AT
ALL OF THE ITEMS AND WORK WITH THE DEPARTMENT WIDE ISSUES
BALLISTIC OBSTACLE WHY DON'T YOU HAVE ONE?
>> SO WE ARE WORKING TO HIRE A NEW ONE SO THAT ANNOUNCEMENT
WILL BE OUT. WE HAD A PREVIOUS CIO WE ARE
GOING IN A DIFFERENT DIRECTION AND I WOULD EXPECT IN THE NEXT
COUPLE OF WEEKS THE JOB LISTING WILL BE POSTED.
WE'RE DOING HOPEFULLY A NATIONWIDE RECRUITMENT AS IT
RELATES TO THIS BECAUSE IT'S A CRITICAL CRITICAL POSITION FOR
THE POLICE DEPARTMENT NOT JUST AS IT RELATES TO CRY BUT JUST
EFFICIENCY IN GENERAL AND HOW WE CAN DO MORE WITH LESS AT THE
MOMENT. >> THANK YOU.
I DON'T HAVE ANY MORE QUESTIONS.
PRESIDENT MM. ALL RIGHT.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE PRESENTATION.
APPRECIATE IT. I HAD A QUESTION ABOUT, YOU
KNOW, A FEW YEARS AGO SAN FRANCISCO STANDARD DID AN
ANALYSIS OF STOPS AND FOUND THAT THERE WAS ONE I MEAN THERE
WAS ONE KNOWN INSTANCE OF AN OFFICER AND THE CASE WAS
INVESTIGATED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF POLICE ACCOUNTABILITY
BASICALLY UNDERREPORTING UM BASICALLY INFLATING THE NUMBERS
OF PEOPLE STOPPED UH MORE THAN A THOUSAND PEOPLE IDENTIFIED AS
WHITE BY THIS OFFICER. UM AND STANDARD ALSO FOUND THAT
SEVERAL OTHER OFFICERS HAD IN THE MAJORITY OF THEIR STOPS
IDENTIFIED ONE INDIVIDUAL FEW INDIVIDUALS WITH MULTIPLE
RACIAL CATEGORIES. >> AND THIS ALL SERVES TO
OBSCURE THE STOPS OF PREDOMINANTLY LATINO AND BLACK
UH, PEOPLE BEING STOPPED. >> AND SO I JUST WONDER WHAT
HAS BEEN DONE SINCE THEN TO CORRECT FOR THIS.
>> UM, PRACTICE OF FUDGING NUMBERS WHETHER THAT'S
DISCIPLINE OR SOMETHING ELSE BECAUSE THE DATA THAT WE HAVE
IS ONLY AS GOOD AS UM WHAT'S BEING INPUT INTO THE SYSTEM?
>> YEAH, WE WHOLEHEARTEDLY AGREE.
OBVIOUSLY THOSE OFFICER THAT DID NOT GO I'M DEALT WITH BY
THE DEPARTMENT AND I WILL LEAVE IT THERE.
BUT I THINK NOW THERE'S LIKE AUDITING LOOKING FOR IF ANY OF
THOSE PATTERNS PERSIST AND ANY OTHER YOU KNOW WITH ANY OTHER
OFFICER RIGHT NOW IN THEIR WORK PRODUCT.
SO IT'S NOT THAT THE DEPARTMENT IS TURNING A BLIND EYE TO THAT.
>> ADDITIONALLY TO MAKE SURE THAT OFFICERS JOGGING THEIR
MEMORIES THAT THEY DO THEIR STOPS BECAUSE I THINK THAT
SOMETIMES THAT CAN BE FORGOTTEN ABOUT WE'RE ACTUALLY IN THE
PROCESS OF ADDING A CHECKBOX ON OUR INCIDENT REPORTS THAT SAYS
YOU KNOW, THE STOP WAS DONE AS JUST ANOTHER EXTRA LAYER.
SO THERE'S BEEN MANY THINGS THAT HAVE BEEN PUT IN PLACE TO
TRY TO PREVENT THAT FROM HAPPENING AGAIN.
AND ALSO IT'S PRETTY WIDELY KNOWN THROUGHOUT THE DEPARTMENT
THAT THIS INCIDENT OCCURRED AND THAT THERE WERE
CONSEQUENCES. AND THAT HAS HOPEFULLY WILL BE
FOR THE FUTURE A DETERRENT. >> IN ADDITION TO THE THINGS I
JUST MENTIONED. >> AND HAVE WE SEEN A DECREASE
? IT'S AN OBVIOUSLY INFLATED
NUMBERS. >> ANY.
YES, I WOULD SAY THAT WE HAVEN'T SEEN A SIMILAR
SITUATION AS THE ONE THAT YOU'VE JUST DESCRIBED.
SO AND THEN ANY OTHER ONES WOULD AGAIN BE AND WE'RE
TALKING THE DISCIPLINARY ARENA AT THAT POINT.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANKS. >> CAN I ASK JUST TO WHAT
EXTENT COULD TECHNOLOGY AUTOMATE TRAFFIC ENFORCEMENT?
I KNOW THAT WE HAVE HAD RED LIGHT CAMERAS I THINK FOR 20
YEARS. WE'VE IMPLEMENTED I THINK 33 OR
WE'VE INTERVENED AND IMPLEMENTED SPEED
ENFORCEMENT CAMERAS AT I BELIEVE 33 LOCATIONS.
THAT'S ONLY BECAUSE THE LEGISLATURE IS LETTING US DO
THAT MUCH. BUT WHO KNOWS WHAT THEY WILL
ALLOW US TO DO IN THE FUTURE. AND I'M JUST I'M NOT EVEN
CERTAIN IF THERE'S THINGS THAT WE'RE ALLOWED TO USE OR NOT
ALLOWED TO USE. BUT GIVEN THE STAFFING
CHALLENGES THAT WE HAVE, HOW TO WHAT EXTENT COULD WE JUST
AUTOMATE ALL THIS? >> I THINK THAT WELL YOU KNOW,
I LOVE TO TALK TRAFFIC SUPERVISOR SO BRACE YOURSELVES
NOW. BUT I MEAN OTHER STATES ARE
LOOKING IN JUST BEYOND DOING RED LIGHT CAMERA VIOLATIONS
AND SPEED. THEY'RE USING IT FOR THINGS
LIKE NO LEFT TURNS. AGAIN, THAT'S NOT MAINSTREAM.
THERE ARE OTHER VIOLATIONS OF COURSE TOO.
BUT I'M JUST I COULD GO ON FOR DAYS AND I WON'T BUT I THINK TO
THE GREATEST EXTENT POSSIBLE THAT WE CAN LEVERAGE TECHNOLOGY
TO PICK UP THOSE ADDITIONAL VIOLATIONS.
IT JUST EXPANDS THE WORK FORCE. I MEAN CURRENTLY THE TRAFFIC
COMPANY HAS I WOULD SAY NOW MAYBE 18 BECAUSE THEY'VE GOT A
FEW EXTRA MOTORCYCLE OFFICERS WHO ARE REALLY HAVE ALWAYS
AGAIN SHOULDERED YOU KNOW, THE BULK OF THE BURDEN FOR TRAFFIC
ENFORCEMENT IN THE CITY BUT FOR A CITY OF THIS SIZE WITH THE
AMOUNT OF PEOPLE THAT NOT ONLY LIVE HERE BUT THAT COME IN ON A
DAILY BASIS TO WORK SORELY INADEQUATE FOR THE ENFORCEMENT
THAT WE NEED DONE. SO I THINK THAT WE SHOULD
REALLY LOOK INTO ANYTHING AND EVERYTHING THAT COULD BE
DONE HERE. AGAIN, DRONES HAVE BEEN USED
IN CERTAIN INSTANCES AS IT RELATES TO THIS BUT MANY
FURTHER DISCUSSIONS HAVE TO TO COME.
BUT I THINK THERE'S ABSOLUTELY THE POTENTIAL FOR TECHNOLOGY TO
ASSIST. WE'RE JUST PERHAPS NOT EVEN
BEHIND BUT THE STATES THAT ARE DOING THOSE ADDITIONAL
VIOLATIONS ARE REALLY ON THE CUTTING EDGE OF THIS.
AND MOST STATES I THINK ARE IN A SIMILAR SITUATION AS
CALIFORNIA. >> GREAT.
OKAY. AND I JUST I APPRECIATE THAT.
YOU KNOW, I KNOW THAT THE DATA CHALLENGES THIS WAS SOMETHING
THAT DURING MY TWO YEARS IN THE DEPARTMENT WAS INCREDIBLY
FRUSTRATING TO ME. >> SO I'M GLAD THAT IS
SOMETHING THAT'S BEING DONE. I WILL SAY I DO WANT TO
APPRECIATE THE WORK OF THE DEPARTMENT AND HONESTLY THE
WORK OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND ITS OVERSIGHT
ROLE ON POLICE REFORM. THIS GOES BACK FOR THOSE WHO
MAY NOT KNOW THAT TO PRESIDENT OBAMA'S TASK FORCE ON 21ST
CENTURY POLICING AT A REALLY CRITICAL JUNCTURE IN 2017 WHEN
DONALD TRUMP PULLED THE PLUG ON POLICE REFORM FOR 16 CITIES,
SAN FRANCISCO WAS THE ONLY ONE THAT KEPT GOING.
>> BUT ONE OF THE THINGS THAT REALLY IMPRESSED ME WHEN I WAS
WORKING WITH BILL SCOTT ON SOME OF THIS IS THAT REFORM IS NEVER
DONE AND WHEN WE GET TO 272 WE GOT TO KEEP THIS GOING AND WE
PROBABLY HAVE TO KEEP THESE HEARINGS.
THAT'S REFORM IS SOMETHING THAT IT NEEDS TO BE PART OF THE
CULTURE. THERE WERE ALWAYS LOOKING AT
IMPROVING. SO THANKS FOR YOUR WORK
AND THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP ON THIS.
>> SUPERVISOR ONE SUPERVISOR WALTON.
ANY FINAL THOUGHTS FOR PUBLIC COMMENT?
>> PRESIDENT WHEN WE CAN GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT AND YOU I SAY
SOMETHING. >> ALL RIGHT, GREAT.
LET'S OPEN OPEN PUBLIC COMMENT ON OUR 3 P.M. HEARING ON LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS REGARDING
LAW ENFORCEMENT PRACTICES. THIS IS NOT GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. THIS IS PUBLIC COMMENT ON THIS
HEARING. >> DON'T WORRY.
>> OKAY. SO ABSOLUTE INCOMPETENCE
AND ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE TO WHICH TO MAKE THEM GIVE YOU THE
DATA IT WANTS. >> OBVIOUSLY SINCE IT'S IN THE
CONTROL ROOM ARE YOU OKAY? SO YOU ARE TALKING ABOUT
SYSTEMIC SUSTAINABILITY OF INSTITUTIONALIZED CHILD
TRAFFICKING. >> THAT'S IT.
SO YES, ALL THE REST IS ABSOLUTE NONSENSE.
>> IT MEANS THAT YOU ARE PART OF THE GAME A BIG PROBLEM
BECAUSE MEANWHILE KIDS ARE BEING TRAFFICKED.
>> THE EVIDENCE OF INSTITUTIONALIZED STATE
TRAFFICKING IS THE ABSOLUTE SILENCE FROM THE GOVERNMENT
AND ALL THE MAJOR SYSTEM. >> THAT'S IT.
SO TRUST ME IF YOU ADDRESS THIS YOU GET ABSOLUTELY SPIKED FROM
EVERYONE IN THE BLACK COMMUNITY AMONG OTHERS BECAUSE THEY ARE
FED UP WITH THIS SILENCE. >> YOU'RE GOING TO YOU'RE GOING
TO GET ABSOLUTE RESPECT, TRUST ME MUCH LESS PETTY CRIMES
AND ALL THIS. DO WHAT YOU CAN.
I'M HERE FOR YOU UP TO A CERTAIN POINT.
>> PLEASE. THE CHILDREN THAT SHOULD GO
NEXT SPEAKER VISIT WOULD ANYBODY ELSE LIKE TO SPEAK ON
ITEM 34 THE COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE?
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS RICHARD S.G.
PETERSON, BOARD PRESIDENT AND NEW BOARD MEMBER.
LONG CONGRATULATIONS FOR YOUR APPOINTMENT AND I WILL BE
PUSHING TO FIND OUT WHAT YOUR POSITION ON PARCEL TAXES IS.
BUT THAT'S NOT REALLY WHERE I'M GOING TO TALK ABOUT TODAY.
>> TODAY I'M WONDERING WHY WE OPENED THIS MEETING CLAIMING
THAT RON ALONI LAND AND WE HAVE NOT ONLY THAT THIS BUILDING
WHICH IS BEAUTIFUL BUT WE HAVE THE DOWNTOWN THE SAN FRANCISCO
CENTER MALL WHICH HAS ONE OF THE MOST BEAUTIFUL DOMES IN THE
CITY AND I'VE ALWAYS WONDERED WHY THAT PROPERTY CAN'T BE SOLD
TO THE ALONI TRIBE WHO PROBABLY COULD COME UP WITH THE MONEY
SOONER OR LATER AND THEN RUN A CASINO THERE.
I'VE SUGGESTED A NIGHTCLUB KIND OF A LAS VEGAS STYLE NIGHT
NIGHTCLUB. BUT WHAT ABOUT GOING THROUGH
THE WORK IF DONALD TRUMP CAN GET THINGS DONE IN 100 DAYS WE
SHOULD BE ABLE TO PUSH IT THROUGH BRIEFLY LOOKED AT THE
LAWS ON ON OPERATING A CASINO AND AND IF YOU REALLY HAD THE
WILL TO DO IT YOU COULD DO IT ANYWAY THANK YOU FOR ALLOWING
ME TO SPEAK THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ARE THERE ANY ADDITIONAL SPEAKERS?
SEEING NONE, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT BENJAMIN AND THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR SITTING
IN THIS COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK DC
JONES AND MANAGER STEPHENS FOR YOUR PRESIDENT'S MOTION.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT ONE WE DO THANK THE DEPARTMENT FOR
ACHIEVING AND COMPLETING MOST OF THE RECOMMENDATIONS.
BUT I KNOW AS A CITY WE STILL HAVE A LONG WAY TO GO UNTIL
EVERYONE OBVIOUSLY IN THE CITY FEELS COMFORTABLE BEING ABLE TO
MOVE AROUND. >> THERE'S A LOT OF WORK STILL
TO BE DONE WITH BIAS AND POLICE STOPS, BIAS AND ARRESTS FOR
CERTAIN OFFENSES OR PERCEIVED OFFENSES AND I WANT TO THANK
THE DEPARTMENT FOR WORKING OBVIOUSLY WITH COMMUNITY ON
THESE THINGS. BUT THESE ARE GOALS THAT WE
STILL HAVE TO REACH. AND SO WE WILL CONTINUE TO
PROVIDE OUR ROLE AS OVERSIGHT BODY IN TERMS OF MAKING SURE
THAT THESE CONTINUE TO BE ADDRESSED.
AND AGAIN APPRECIATE EVERYONE FOR HOSTING THIS COMMITTEE THE
WHOLE TODAY AND WOULD LIKE TO CONTINUE THIS ITEM TO OUR
TUESDAY MAY 12TH MEETING. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO FIRST ONE HAS MADE A MOTION TO CONTINUE THIS HEARING TO
TUESDAY MAY 12TH. >> IS THERE THEIR SECOND
SECONDED BY FIELDER? MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON THE MOTION TO CONTINUE ITEM 34 TO MAY 12TH, 2026.
>> IS THAT CORRECT? MAY 12TH.
>> YEAH. MAY 12TH.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR BENJAMIN I MENDHAM AND I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I SUPERVISOR WANG I HUANG I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY THERE ARE LEBANESE.
>> THE MOTION PASSES AND THIS HEARING IS CONTINUED TO MAY
12TH. MADAM CLERK NOW LET'S GO TO
COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL ITEM 35 ITEMS 35 THROUGH 38
WERE CONSIDERED. >> NOPE NO I THINK WE'RE OFF TO
35 ALONE AND THEN 36 3038 I MAKE THE STATEMENT FIRST ITEM
35 THROUGH 38 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY
DECEMBER 1ST, 2025 AND RECOMMENDED TO THE FULL
BOARD TODAY ITEM 35 IT IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING
CODE TO EXPAND THE BOUNDARIES OF THE CENTRAL NEIGHBORHOODS.
LARGE RESIDENTS STUDY AND TO APPLY ITS CONTROLS TO ALL LOTS
WITHIN THE STUDY TO DELETE THE CURRENT HEIGHTS LARGE RESIDENCE
STUDY AND MERGE IT INTO THE CENTRAL NEIGHBORHOODS LARGE
RESIDENCE A STUDY AMENDING THE ZONING MAP TO REFLECT THE
DELETION AND BOUNDARY EXPANSION AND MAKE THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> APOLOGIES MADAM CLERK I
JUMPED THE GUN. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM
35 AN ITEM 35 SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MAN'S WOMAN HI MEN'S EYES
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WHILE I HUANG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EITHER
LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THIS ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING MADAM CLERK NOW LET'S CALL IT PLEASE CALL ITEM 3638
TOGETHER ITEM NUMBER 36 IT IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
GENERAL PLAN TO REVISE THE URBAN DESIGN ELEMENT COMMERCE
AND INDUSTRY ELEMENT TRANSPORTATION ELEMENT BALBOA
PARK STATION AREA PLAN GLEN PARK COMMUNITY PLAN MARKET
IN OCTAVIA AREA PLAN NORTHEASTERN WATERFRONT PLAN
VENICE AVENUE AREA PLAN WESTERN SOMA AREA PLAN THE WESTERN
SHORELINE AREA PLAN DOWNTOWN AREA PLAN AND LAND USE INDEX TO
IMPLEMENT THE FAMILY HOUSING ZONING PROGRAM BY ADJUSTING
GUIDELINES REGARDING BUILDING HEIGHTS, DENSITY DESIGN
AND OTHER MATTERS AMENDING THE CITY'S LOCAL COASTAL PROGRAM
AND MAKING THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
ITEM 37 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ZONING MAP TO
IMPLEMENT THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN BY AMENDING THE ZONING USE
DISTRICT MAPS TO RECLASSIFY CERTAIN PROPERTIES AMENDING THE
HEIGHT AND BULK MAP TO RECLASSIFY PROPERTIES, CHANGE
THE HEIGHT LIMITS ON CERTAIN LOTS AND DESIGNATING VARIOUS
PARCELS TO BE INCLUDED IN THE S.F. MTA STUDY AMENDING THE
LOCAL COASTAL PROGRAM TO RECLASSIFY CERTAIN PROPERTIES
AND DESIGNATE ONE PARCEL AS PART OF THE S.F. MTA STUDY
AND MAKING APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AT ITEM 38 IS AN ORDINANCE
AMENDING THE PLANNING CODE TO CREATE THE HOUSING CHOICE SAN
FRANCISCO PROGRAM MODIFY HEIGHT AND BULK LIMITS REQUIRE ONLY
BUILDINGS TALLER THAN 85FT IN CERTAIN DISTRICTS TO REDUCE
GROUND LEVEL WIND CURRENTS CREATE THE RESIDENTIAL TRANSIT
ORIENTED COMMERCIAL DISTRICT IMPLEMENT THE METROPOLITAN
TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION'S TRANSIT ORIENTED COMMUNITIES
POLICY, REVISE OFF STREET PARKING AND CURB CUT
OBLIGATIONS CITYWIDE. CREATE THE S.F. MTA PERMIT
BUSINESSES DISPLACED BY NEW CONSTRUCTION TO RELOCATE WITHIN
A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION AND REDUCE USABLE OPEN SPACE
AND BICYCLE PARKING REQUIREMENTS FOR SENIOR HOUSING
AMENDING THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS CODE REGARDING THE
BOARD OF APPEALS REVIEW OF PERMITS AMENDING THE LOCAL
COASTAL PROGRAM TO IMPLEMENT THE HOUSING CHOICE SAN
FRANCISCO PROGRAM AND MAKING THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> CHAIR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND THANK
YOU COLLEAGUES. >> THIS HAS BEEN A VERY LONG
AND ENGAGED PROCESS WITH FOR APPEARANCES BEFORE THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE. I WANT TO THANK MY COLLEAGUES
ON THE LADIES AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE
FOR ALL OF THEIR HARD WORK AND TO THE STAFF AT THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND PRIOR TO THIS COMING TO THE LAND USE
AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE OF COURSE WE HAD HUNDREDS OF
MEETINGS WITH COMMUNITY STAKEHOLDERS AND NEIGHBORHOOD
STAKEHOLDERS BEFORE WE EVEN APPROVED THE HOUSING ELEMENT
AND THROUGH OUR LAST MAYORAL ADMINISTRATION AND NOW THIS ONE
I HAVE ALWAYS BEEN SUPPORTIVE OF BRINGING MORE HOUSING
OPTIONS TO MY DISTRICT IN WHILE I WISH THERE COULD BE MORE THAT
WE COULD DO AS A CITY, I THINK THAT THIS REZONING PACKAGE HAS
IMPROVED SIGNIFICANTLY FROM WHERE IT WAS INTRODUCED BY OUR
FORMER MAYOR AND OUR CURRENT MAYOR IN 1978 WE DOWNTOWN THE
WEST SIDE AND SOME OF THE NORTH SIDE OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND CONCENTRATED ALL DEVELOP INTO THE EAST SIDE
NEIGHBORHOODS TO THE MISSION THE BAYVIEW SYLMAR DEMOLITION
PROTECTIONS CAME DECADES LATER IN 2008 IN RESPONSE IN DUE TO
TENDER RIGHTS ADVOCACY ON THE WEST AND NORTH OF THE CITY
BUILT VERY LITTLE HOUSING AND THE ACCOMPANYING
INFRASTRUCTURE TO SUPPORT THAT HOUSING MARKET RATE, HOUSING
AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING, RENTAL HOUSING.
BUT ALSO FREEZING THE RESIDENTIAL PATTERNS OF 1978
AND EVEN EARLIER UNDER THE MESSAGING OF FIGHTING AGAINST
THE MANHATTAN IZATION OF SAN FRANCISCO LED TO A MORE
SEGREGATED CITY BY INCOME BY RACE.
EVERY SOCIAL DETERMINANTS OF HEALTH INFANT MORTALITY RATES,
PUBLIC SCHOOL TEST SCORES ALL THESE THINGS ARE BETTER ON THE
WEST SIDE AND THE NORTH SIDE OF OUR CITY THAN ON THE EAST SIDE
OF TOWN. SOME COLLEAGUES HAVE TALKED
ABOUT THIS PITTING THE WEST SIDE, THIS REZONING MAP PITTING
THE WEST SIDE AGAINST THE EAST SIDE OF SAN FRANCISCO.
I WOULD SAY WE DID THAT IN 1978 IN THIS REZONING.
WE ARE BUILDING A MORE EQUITABLE AND ACCESSIBLE
TOMORROW. THIS PLAN IS NOT PERFECT.
IT HAS BEEN MADE BETTER BECAUSE OF THE EFFORTS OF THE
LEGISLATIVE BRANCH WORKING WITH THE ADMINISTRATION REZONING
ITSELF WILL NOT SOLVE OUR HOUSING CRISIS OR OUR
AFFORDABILITY CRISIS BUT IT IS AN ABSOLUTELY NECESSARY STEP
TOWARDS MEETING OUR COMPLIANCE WITH THE STATE AND MEETING OUR
OBLIGATIONS FOR OUR ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT IN OUR TOMORROWS SO
THAT WE CAN MOVE AHEAD WITH OTHER IMPORTANT STRATEGIES TO
JUMPSTART MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING, TO FUND IT, TO
INCENTIVIZE THE PROJECTS THAT WE WANT TO SEE AND TO ENSURE
THAT TENANTS AND SMALL BUSINESSES ARE PROVIDED THE
STRONGEST PROTECTIONS AGAINST ANY BAD ACTORS.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN. COLLEAGUES, I'M A STRONG
BELIEVER IN THIS MAP AND THIS LEGISLATION.
IN MY VIEW THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN IS THE LINCHPIN OF HOUSING
AFFORDABILITY A STRATEGY THAT SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS TO SURVIVE
INTO THE 21ST CENTURY. IT'S A THOUGHTFUL APPROACH THAT
WILL CREATE MORE HOUSING, ENABLE MORE SMALL BUSINESSES TO
THRIVE AND ENABLE MORE SAN FRANCISCANS TO STAY SAN
FRANCISCANS GENERATION AFTER GENERATION.
IT WILL HELP FACILITATE NEW OPPORTUNITIES IN NEIGHBORHOODS
CITYWIDE WHILE MEANINGFULLY PROTECTING RENT CONTROL
AND DEMOLITION PROTECTIONS IN PRIORITY EQUITY AREAS.
THIS PACKAGE BALANCES OUR OBLIGATION BEGINS WITH
REASONABLE LONG OVERDUE CHANGES SO WE DON'T HAVE TO SEE FRIENDS
AND FAMILY MEMBERS GET PRICED OUT OF OUR CITY.
I WANT TO THANK ALL OF MY COLLEAGUES WHO HAVE OFFERED
AMENDMENTS IN THIS LENGTHY PROCESS TO A PLAN TO ADDRESS
MANY OF OUR SHARED PRIORITIES. THE INCORPORATED AMENDMENTS
STRENGTHENED THIS LEGISLATIVE PACKAGE AND WE'RE LEADING WITH
OUR SAN FRANCISCO VALUES I THINK BY PROTECTING RENT
CONTROL, OPENING UP NEW PATHWAYS TO AFFORDABILITY
AND ENCOURAGING HOUSING NEAR TRANSIT.
I ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK CHAIR MELGAR FOR HER HEROIC
WORK THROUGH THE LAND USE COMMITTEE.
I AM AWARE THAT I PROBABLY REPRESENT THE MOST YIMBY SAFE
YOU KNOW HOUSING FRIENDLY DENSITY FRIENDLY DISTRICT
IN SAN FRANCISCO WITH NEIGHBORHOODS THAT HAVE
PRODUCED A LOT OF HOUSING AND QUITE CANDIDLY ARE EXCITED
TO SEE MORE. SO I KNOW THAT'S NOT THE CASE
WITH MANY OF THE NEIGHBORHOODS REPRESENTED BY MY COLLEAGUES.
THERE'S A LOT OF COMPETING INTERESTS, A LOT OF COMPETING
SUPERVISOR DISTRICTS, A LOT OF COMPETING NEIGHBORHOODS.
I'M JUST REALLY IMPRESSED. CHAIR MALKA AT THE WORK THAT
YOU HAVE DONE TO BRING THIS ALL TOGETHER AND HOPEFULLY LAND
THIS PLANE YOU KNOW, IN TIME. SO GREAT JOB TO ALL OF MY
COLLEAGUES. THANK YOU PLANNING BUT I DID
WANT TO JUST SAY ESPECIALLY TO SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR TRAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENDELSOHN.
COLLEAGUES, I DO SHARE THE SENTIMENTS THAT IT'S BEEN A
LONG TIME COMING AND THERE ARE MANY STEPS TO TODAY AND THROUGH
THIS JOURNEY AND DEFINITELY WANT TO THANK CHAIR MELGAR FOR
HER EFFORT AND LEADERSHIP DURING THIS PROCESS AND ALSO
WANT TO THANK LANGLEY'S COMMITTEE FOR THEIR WORK
AND TIME SPENT AS WELL AS OUR PLANNING COMMISSION
AND PLANNING STAFF IN PARTNERSHIP WITH COMMUNITY
ADVOCATES AND STAKEHOLDERS ACROSS THE CITY.
WE'VE BEEN WORKING IN GOOD FAITH TO IMPROVE THE PROPOSED
UP ZONING PLAN TO ENSURE THAT WE MEDICATE RISK OF SPECULATIVE
REAL ESTATE INVESTMENT AND DISPLACEMENTS, ATTENDANCE
AND SMALL BUSINESSES. MANY OF OUR COMMUNITY ADVOCATES
AND STAKEHOLDERS AND MYSELF INCLUDED I HAVE BEEN SUPPORTIVE
OF BUILDING MORE HOUSING THAT SAN FRANCISCANS CAN AFFORD
AND WE PUSH FOR POLICIES TO BUILD HOUSING WITHOUT
DISPLACEMENT. PRIORITIZING OUR EFFORTS
IN IDENTIFYING VACANT AND SURPLUS LANDS
AND ADVOCATING FOR BOND DOLLARS TAX CREDITS AND STATE
AND FEDERAL GRANTS SO THAT WE CAN BUILD MORE HOUSING PEOPLE
SAN FRANCISCANS NEED HOUSING BOTH EXISTING AND NEW.
WE KNOW THAT OUR EXISTING HOUSING STOCK ESPECIALLY RENT
CONTROL HOUSING IS OUR MOST VALUABLE AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING
STOCK. >> THIS IS WHY COLLEAGUES I
THINK EVEN TODAY AS OF TODAY I REALLY HOPE TO ARE STILL MAKING
THIS ONE MORE EFFORT TO ENSURE WE PROTECT TENANTS AND DRAW A
LINE ON ONE OF SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST IMPORTANT VALUES OUR RENT
CONTROL HOUSING UNITS AND THE LAND USE COMMITTEE.
>> THANKS TO CHAIR MAL GAR AND THE COMMITTEE AND THAT YOU
ALL HAVE SOLIDIFY RENT CONTROL UNITS AS AN IMPORTANT
AFFORDABLE HOUSING STOCK AND ENSURE BUILDINGS WITH THREE
OR MORE CAN FOR RENT CONTROL UNITS ARE PROTECTED.
FOR THAT WE'RE REALLY GRATEFUL BECAUSE YOUR AMENDMENT HAS CHIO
ABOUT 18,000 RENT CONTROL UNITS FROM DEMOLITION.
WE DO KNOW THOUGH WE'RE STILL LEAVING APPROXIMATELY 20,000
RENT CONTROL UNITS BEHIND PUTTING 20,000 HOUSEHOLDS AT
RISK OF DISPLACEMENTS AND DEMOLITION.
AND IT IS TRUE THAT MOST OF THEM ARE LOCATED ON THE WEST
SIDE ESPECIALLY IN THE RICHMOND 30% OF THOSE 20,000 A RENT
CONTROL UNITS ARE LOCATED IN THE RICHMOND THE DISTRICT
THAT I REPRESENT. SAN FRANCISCO IS A LEADER
IN TENANT PROTECTION AND WE HAVE TO STAND FIRM TO PROTECT
OUR EXISTING AFFORDABLE HOUSING STOCK.
SO COLLEAGUES FOR THAT ONE MORE TRY.
TODAY I AM MAKING A MOTION TO AMEND ITEM 38 FILE NUMBER
25070. AND THAT WITH THE GOAL IS TO
PROTECT ALL RENT CONTROL UNITS .
>> AND THE AMENDMENT IS GOING TO BE VERY SIMPLE
AND STRAIGHTFORWARD IS ON PAGE 13 LINE TEN.
>> AGAIN IT'S FOR THE ITEM 38 FILE NUMBER 25070.
COLLEAGUES ALSO THERE ARE ACTUALLY ELECTRONIC FILE
IN YOUR INBOX THROUGH EMAIL AS WELL AND SENT TO CALVIN YAN ON
OUR TEAM AT 2:02 P.M. TODAY. AND THEN SHOULD YOU SO THE
AMENDMENT SHOULD WE DECIDE TO APPROVE IT IT WILL READ AS SUCH
THAT THE CRITERIA UNDER THE LOCAL DENSITY PROGRAM WILL THEN
BE IS NOT LOCATED ON A SITE CONTAINING RESIDENTIAL UNITS
WHERE THE PROJECT WILL REQUIRE THE DEMOLITION AND OF
RESIDENTIAL USES THAT ARE SUBJECT TO THE RENT INCREASE
LIMITATION SET FORTH IN CHAPTER 37 OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE.
COLLEAGUES WITH THIS AMENDMENT WE WILL EFFECTIVELY PROTECT ALL
TENANTS CURRENTLY LIVING IN RENT CONTROL UNITS
THROUGHOUT THE CITY MANY OF WHOM WE KNOW TO BE WORKING
PEOPLE WHO CAN AFFORD TO LIVE IN OUR CITY BECAUSE THEY LIVE
IN RENT CONTROL UNITS. >> THEY ARE TEACHERS, NURSES,
FIRST RESPONDERS, BARTENDERS AND JANITORS AND MANY MORE ARE
IMMIGRANTS TRULY ARE THE WORKING PEOPLE THAT MAKE SAN
FRANCISCO THE GREAT CITY THAT IT IS TODAY.
AND I KNOW THIS TO BE TRUE BECAUSE THAT WAS MY MOTHER A
SINGLE MOTHER, AN IMMIGRANT LONG TIME WORKER IN CHINATOWN.
SHE WAS ABLE TO WORK AND LIVE IN CHINATOWN BORDERING NORTH
BEACH AREA BECAUSE OF THE RENT CONTROL UNITS WHERE SHE RESIDE
FOR THREE DECADES WHERE I GREW UP UNTIL SHE PASSED IN 2021
AND I AM WHO I AM TODAY AS A MEMBER OF THE BOARD RAISING MY
FAMILY IN RICHMOND BECAUSE OF THE STABLE RENT CONTROL HOUSING
I HAVE GROWING UP WITH SO COLLEAGUES I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR
SUPPORT IN THIS AMENDMENT. >> I DO WANT TO ALSO BE
TRANSPARENT AND BE CLEAR WITH THIS AMENDMENT SHOULD SHOULD IT
PASS WITH YOUR SUPPORT AND AMENDMENT?
I AM STILL NOT ABLE TO SUPPORT THIS PROPOSAL WHICH IS RARE FOR
ME BECAUSE TYPICALLY WHEN I CONTRIBUTE AND TO SAY THAT
LET'S LET'S MAKE AMENDMENTS TO A PLAN OR TO A LEGISLATION I
TEND TO HOPE THAT I COULD ALSO VOTE YES TO THAT PLAN OR A
LEGISLATION BUT I STILL CANNOT DO SO TODAY.
FOR ONE, I KNOW THAT WHILE WE'VE BEEN HAVING A LOT OF
THESE ONGOING CONVERSATION I DO UNDERSTAND THAT WHILE CHAIR
MELGAR AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AS WELL AS THE
MAYOR HAVE REALLY HAVE BEEN OPEN DIALOG AND HAVING THESE
CONVERSATION ABOUT WHAT CAN WE ACCEPT AS AS AMENDMENTS.
BUT I DO UNDERSTAND THAT THERE IS ALSO A STATE DEPARTMENT THAT
IS BEING INVOLVED AND HAVING MAKING DETERMINATION WHETHER
THESE AMENDMENTS AND A SAN FRANCISCO PLAN IS ACCEPTABLE TO
THE STATE STANDARD OR NOT. >> I'M DISAPPOINTED.
I'M DISAPPOINTED WHERE WE'RE AT.
I'M DISAPPOINTED THAT WE'RE DOING THIS BECAUSE WE BELIEVED
THAT IF WE DON'T THEN THERE WILL BE A BILL DOES RAMADI A
GREATER THREAT TO HOW WE DETERMINE OUR FATE AND OUR
FUTURE AND HOW WE PLAN AND BUILD OUR CITY?
>> I AM DISAPPOINTED THAT WE ARE NOT CHOOSING A PATH TO
FIGURE OUT A WAY TO EITHER NEGOTIATE OR FRANKLY EVEN FIGHT
SOME OF THESE MANDATES THAT ARE UNFUNDED AND WITHOUT A LOT OF
DATA OR CONFIRM AND INDEPENDENTLY VERIFY DATA.
SO WITH THAT THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN HAS MADE A
MOTION HAS BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN.
I WANT TO BEGIN BY APPRECIATING EVERYONE FOR THEIR HARD WORK ON
THIS PARTICULARLY THE MEMBERS OF THE LAND USE COMMITTEE.
CHAIR MELGAR. CHAIR MELGAR CHAIR MELGAR
AND SUPERVISORS MAHMUD AND CHEN.
I WANT TO GIVE A BIG THANKS TO MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE MICHELLE
ANDREWS FOR HER EXTENSIVE WORK ON THIS AND ALSO TO THE
DEDICATED STAFF AT PLANNING. THANKS AS WELL TO THE MANY,
MANY COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND GROUPS WHO SPENT
SIGNIFICANT TIME WORKING TO GIVE FEEDBACK AND SHAPE
AND IMPROVE THIS PLAN. THIS HAS INDEED BEEN A YEARS
LONG PROCESS. MUCH OF THE WORK ACTUALLY
STARTED BEFORE MANY OF US WERE IN THIS CHAMBER.
DEEP WORK HAS BEEN UNDERTAKEN TO CONSIDER COUNTLESS
AMENDMENTS. GIVEN THIS I WANT TO SAY
UPFRONT AT THIS POINT THAT I WILL NOT BE CONSIDERING ANY
AMENDMENTS INTRODUCED TODAY SO LATE IN THE PROCESS.
IN FACT I BELIEVE ANY ATTEMPTS TO MAKE AMENDMENTS AT THIS
POINT ARE MORE POLITICAL RATHER THAN SERIOUS IN NATURE.
TODAY I WILL BE CASTING MY VOTE IN SUPPORT OF THE FAMILY ZONING
PLAN. I'M DOING SO BECAUSE WHEN I RAN
FOR OFFICE I VOWED TO WORK EVERY DAY FOR A SAN FRANCISCO
THAT IS MORE AFFORDABLE AND MORE WELCOMING.
AND THIS PLAN ACHIEVES BOTH OF THOSE GOALS.
I LOVE SAN FRANCISCO AND I KNOW WE'RE ALL IN THIS ROOM BECAUSE
WE DO TOO. I BELIEVE THAT TO LOVE SAN
FRANCISCO IS TO WANT SO DEEPLY TO SHARE IT TO LET OTHERS HAVE
A CHANCE A CHANCE TO LIVE HERE WHETHER THAT MEANS COMING HERE
,PURSUING DREAMS OR SEEKING SANCTUARY OR TO STAY HERE
AND GROW OLD HERE TO GIVE YOUR CHILDREN OR GRANDCHILDREN A
CHANCE TO ALSO GROW UP IN THIS GREAT CITY.
I'M RAISING MY FAMILY IN A RENT CONTROLLED APARTMENT IN NORTH
BEACH. MY NEIGHBORS MY DISTRICT ARE
MAJORITY RENTERS. I REJECT THE NOTION THAT WE
HAVE TO CHOOSE BETWEEN BUILDING MORE HOMES AND PROTECTING
RENTERS. WE CAN DO BOTH.
AND THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT THIS PLAN DOES.
BY PACKAGING THE STRONGEST POSSIBLE TENANT IN DEMOLITION
PROTECTIONS WITH A PLAN TO ALLOW NEW HOMES
IN NEIGHBORHOODS THAT HAVE TYPICALLY EXCLUDE ADD
APARTMENTS AND MULTIFAMILY HOMES THIS VERY BODY AT A
SIMILAR QUESTION BEFORE THEM IN 1978.
BUT FOR THAT BOARD OF SUPERVISORS THE QUESTION WAS
WHETHER TO DOWN ZONE RATHER THAN TO UP ZONE.
THE 1978 DOWN ZONING RESULTED IN MAKING APARTMENT BUILDINGS
ILLEGAL IN LARGE SWATHS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND DECREASING THE
CAPACITY OF NEW HOMES BY NEARLY 200,000 UNITS.
NOT COINCIDENTALLY THE AREAS COVERED BY THE 1978 DOWN ZONING
LARGELY MATCHED THE AREAS WE ARE CONSIDERING UNDER TODAY'S
FAMILY ZONING PLAN. THE FINDINGS FROM THE 1978 DOWN
ZONING PLAN PREDICTED EXACTLY WHAT ENDED UP HAPPENING.
THEY WARNED OF DISPLACEMENT OF CERTAIN TYPES OF HOUSEHOLDS
THAT PRICES AND RENTS MAY BID UPWARDS AND HOUSEHOLDS BOTH
CURRENT AND PROSPECTIVE WOULD BE FORCED TO SEEK HOUSING
OUTSIDE OF SAN FRANCISCO. ADVERSELY AFFECTING AIR QUALITY
IF AUTOMOBILE USAGE INCREASES. >> ALL OF THOSE WARNINGS CAME
TRUE THAT 1978 BOARD MADE ITS DECISION AND WE'VE BEEN LIVING
WITH ITS CONSEQUENCES EVER SINCE.
THIS HOUSING CRISIS ISN'T A NATURAL PHENOMENON.
IT'S A POLICY CHOICE ONE THAT HAS BEEN EXACERBATED YEAR AFTER
YEAR EVICTION AFTER EVICTION BLOCKED HOUSING PROJECT AFTER
BLOCKED HOUSING PROJECT AND NOW NEARLY 50 YEARS AFTER THE
CITY'S 1978 TOWN ZONING. I THINK IT'S ABOUT TIME WE MADE
A DIFFERENT CHOICE. >> SOME HAVE MADE THIS PLAN OUT
TO BE ALL ABOUT FUTURISTIC TOWERS OR BIG CHANGES TO OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS. THAT'S NOT WHAT THIS IS.
IN MANY WAYS IT SIMPLY LEGALIZES WHAT WE USED TO ALLOW
IN OUR CITY. IN FACT, ONE STUDY SHOWED THAT
54% OF THE HOMES IN SAN FRANCISCO WOULD BE ILLEGAL TO
BUILD TODAY. THAT'S A FEW HUNDRED THOUSAND
OF OUR NEIGHBORS. MY OWN APARTMENT IN NORTH BEACH
WOULD BE ILLEGAL TO BUILD TODAY BECAUSE IT IS TOO DENSE.
YES, WE LITERALLY HAVE A LAW ON THE BOOKS TODAY THAT SAYS THE
THREE FAMILIES THAT LIVE IN MY BUILDING ARE TOO MANY AND ONLY
TWO SHOULD BE ALLOWED TO LIVE THERE.
INSTEAD, BY TODAY'S STANDARDS THE DENSITY DECONTROL CHANGES
IN THIS PLAN WOULD CHANGE THAT AND WOULD SIMPLY ALLOW THREE
FAMILIES TO LIVE WITHIN THE SAME 40 FOOT HEIGHT LIMIT ONCE
AGAIN AS WE TAKE THIS VOTE. I THINK ABOUT ONE OF THE FEW
HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS BUILT IN DISTRICT THREE IN RECENT
YEARS. BROADWAY COVE AN AFFORDABLE
HOUSING SITE STEPS AWAY FROM THE EMBARCADERO.
IN 2021 A LOTTERY WAS HELD FOR 93 AVAILABLE UNITS THERE 8431
PEOPLE APPLIED. IT'S BEEN ALMOST FIVE YEARS
SINCE THOSE 8338 PEOPLE WHO APPLIED WERE REJECTED.
WHAT MESSAGE DO WE SEND THEM IF WE TURN DOWN THIS CHANCE NOW TO
BUILD MORE HOMES FOR THEM? A VOTE AGAINST THE FAMILY
ZONING PLAN IS A VOTE FOR THE STATUS QUO AND IT IS A
PRIVILEGE TO BE OKAY WITH THE STATUS QUO.
LANDLORDS AND BILLIONAIRES MAKE THEIR MONEY OFF THE STATUS QUO.
WELL, FAMILY IS RENTERS AND WORKING CLASS COMMUNITIES
LOSE OUT AND I'M NOT OKAY WITH THE STATUS QUO TODAY.
OUR OWN CITY ECONOMISTS HAVE SHOWN US DATA THAT INDICATES
THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN WILL REDUCE THE COST OF LIVING FOR
OUR RESIDENTS. THE AVERAGE HOME IN SAN
FRANCISCO COSTS $1.3 MILLION AND THE AVERAGE RENT FOR A TWO
BEDROOM IS NEARLY $5,000 PER MONTH.
WHAT MESSAGE ARE WE SENDING OUR RESIDENTS, OUR CONSTITUENTS IF
WE TURN DOWN THIS PLAN AND LITERALLY VOTE AGAINST
LOWERING THEIR COST OF LIVING? THIS PLAN ISN'T PERFECT.
FEW PLANS ARE. BUT LET'S BE VERY CLEAR ABOUT
WHAT A VOTE AGAINST THIS PLAN MEANS.
>> IT WOULD BRING THE LOSS OF HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
IN HOUSING FUNDS. IT WOULD BLOCK THOUSANDS OF
FUTURE AFFORDABLE HOMES. >> AND IT WOULD SET US DOWN A
PATH TO A FLURRY OF BUILDERS REMEDY PROJECTS.
THINK HIGHRISE TOWERS IN ANY PART OF THE CITY WITH NO LOCAL
INVOLVEMENT IN THESE DECISIONS. AND THAT'S NOT AN EXAGGERATION.
THAT IS THE REALITY OF WHAT YOU RISK BY VOTING AGAINST THE
FAMILY ZONING PLAN. TO ME THIS COMES DOWN TO A
CHOICE. DO WE MAKE THE SAME MISTAKE
THAT THIS BOARD MADE IN 1978 BY VOTING AGAINST ALLOWING MORE
HOMES? >> DO WE CHOOSE TO PULL UP THE
LADDER BEHIND US BECAUSE WE ALREADY HAVE OUR SLICE OF SAN
FRANCISCO? I KNOW WHAT MY CHOICES.
AND THAT IS WHY I WILL BE VOTING FOR THIS PLAN TODAY.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> COLLEAGUES.
FIRST AND FOREMOST I WANT TO THANK THE MANY STAKEHOLDERS WHO
PUT IN SIGNIFICANT WORK TO SHAPE THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN
IN FRONT OF US TODAY STARTING WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
TEAM LED BY DIRECTOR TENOR JOSH WHISKEY LISA CHEN WHO WORKED
FOR YEARS ON THIS PLAN. >> I ALSO WANT TO THANK YOU
CHAIR MELGAR OVER THE SEVERAL SEVERAL HEARINGS YOU'VE
DEMONSTRATED YOUR LEGISLATIVE EXPERTISE AND IMMENSE PATIENCE
WHILE UNDERGOING THE EXTENSIVE AMENDMENT PROCESS.
I'M GRATEFUL FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP ON THE BOARD
AND ALSO ON THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU FOR YOUR PARTNERSHIP ON A
SUCCESSFUL AMENDMENT THAT WILL ENSURE CITY HALL IS DOING ALL
WE CAN TO INCENTIVIZE MORE FAMILY SIZED HOMES.
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN, THANK YOU FOR YOUR WORK ON THE TENANT
PROTECTIONS ORDINANCE WHICH WILL FURTHER STRENGTHEN SAN
FRANCISCO'S LEGACY OF BEING A LEADER ON RENT CONTROL
AND TENANTS RIGHTS. I'M VERY PROUD TO BE ABLE TO
CO-SPONSOR YOUR LEGISLATION. MOST IMPORTANTLY THOUGH, I
ESPECIALLY WANT TO THANK THE DISTRICT TWO COMMUNITY FOR
SHOWING UP TO THE TOWN HALLS TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD MEETINGS, TO
THE COMMUNITY ROUNDTABLES TO THE OFFICE HOURS TO ADD YOUR
VOICES TO THE FUTURE OF HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THROUGH THESE COMMUNITY CONVERSATIONS I HAVE LEARNED
AND BEEN ABLE TO RESPOND TO COMMUNITY FEEDBACK HELPING
SUCCESS FULLY BRING FORWARD THOUGHTFUL AMENDMENTS
IN COLLABORATION WITH ALL OF YOU.
I'M PROUD THAT MY AMENDMENTS HELPED SHAPE THIS PLAN TO BE AS
METICULOUS AND D2 AS POSSIBLE GOING BLOCK BY BLOCK AND PASS
GOAL BY PARCEL WHILE ENSURING THAT WE ARE NOT FAILING OUR
LEGAL OBLIGATION AND JEOPARDIZING CRITICAL FUNDS
AS WELL AS THE VERY REAL POTENTIAL STATE TAKEOVER OF OUR
PLANNING AND ZONING LAWS. >> THIS PLAN IS ABOUT THE
FUTURE. IT'S ABOUT CREATING A FUTURE
THAT IS MORE AFFORDABLE, MORE ACCESSIBLE FOR EVERYONE WHO
WANTS TO LIVE, GROW AND THRIVE HERE.
THIS IS ABOUT FAMILIES THAT ARE STARTING HERE, FAMILIES THAT
ARE GROWING HERE, FAMILIES THAT ARE STAYING HERE ACROSS
GENERATIONS BECAUSE RIGHT NOW SAN FRANCISCO HAS THE LOWEST
NUMBER OF CHILDREN PER CAPITA OF ANY MAJOR CITY IN THE UNITED
STATES. WE'RE THE FASTEST AGING CITY
IN THE UNITED STATES AND WE ALL KNOW THAT THE NUMBER ONE ISSUE
FOR FAMILIES IS HOUSING AFFORDABILITY.
THESE ARE NOT A RECIPE FOR SUCCESS.
WE NEED A DIFFERENT PATH FORWARD.
WE NEED A FUTURE THAT WELCOMES FAMILIES THAT WELCOME CIVIL
SERVANTS, TEACHERS, COPS, FIREFIGHTERS, OUR ELDERS.
WE NEED A FUTURE THAT PRIORITIZES OPPORTUNITY BY
WIDENING FLEXIBILITY FOR MORE HOUSING.
WE'RE BUILDING THAT FUTURE AND INVITING SAN FRANCISCANS TO
INVEST THEIR LIVES IN THIS CITY AND RAISE THE NEXT GENERATION
HERE. WHILE ALL GENERATIONS STAY HERE
AND WHILE WE BUILD THAT FUTURE WE MUST ALSO PLAN FOR WAYS TO
ENHANCE SAN FRANCISCO'S UNIQUE CHARM THAT ATTRACTS PEOPLE FROM
AROUND THE WORLD. THAT'S WHY I'M EXCITED TO BE
PURSUING AN OVERHAUL OF THE CITY'S DESIGN STANDARDS WITH A
PATH TOWARDS NEIGHBORHOOD DESIGN STANDARDS.
I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS FAMILY ZONING PLAN TODAY AS IT
WILL EMPOWER US TO BUILD MORE HOMES AND MAKE PROGRESS TOWARDS
A MORE ACCESSIBLE, AFFORDABLE AND ATTRACTIVE FUTURE.
AND I'LL BE SUPPORTING THIS BECAUSE I ALSO AM NOT OKAY WITH
THE STATUS QUO. >> BUT WE NEED TO BE UP FRONT
ABOUT THE FACT THAT ZONING IS NOT THE ONLY PART OF THE STATUS
QUO THAT MUST CHANGE. ZONING IS NOT A PANACEA FOR
HOUSING IN THIS CITY. IF WE JUST STOP WITH ZONING WE
WILL FAIL TO ADDRESS HOUSING AFFORDABILITY MUCH MUCH MORE
WILL BE NEEDED TO ADDRESS CONSTRUCTION COSTS.
NEIGHBORHOOD VITALITY. THE WAY THAT WE FUND AFFORDABLE
HOUSING WE MUST BE HONEST ABOUT THE FACT THAT THE WAY THAT WE
FUND AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS NOT GENERATING ENOUGH MONEY.
AND WHILE THE TIME FOR AMENDMENTS ON THIS PLAN HAS
PASSED, I PROMISE TO CONTINUE TO BE AT THE TABLE FOR THESE
FUTURE DISCUSSIONS ENGAGE ALL STAKEHOLDERS AND PUT FORTH
THOUGHTFUL IDEAS THAT BUILD ON THE PROGRESS OF THIS PLAN.
SO COLLEAGUES, I WANT TO THANK YOU ALL TO THE DEPARTMENT
REPRESENTATIVES, THANK YOU AND TO THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS
ESPECIALLY THANK YOU FOR THE WORK THAT HAS BEEN DONE TO GET
TO THIS POINT. AND I LOOK FORWARD TO
CONTINUING TO WORK ON HOUSING AFFORDABILITY IN THE MONTHS
AND YEARS AHEAD. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD, THANK
YOU GUYS AND THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
I WANT TO AGAIN EXPRESS MY THANKS TO SUPERVISOR AND CHAIR
MELGAR FOR LEADING THIS PROCESS FOR THE LAST SEVERAL MONTHS
AND ALSO TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR MANY YEARS ON
THIS PROCESS AS WELL. BEFORE GETTING TO MY REMARKS AS
A MEMBER OF THE LAND USE COMMITTEE THAT HAS BEEN IN THE
HEARINGS FOR THE LAST SEVERAL MONTHS, I HAD A COUPLE OF
QUESTIONS ACTUALLY TO GET A BETTER UNDERSTANDING OF THE
IMPLICATIONS OF SUPERVISOR CHEN'S AMENDMENT.
YES. WOULD SOMEONE FOR THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT BE AVAILABLE TO ANSWER SOME QUESTIONS?
>> SO AS I UNDERSTAND IT, THIS IS AN AMENDMENT THAT IS GOING
TO CHANGE THIS LANGUAGE TO ALL RESIDENTIAL HOUSEHOLDS AND RENT
CONTROL. >> AS I UNDERSTAND IT, SOME ONE
OF THE CONTINUOUS POINTS THAT WE HEARD ACROSS THE HEARINGS
WAS GUIDANCE FROM HKT THAT IF YOU REMOVE SOMETHING FROM THE
ZONING PLAN FROM A CAPACITY PERSPECTIVE YOU HAVE TO PROVIDE
A COMMENSURATE INCREASE. OTHERWISE IT RISKS BEING OUT OF
COMPLIANCE WITH THE HOUSING ELEMENT.
>> IS THAT CORRECT? THAT'S CORRECT.
SUPERVISORS LISA CHEN WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
SO I DID ISSUE A LETTER ON SEPTEMBER I BELIEVE NINTH RIGHT
BEFORE THE ADOPTION HEARING AT THE PLANNING COMMISSION THAT
SAID THAT THEY HAD REVIEWED THE ORDINANCE AS IT WAS INTRODUCED
IN IN JUNE. AND ESSENTIALLY THEY FOUND IT
TO BE COMPLIANT BUT THAT ESSENTIALLY WE WERE VERY CLOSE
TO JUST ABOVE WHAT WE NEED TO MEET OUR REQUIREMENTS AND SO
THAT IF WE DO MAKE FUTURE CHANGES THAT EITHER REDUCE
CAPACITY OR ADD CONSTRAINTS TO DEVELOPMENT SO THAT COULD BE
NEW FEES ANYTHING THAT CREATES GREATER UNCERTAINTY OR GREATER
TIMELINES FOR PROJECTS WE WOULD NEED TO MAKE COMMENSURATE
CHANGES IN THE OPPOSITE DIRECTION RECEIVING THIS
AMENDMENT AT LITERALLY THE 11TH HOUR HAS ANY COMMENSURATE
CHANGE BEEN PROPOSED TO MAKE UP FOR THE CAPACITY LOSS?
>> WE WE HAVE NOT RECEIVED ANY REQUESTS TO MAKE OTHER CHANGES
TO INCREASE CAPACITY. >> AND WHAT ARE THE
IMPLICATIONS AGAIN OF CONSTRAINTS AND REDUCING
CAPACITY THAT WE'VE RECEIVED GUIDANCE FROM THE OECD?
WHAT IMPLICATIONS DO WE HAVE IF WE DON'T PASS THIS HOUSING
ELEMENT AND PUT US OUT OF COMPLIANCE WITH THAT DIRECTION?
>> THE DIRECTIVE THAT THEY GAVE IF WE DO NOT PASS THE FAMILY
ZONING PLAN OR IF WE PASS A PLAN THAT IS NOT SUFFICIENT TO
MEET OUR REQUIREMENT WHICH IS FOR 36,200 UNITS OF CAPACITY
THEN OUR HOUSING ELEMENT COULD BECOME DECERTIFIED AND THIS
WOULD HAPPEN AFTER THE DEADLINE WHICH IS THE END OF JANUARY OF
NEXT YEAR IF WE RECEIVE IF OUR HOUSING ELEMENT IS DECERTIFIED
IT MEANS THAT BUILDERS REMEDY WOULD GO INTO EFFECT MEANING
THAT PROJECTS COULD COME IN AND PROPOSE ANY HEIGHT AND DENSITY
AS LONG AS IT'S MEETING YOU KNOW ESSENTIALLY SAFETY
STANDARDS. IT ALSO MEANS THAT WE WOULD BE
INELIGIBLE FOR CERTAIN FUNDING STREAMS, DIFFERENT GRANTS
AND RESOURCES AT THE STATE LEVEL INCLUDING FUNDING FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING AS WELL AS INFRASTRUCTURE.
AND WE HAVE TALLIED KIND OF THE PAST RECEIPTS FROM SOME OF
THOSE FUNDING SOURCES AND IT'S AVERAGED ABOUT $100 MILLION A
YEAR. AND THEN FINALLY WE WOULD BE
SUSCEPTIBLE TO OTHER POTENTIAL LEGAL CHALLENGES.
WE COULD BE SUED OR BE FINED AND RECEIVE OTHER PENALTIES.
>> SO AGAIN TO CLARIFY, YOU'RE BASICALLY SAYING IF WE
INTRODUCE AMENDMENTS THAT DO REDUCE CAPACITY AND DON'T
PROVIDE COMMENSURATE INCREASE IN CAPACITY, WE COULD BE LOSING
HUNDREDS OVER $100 MILLION A YEAR IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING
FUNDING. >> THAT'S CORRECT.
ANOTHER CLAIM THAT WAS MADE WAS THAT THIS PLAN PUTS 20,000
HOUSEHOLDS AT RISK OF DEMOLITION AND DISPLACEMENT.
>> IS THERE ANYTHING IN THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN THAT MAKES
DEMOLITIONS ADMINISTRATIVELY EASIER THAT THAT IS NOT
ACCURATE? SO OUR TENANT PROTECTIONS DON'T
EXIST IN THE REZONING ITSELF AND WE ALREADY HAVE STRONG
TENANT PROTECTIONS UNDER SECTION 317 OF OUR PLANNING
CODE. AS YOU ARE ALL AWARE, WE ALSO
HAVE A PENDING PROPOSAL THE TENANT PROTECTIONS ORDINANCE
WHICH IS LED BY SUPERVISOR CHEN AND CO-SPONSORED BY MANY OF YOU
WHICH IS GOING TO STRENGTHEN THOSE PROTECTIONS EVEN FURTHER.
AND WE DO HAVE EVIDENCE THAT THOSE PROTECTIONS HAVE BEEN
SUCCESSFUL DETERRENT TO DEMOLITIONS BECAUSE THEY MAKE
IT EXTREMELY DIFFICULT TO DEMOLISH YOU NEED FOR ANY
DEMOLITION OF A RENT CONTROLLED BUILDING YOU ARE REQUIRED TO GO
TO A PLANNING COMMISSION HEARING FOR A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION AND THOSE ARE OFTEN DENIED.
AND SO WE HAVE SEEN THAT THAT HAS RESULTED IN AN EXTREMELY
LOW NUMBER OF IF ALL UNITS AND PARTICULARLY RENT
CONTROLLED UNITS BEING DEMOLISHED.
>> AND WHAT YOU'RE REFERRING TO IS THAT WE HAVE UP ZONED ON THE
EAST SIDE OF THE CITY AND WE HAVE NOT SEEN THOUSANDS OF
UNITS OF DISPLACEMENT IN THAT CONTEXT.
>> THAT IS CORRECT. WE'VE EVALUATED THE DATA GOING
BACK TWO YEARS BEFORE REZONING AND WE HAVE NOT SEEN ANY
PARTICULAR UPTICK OR INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF DEMOLITIONS
AFTER REZONING EFFORTS ELSEWHERE IN THE CITY.
>> THANK YOU. AND JUST TO REITERATE THIS
POINT, AS A RESULT OF THE LEGISLATURE ON THE TENANT
PROTECTION ORDINANCE WE'RE ACTUALLY AT THIS TIME ONCE THAT
PASSES AS WELL MAKING SAN FRANCISCO THE STRONGEST CITY
AND I BELIEVE THE NATION ON TENANT PROTECTIONS.
>> I DON'T KNOW THAT IN CALIFORNIA.
YES, MAYBE THE CITY ATTORNEYS OR SOMEBODY WHO'S MORE
INTIMATELY FAMILIAR WITH OTHER CITIES WOULD BE ABLE TO OPINE
FURTHER. BUT WE ARE WE ARE KNOWN AS
HAVING VERY STRONG PROTECTIONS .
WE KNOW THERE ARE VERY HARD FOUGHT AND WON PROTECTIONS.
>> YOU KNOW, MANY CITIES DO NOT HAVE PUBLIC HEARINGS FOR
DEMOLITION PROPOSALS. SO WE THINK THAT THAT HAS
REALLY CREATED A DISINCENTIVE TO DEMOLISH UNITS IN LARGE
NUMBERS. >> AS I MENTIONED, WE DO SEE
SOME DEMOLITIONS EVERY YEAR BUT THEY'RE VERY SMALL IN TERMS OF
THE PERCENTAGE OF UNITS. >> THANK YOU.
THEY ANSWERED MY QUESTIONS, COLLEAGUES.
BASED ON THAT CONTEXT, ONE I THINK REITERATE WHAT IS THE
FAMILY ZONING PLAN? WHAT DOES IT DO?
WHAT ARE ITS IMPACTS AND WHERE ITS BENEFITS?
I THINK THAT'S BEEN LOST. I MISSED A LOT OF THE
CONVERSATION THAT WE'VE BEEN HAVING THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN
WITH THE ZONING CHANGES THAT IT IS PRODUCING AROUND SORT OF
SPECIFIC CORRIDORS THE INCREASED DENSITY ALLOWANCES
AND NEIGHBORHOODS AND THE NEW LOCAL DENSITY BONUS PROGRAM
WILL MAKE IT EASIER TO ADD MUCH NEEDED HOUSING UNITS TO IMPROVE
AFFORDABILITY LIVABILITY AND VITALITY IN THIS GREAT
CITY. >> THIS PLAN CREATES CAPACITY
AS MANDATED BY OUR HOUSING ELEMENT FOR 36,000 HOMES TO BE
BUILT LARGELY IN AREAS ON THE WEST SIDE AND NORTH OF THE CITY
THAT HAVE SEEN LITTLE TO NO DEVELOPMENT IN THE PAST
DECADES. >> IT CREATES A LOCAL DENSITY
BONUS PROGRAM THAT ENCOURAGES NEW DENSER HOUSING IN A WAY
THAT CONFORMS TO OUR VALUES IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND TO REITERATE THIS LOCAL DENSITY BONUS PROGRAM CREATES
INCENTIVES TO GENERATE AFFORDABLE HOUSING FUNDING
INCLUDING FOR INNOVATIVE MODALITIES LIKE 100% RENT
CONTROL BUILDINGS AS WELL. >> IT CHANGES THE RULES THAT
WHERE WE ALREADY HAVE 40 FOOT BUILDINGS THOSE BUILDINGS ARE
NO LONGER LIMITED BY THE NUMBER OF UNITS THEY HAVE JUST THEIR
SIZE AND SHAPE. >> IT ENCOURAGES BRINGING NOT
JUST MORE SHOPPERS TO OUR COMMERCIAL CORRIDOR IS THROUGH
NEW HOUSING ON VACANT AND UNDERUTILIZED SITES BUT
ALSO INCENTIVIZES BUILDERS TO MAKE THEIR COMMERCIAL SPACES
MOVE AND READY. PERHAPS MOST IMPORTANTLY IT
WILL ENABLE SAN FRANCISCO TO CONTROL ITS OWN DESTINY WHEN IT
COMES TO HOUSING PROTECTING US FROM STATE PENALTIES LIKE WE
JUST HEARD. >> BUT LIKE WE JUST HEARD, IT
IS IMPORTANT TO REITERATE WHAT THIS PLAN DOES NOT DO IN MOST
AREAS. >> THE LEGISLATION DOESN'T
INCREASE HEIGHTS WHERE IT DOES. IT ONLY INCREASES BY A FEW
STORIES THAN WHAT IS CURRENTLY ALLOWED UNDER CURRENT ZONING
AND AROUND THE SAME HEIGHTS THAT ARE CURRENTLY ALLOWED BY
THE STATE'S DENSITY BONUS PROGRAM.
>> AS WE JUST HEARD FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT, NOTHING
IN THIS LEGISLATION WILL MAKE IT EASIER TO EVICT TENANTS OR
DEMOLISH BUILDINGS. >> IN FACT THROUGH THIS PROCESS
WE HAVE STRENGTHENED THOSE TENANT PROTECTIONS AND I THINK
IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT WHEN THESE STATEMENTS ABOUT
DEMOLISHING 20,000 HOMES ARE SAID, IT IS FEAR MONGERING.
IT'S NOT TRUE. IT IS FACTUALLY NOT TRUE
AND IT'S EXPLOITING GENUINE CONCERNS OF RESIDENTS ACROSS
THE CITY TO SCORE POLITICAL POINTS.
THAT'S NOT LEADERSHIP. IT'S EMOTIONAL EXPLOITATION.
AND OUR RESIDENTS DESERVE BETTER.
>> AND SO ON THIS NOTE, I WANT TO THANK THE HARD WORK OF
SUPERVISORS CHEN AND MELGAR. ON THE TENANT PROTECTION
ORDINANCE WHICH WILL STRENGTHEN OUR NETWORK OF LAWS
AND PROGRAMS THAT SUPPORT EXISTING TENANTS AND BUILDINGS
OF ALL TYPES AND ALL SIZES PROVIDING OUR CITY THE
STRONGEST TENANT PROTECTIONS IN THE COUNTRY.
AND THANKS TO SUPERVISOR MELGAR, IF THERE'S ANYONE
LOOKING TO DEMOLISH A RENT CONTROLLED APARTMENT BUILDING
WITH THREE OR MORE UNITS TO TAKE OUT LOCAL LANDMARKS, THEY
CANNOT DO SO. >> ANY EFFORT TO AMEND THE
LOCAL DENSITY BONUS PROGRAM AT THIS STAGE SENDS A MESSAGE THAT
WE ARE NOT SERIOUS ABOUT TACKLING OUR AFFORDABILITY
CRISIS BECAUSE IT WOULD BE SENDING A MESSAGE THAT WE ARE
COMFORTABLE WITH LOSING OVER $100 MILLION OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING FUNDING A YEAR. >> AND TO ALSO MAKE CLAIMS THAT
WE SHOULD BE FIGHTING THE STATE IS CLEARLY NOT RESPONSIBLE AT A
TIME WHEN WE SHOULD BE FIGHTING THE PRESIDENT IN WASHINGTON,
D.C. WE SHOULD BE FOCUSING OUR EFFORTS THERE RATHER THAN AT A
STATE WHOSE HELP WE NEED TO SURVIVE.
THE CURRENT ADMINISTRATION. >> THE BEST WAY FOR US TO HELP
RENTERS ISN'T AN OBTUSE TOOL THAT FREEZES THE BUILT
ENVIRONMENT AND MEMBER. IT'S MAKING SURE RENTERS HAVE
MORE PLACES TO CALL HOME. AND PROTECTING EXISTING TENANTS
AS OUR CITY CREATES HOUSING TO WELCOME NEW NEIGHBORS.
>> I LOVE SAN FRANCISCO. I KNOW ALL OF YOU DO AS WELL.
>> AND FUNDAMENTALLY I THINK SOME OF THE RESISTANCE THIS
LEGISLATION IS AN AFFINITY FOR THE STATUS QUO.
>> AS MY COLLEAGUES HAVE SAID. BUT THAT STATUS QUO IS A ZONING
PARADIGM THAT IS CENTERED AROUND AN EXCLUSIONARY ZONING
PROCESS THAT HAS A RACIST HISTORY IN OUR IN OUR AN
UNFORTUNATE HISTORY AROUND A NIGHTMARISH HOUSING
AFFORDABILITY LANDSCAPE. ONE THAT FORCES MANY OF THE
VERY PEOPLE WHO MAKE THIS CITY WORK OUR TEACHERS,
FIREFIGHTERS, WORKERS TO COMMUTE FROM DOZENS OR HUNDREDS
OF MILES AWAY IN SUBSTANDARD HOUSING.
>> WE CAN'T KEEP DOING THE SAME THING AND EXPECT DIFFERENT
RESULTS. OUR RESIDENTS ARE COUNTING ON
US TO BUILD A FUTURE FOR THEM. >> AND WHAT MAKES THIS CITY SO
GREAT IS HOW WELCOMING IT IS. >> I DIDN'T GROW UP HERE BUT
THIS IS MY HOME. I KNOW MANY OF YOU MY
COLLEAGUES ARE TRANSPLANTS ARE IMMIGRANTS ARE FIRST GENERATION
LIKE ME. AND BEING WELCOMING IS WHAT HAS
MADE THIS CITY SAN FRANCISCO TO GROW TO CHANGE AS ALL CITIES
SHOULD. >> THAT'S THE STORY OF SAN
FRANCISCO THAT WE'VE KNOWN FOR ACROSS THE WORLD.
>> BUT IF WE DON'T PASS THIS PLAN, WE LOSE THAT STORY
AND LOSE AND ROBBED THE EXPERIENCE OF THIS SEVEN BY
SEVEN CITY FROM OTHERS. >> THAT IS NOT THE MESSAGE I
THINK ANY OF US WANT TO SEND HERE TODAY.
WE ARE NOT. >> WE DON'T WANT TO SEND A
MESSAGE THAT IF YOU'RE NOT FROM HERE.
SORRY BUT YOU DON'T MAKE THE CUT.
>> IF WE DON'T PASS THIS PLAN WE WILL CONTINUE THE CITY'S
LONG DESCENT INTO HOUSING INEQUALITY PERPETUATING THE
UNFAIR SYSTEMS THAT HAVE GRINDED DOWN TENANTS FOR
DECADES FURTHER EXACERBATING SOCIAL INEQUITIES FOR OUR MOST
VULNERABLE RESIDENTS. >> IF WE DON'T PASS THIS PLAN,
THE FORCES THAT HAVE PUSHED OUR YOUNGER GENERATIONS
AND FAMILIES OUT OF THE CITY WILL CONTINUE UNABATED.
>> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS WORKED IN THE LAST SEVERAL
MONTHS TO GET THIS ITEM TO THE FINISH LINE.
THEY HAVE ENGAGED WITH EIGHT KEY WITH OUR OFFICES
AND DIRECTLY WITH MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC TO ANSWER ANY
QUESTIONS AND ASSESS THE VIABILITY OF DOZENS OF PROPOSED
AMENDMENTS. >> WE'VE ALSO HEARD HEARING
SINCE OCTOBER AT THE LAND USE COMMITTEE WHERE WE HEARD FROM
OUR BOARD COLLEAGUES AND THE PUBLIC AND MADE CLEAR
IMPROVEMENTS TO THIS PLAN. IT IS CLEAR THAT THIS VERSION
OF THE LEGISLATION WILL BE THE ONE THAT THE STATE ACCEPTS AS A
VALID AND COMPLIANT IMPLEMENTATION OF OUR HOUSING
ELEMENT. BUT ANYTHING THAT ADDS CAN
STRENGTH TO DEVELOPMENT OR TAKES AWAY HOUSING CAPACITY
COULD TAKE US OUT OF COMPLIANCE.
>> THAT WOULD BE CATASTROPHIC. >> AS WE HAVE HEARD
CONSISTENTLY, THE NONCOMPLIANCE RATES WOULD TRIGGER THE
BUILDER'S REMEDY A PATH TO NEARLY UNFETTERED APPROVALS FOR
OVERSIZE RESIDENTIAL PROJECTS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO WITHOUT
INPUT FROM RESIDENTS. IT WOULD LEAD TO FINES THAT
WOULD DRAW DOWN FROM OUR ALREADY PRECARIOUS BUDGET
AND WOULDN'T EVEN LEAD TO THE CITY LOSING ACCESS TO MANY
FORMS OF STATE FUNDING. LET ME DIG IN TO THAT.
BECAUSE GOING OUT OF COMPLIANCE WOULD MEAN THE CITY LOSES
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING EVERY
YEAR. >> AS WE HAVE HEARD REPEATEDLY,
THAT IS DISASTROUS FOR A LIVABLE CITY.
THAT IS NOT THE CITY THAT WE WANT.
SAN FRANCISCO TO BE ONE WHERE OUR KIDS CAN'T STAY HERE
BECAUSE WE TOLD THEM THAT WE WANTED TO WIN A POLITICAL
ARGUMENT AND RISKED $100 MILLION A YEAR IN AFFORDABLE
HOUSING FUNDING. >> AND I CERTAINLY DON'T THINK
THAT'S WHAT MANY OF OUR COMMUNITY MEMBERS ACROSS THE
CITY WANT AS WELL. >> NEITHER DO THE COUNCIL OF
DISTRICT MERCHANTS ASSOCIATION. NEITHER DOES THE GOLDEN GATE
RESTAURANT ASSOCIATION. NEITHER DOES THE SAN FRANCISCO
FIREFIGHTERS LOCAL SEVEN AND EIGHT NOR DOES THE SMALL
BUSINESS COMMISSION. >> NEITHER DOES THE YOUTH
COMMISSION. >> NEITHER DO THE BUILDING
TRADES THAT BUILD OUR HOUSING. ALL WHO HAVE SUPPORTED
AND ENDORSED THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN.
>> SO IN SUPPORT AND IN COLLABORATION WITH ALL OF THEM
I ASK MY COLLEAGUES LET'S DO WHAT'S RIGHT FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
LET'S PASS THIS LEGISLATION AS IT IS AND START LOOKING FORWARD
AHEAD TOWARDS BUILDING A MORE AFFORDABLE AND PROSPEROUS SAN
FRANCISCO. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON, THANK YOU
SO MUCH. I WANT TO START OFF BY SAYING
TO ONE OF MY COLLEAGUES WHO I RESPECT I AM EXTREMELY GLAD
THAT I DON'T HAVE TO SCORE POLITICAL POINTS.
>> BUT IN ADDITION TO THE FACT THAT THE PLAN WILL NOT PROTECT
ALL RENT CONTROL HOUSING FROM DEMOLITION WHICH I HAVE TO
REMIND EVERYONE IS CRITICAL FOR AFFORDABILITY IN THIS CITY.
>> AND THE FACT THAT THIS PLAN DOES NOT IDENTIFY ANY SPECIFIC
PROJECTS OR PROVIDE A ROUTE TO FINANCING FOR ANY PROJECT THE
PLAN DOES NOT LEAD TO ACHIEVING THE GOALS.
THAT PUTS SAN FRANCISCO IN COMPLIANCE WITH THE STATE AS
A SUPERVISOR WHO ACTUALLY BUILDS AND HAS ACTUALLY WORKED
WITH CITY DEPARTMENTS DEVELOPERS BOTH NONPROFIT
AND PRIVATE TO COME UP WITH ACTUAL FINANCING IDEAS NEVER
BEFORE IMPLEMENTED IN SAN FRANCISCO NOW IS A MODEL THAT
WE ALL ARE USING AND SUPPORTING THAT ACTUALLY LEAD TO HOUSING
WITHOUT DISPLACING FAMILIES AND COMMUNITIES LIKE THE SENSE
THAT THE RICHMOND IN AREAS OUTSIDE OF DOWNTOWN.
I WANT TO COMMEND AND SAY THANK YOU TO THE LAND USE COMMITTEE
FOR PUTTING IN THE TIME AND PUTTING IN THE HARD WORK.
I KNOW THAT AT TIMES WE JUST WON'T COME TO AN AGREEMENT ON
POLICY FOR MANY DIFFERENT REASONS.
BUT SOME OF THE SLIGHT AMENDMENTS THAT HAVE BEEN PUT
IN PLACE HAVE PROTECTED PEOPLE FROM LOSING HOUSING IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> BUT WE SHOULD NOT BE
DISPLACING ANYONE IN THIS CITY. WE HAVE A HOUSING CRISIS
IN THIS CITY AND LOSING JUST ONE UNIT JUST ONE UNIT OF
HOUSING IS COMPLETELY ARBITRARY.
BUT MOST CERTAINLY LOSING 20,000 UNITS IS A MAJOR PROBLEM
AND IS VERY ARBITRARY TO ADDRESSING HOMELESSNESS
AND CREATING THE STABILIZATION THAT IS NEEDED TO KEEP OUR
RESIDENTS HOUSE. >> AND I KNOW THIS PLAN IS
DESCRIBED AS MAKING SAN FRANCISCANS MAKING DECISIONS
FOR SAN FRANCISCO BUT THIS IS A RESPONSE TO STATE BULLYING
DISGUISED AS RESULTS ORIENTED. THIS PLAN WILL MOST CERTAINLY
HAVE NEGATIVE INTENDED AND UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES.
MY COLLEAGUES HAVE CERTAINLY LABORED OVER WHETHER OR NOT TO
SUPPORT THIS PLAN. >> AND AGAIN I THANK EVERYONE
FOR THEIR WORK. BUT THERE IS STILL TOO MANY
ISSUES IN THIS PLAN FOR ME TO SUPPORT IN GOOD CONSCIENCE AS A
SUPERVISOR WHO BUILDS. NOW MAYBE IF IT INCLUDED ACTUAL
LOCATIONS FOR HOUSING IDENTIFIED MAYBE IF IT INCLUDED
A FINANCING PACKAGE OR A PROPOSAL TO ACTUALLY BUILD
HOUSING, MAYBE IF IT GUARANTEED NOT TO DISPLACE FAMILIES
AND BUSINESSES AND ACTUALLY BRING THE DESIRED HOUSING THAT
PUTS US IN COMPLIANCE WITH THE STATE.
>> THIS PLAN IS GOOD FOR THEORY AND FOR RHETORIC, NOT FOR
BUILDING AND CERTAINLY FOR NOT BUILDING FOR OUR MOST
VULNERABLE POPULATIONS IN THIS CITY.
>> AND IF YOU BELIEVE THAT THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA IS GOING TO
ATTACK THE CITY WITH THE MOST MILLIONAIRES AND THE TOP FIVE
GDP FOR THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA TO RICH BECAUSE THEY DON'T
ACHIEVE OR GIVE THE PERCEPTION OF ACHIEVING ARBITRARY GOALS
THAT NO COUNTY NO CITY IN THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA WILL
ACHIEVE. I CANNOT ADHERE TO THAT SCARE
TACTIC. AND YES, SUPERVISOR MAHMUD, I
100% AGREE WITH YOU THAT WE SHOULD NOT BE FIGHTING THE
STATE OF CALIFORNIA RIGHT NOW. YOU ARE ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
BUT THERE ARE TIMES WHEN WE HAVE TO FIGHT THE STATE OF
CALIFORNIA. THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA DIDN'T
ALWAYS BELIEVE IN SAME SEX MARRIAGE.
REMEMBER THOSE BATTLES? THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA DIDN'T
ALWAYS FIGHT AGAINST REDLINING. THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
SOMETIMES DEFINES EDUCATION SO YOU RIGHT.
>> I DON'T HAVE A PROBLEM FIGHTING THE STATE OF
CALIFORNIA WHEN IT'S THE RIGHT THING TO DO.
WHAT WE HAVE HERE IS A BUNCH OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE NEVER BUILT
ANYTHING TRYING TO SET POLICY FOR BUILDING HOUSING IN SAN
FRANCISCO. NOT ONE OF THESE UNITS NOT ONE
THESE PROPOSED IMAGINARY UNITS WILL BE BUILT BY WHERE THE
MAYOR LIVES. NOT ONE.
>> THIS IS A THEORETICAL FRAMEWORK THAT WILL ACHIEVE
NOTHING THAT PUTS US IN LINE WITH MEETING STATE GOALS.
AND IT MOST CERTAINLY WILL NOT PUT US IN LINE WITH ADDRESSING
THE HOUSING CRISIS THAT WE HAVE HALF HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I CANNOT SUPPORT THIS. AND I KNOW HISTORY IS GOING TO
DEMONSTRATE WHY THIS WAS A BAD IDEA FOR THIS CITY AND THIS
COUNTY. >> WE CAN DO BETTER.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN, THANK YOU PERSON.
>> TO BEGIN WITH I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY COMMITTEE CHAIR
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY
COLLEAGUES SUPERVISOR MOORE AND THE COMMITTEE.
AND ALSO I WANT TO THANK ALL MY COLLEAGUES AT THE BOARD AND THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF AND ALSO THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE FOR ALL THE WORK AND SUPPORT.
>> A VICE CHAIR OF THE LAND USE COMMITTEE AND ALSO AS THE
CITY'S SUPERVISOR THAT REALLY CARED DEEPLY FOR MY CITY.
I DO NOT TAKE MY VOTE LIGHTLY. I HAVE ENGAGE VERY ACTIVELY
IN THIS LEGISLATION SINCE INTRODUCTION.
>> I JUST WANT TO BE CLEAR AGAIN I ABSOLUTELY SUPPORT
BUILDING MORE HOUSING AND IT NEEDS TO BE THE RIGHT KIND OF
HOUSING. >> I AND MY OTHER COLLEAGUES ON
THE BOARD HAVE WORKED OVER TIME AND APPROACHED THIS PROCESS
IN GOOD FAITH TO AMEND THIS ZONING PLAN WITH EVERY
INTENTION TO MAKE IT BETTER. >> WE HAVE SOUGHT TO ACHIEVE
THOUGHTFUL, AFFORDABLE INFILL DEVELOPMENT THAT STRENGTHENS
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS WITHOUT PUSHING ANYONE OUT.
>> STABILIZING OUR SMALL BUSINESS AND ALSO SUPPORT OUR
RESIDENTS TO RAISE THEIR FAMILIES HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
WE HAVE DRAFTED COMMON SENSE AMENDMENTS THAT ARE PRO HOUSING
AND ALSO PUT AFFORDABILITY PRO SMALL BUSINESS, POOR TENANT
AND PRO WORKING FAMILIES. >> I, I HAVE TO REPEAT MYSELF.
IT PAINS ME TO SEE THAT MAJORITY OF THIS CRITICAL
EQUITY AMENDMENTS HAVE BEEN VOTED DOWN OR TABLE OUR
TEACHERS, BUS DRIVERS, JANITORS ,NURSES, FIRST RESPONDERS
AND ALL THE WORKING FAMILIES WHO KEEP THIS CITY RUNNING
DESERVE REAL OPTIONS TO LIVE HERE WITH DIGNITY.
IN MY VERY OWN DISTRICT I HAVE RECEIVED CONSTITUENT EMAILS
WITH A RATIO OF 2 TO 1 TO OPPOSE THE REZONING SIMPLY
BECAUSE INDUSTRIAL HEAVEN WE HAVE LARGER HOUSEHOLDS AND MANY
INTERGENERATIONAL FAMILIES. WE NEED DEVELOPMENT THAT
ENSURES A GOOD BALANCE OF FAMILY SIZE UNITS HOUSING PRICE
TO REFLECT AFFORDABILITY THE AFFORDABILITY NEEDS OF WORKING
RESIDENTS AND PROTECTION FOR THE LOCALLY ROOTED SMALL
BUSINESS ON OUR BUSINESS CORRIDOR.
>> INSTEAD IN DISTRICT 11 WE ARE SEEING A DEVELOPMENT
PROJECT ON OCEAN AVENUE THAT DISPLACES THAT DISPLACED IF FOR
LOCALLY ROOTED SMALL BUSINESS BY PROVIDING ONLY NINE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS SIX THREE BEDROOM OUT OF 92 TOTAL
UNITS. >> WHEN OUR MAYOR ANNOUNCED A
FAMILY ZONING LEGISLATION AT THE PRESS CONFERENCE AT 1100
OCEAN AVENUE MALE FLURRY UPLIFTED OCEAN AVENUE AS ONE OF
SAN FRANCISCO'S MOST SUCCESSFUL REZONING PROGRAMS.
>> BUT 1100 OCEAN AVENUE WAS POSSIBLE AS 100% AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PROJECT AND A NEW PUBLIC PLAZA.
>> ONLY BECAUSE THE SITE IT'S ON PUBLIC LAND.
THE CURRENT REZONING PROPOSAL MAKES NO SUCH GUARANTEE TO
DELIVER 100% AFFORDABLE PROJECTS ON PUBLIC LANDS.
>> THE MAYOR'S OFFICE HAS REALLY TRY HARD TO WORK ON A
MATH PROBLEM BUT THIS DOES NOT SOLVE THE AFFORDABLE CRISIS
THAT WE HAVE IN SAN FRANCISCO. AND I BELIEVE THAT SAN
FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN COMMITTED TO MEETING THE
STATE'S HOUSING MANDATE. OUR CITY DOES HAVE THE ABILITY
TO MEET THE GOAL. WHY?
MAINTAINING LOCAL CONTROL AND DEVELOPING HOUSING THAT
PEOPLE CAN AFFORD WITHOUT DISPLACING RESIDENTS AND SMALL
BUSINESS. >> BUT THE PLAN THAT IT'S
BEFORE US DOES NOT ACHIEVE THAT.
>> IT HAS IT'S BEEN FRUSTRATING ROLE TO GET TO THIS POINT.
PRIOR TO THE NOVEMBER 17TH HEARING IN THE LAND USE
COMMITTEE. I WAS ASKED TO WATER DOWN SOME
OF MY AMENDMENTS. I REFUSED TO NEGOTIATE AWAY
PORTION OF PRIORITY EQUITY GEOGRAPHIES WITH WITHOUT
IMPACTED COMMUNITY AT THE TABLE .
AND IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT TO REMIND MYSELF THAT I AM THE
KIND OF SUPERVISOR THAT I WANT TO BE.
IT'S TO MAKE SURE THAT WE CONTINUE TO HAVE A PROCESS THAT
IS TRANSPARENT, THAT IT BRINGS EVERYONE ON THE TABLE.
>> ALSO IN TO THAT TODAY IT'S 2025, 2025.
WE SHOULDN'T HAVE TO BE REMINDED OF THE HARM THAT
REDEVELOPMENT COSTS TO VULNERABLE COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO IN THE PAST. >> FOR ME I THINK I HAVE BEEN
VERY CONSISTENT. >> LET'S BUILD AND ALSO LET'S
DO NO HARM TO ASSISTANCE THAT LET'S DO NO HARM TO EXISTING
SAN FRANCISCANS. >> LET'S ALSO TO MAKE SURE THAT
WE PREVENT DISPLACEMENT. AND LET'S ALSO USE EVERY TOOL
THAT WE HAVE TO DELIVER A TRUE AFFORDABILITY TO SAN
FRANCISCANS. >> I AM AND I AM ALWAYS STAND
WITH OUR FAMILIES, OUR CHILDREN ,OUR SENIORS, OUR TENANTS
AND OUR SMALL BUSINESS THAT MAKES OUR NEIGHBORHOODS FEELS
LIKE HOME. >> WE ARE THE LAST LINE TO
DEFEND FOR WORKING FAMILIES. >> AND THIS IS WHY I THINK THE
LEGISLATION AS ITS CURRENT FORM I'M NOT ABLE TO SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT. GENTLEMEN, FIRST OFF, I WANT TO
RECOGNIZE THE TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF WORK THAT WENT BEHIND
SHAPING THE LEGISLATION BEFORE US TODAY.
SPECIFICALLY OUR LAND USE COMMITTEE CHAIRED BY SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. AND SUPERVISORS CHEN
AND MAHMOOD ALONG WITH THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THE
WORK BY OUR CITIES COMMUNITY GROUPS INCLUDING THE REPS S.F.
COALITION ENTITIES PLACEMENT COALITION, SMALL BUSINESS
FORWARD AND EVERYONE ELSE WHO PROVIDED CRITICAL INPUT TO THIS
PLAN. >> ON THE WHOLE I'M SUPPORTIVE
OF INCENTIVIZING EQUITABLE DEVELOPMENT ON THE PARTS OF OUR
CITY THAT ARE WELL-RESOURCED AND HAVE NOT CONTRIBUTED TO OUR
HOUSING POOL. >> AND I SAY THIS AS A
SUPERVISOR WHO HAS HELPED CARRY HOUSING OVER THE FINISH LINE AT
THE BOARD ALREADY THIS YEAR SPECIFICALLY LA MORAVIA AT 16TH
AND MISSION. IN THE FACE OF HEATED
OPPOSITION FROM A SMALL GROUP OF LOCAL NEIGHBORS.
AND I WILL CONTINUE TO DO SO IN THE COMING MONTHS.
>> THIS PLAN EXCLUDES THE MAJORITY OF DISTRICT NINE FOR
THIS VERY REASON. THE SOUTHEAST SIDE OF THE CITY
INCLUDING THE MISSION DISTRICT HAS SEEN VASTLY MORE MARKET
RATE DEVELOPMENT THAN MORE WELL-RESOURCED NEIGHBORHOODS
IN SAN FRANCISCO. THE EASTERN NEIGHBORHOODS PLANS
INCENTIVIZE DEVELOPMENT HERE WHICH HAS ONLY BEEN EXACERBATED
BY STATE DENSER PROGRAMS IN THE MISSION DISTRICT.
>> THIS HAS MEANT THE DISPLACEMENT OF AROUND 12,000
LATINOS A VAST INCREASE IN HOUSEHOLDS MAKING OVER 150%
OF THE AREA MEDIAN INCOME AND A 55% INCREASE IN THE LATINO
HOMELESSNESS POPULATION. BETWEEN OUR LAST POINT IN TIME
COUNTS I AM ALSO WELL AWARE OF THE REALITY OF WHAT'S AT STAKE
WITH THE VARIOUS MANDATES WE MUST FULFILL UNDER EACH CITY
AND STATE LEGISLATION. ALL THAT SAID, IT IS CRITICAL
THAT ANY LOCAL PROGRAMS THAT ARE CREATED BY THE CITY
AND COUNTY ARE RESPONSIVE TO OUR LOCAL COMMUNITIES.
WE MUST DO EVERYTHING IN OUR POWER TO AVOID CREATING
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES SUCH AS DISPLACING MORE VULNERABLE
COMMUNITIES LIKE WE'VE EXPERIENCED IN THE MISSION
DISTRICT. >> SAN FRANCISCO CURRENTLY HAS
SOME OF THE STRONGEST TENANT PROTECTION LAWS IN THE COUNTRY
BECAUSE WE UNDERSTAND HOW CRITICAL OUR RENT CONTROLLED
HOUSING STOCK IS FOR OUR MIDDLE AND LOW INCOME COMMUNITIES.
>> FOR OUR WORKING CLASS STUDENTS, ARTISTS AND EVERYDAY
RESIDENTS. >> HOWEVER, THE FACT IS THAT WE
ARE HAVING TO UPDATE OUR DEMOLITION CONTROLS BECAUSE OF
STATE LAWS LIKE SB 330. I MAY CO-SPONSOR SUPERVISOR
CHEN'S PENDING TENANT PROTECTION ORDINANCE WHICH HAS
BEEN ANOTHER LABORIOUS EFFORT IN LARGE PART BECAUSE WE ARE
NOT ABLE TO KEEP OUR DEMOLITION PROTECTIONS AS STRONG AS WE
WOULD LIKE OR EVEN AS STRONG AS CITIES LIKE LOS ANGELES.
AND THAT IS WHY WE MUST DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO ENSURE
THAT TENANTS IN RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING ARE NOT AT RISK OF
DISPLACEMENT AND THAT WE EXCLUDE THEM FROM THIS UP
ZONING PLAN. >> THE PLAN BEFORE US TODAY
STILL INCLUDES APPROXIMATELY 20,000 RENT CONTROLLED UNITS.
WHY ARE WE UP ZONING SITES WHERE RENT CONTROLLED TENANTS
LIVE AND NOT BILLIONAIRE'S ROW? SAINT FRANCIS WOULD SEACLIFF OR
ANY OF THE OTHER PARCELS PREFERRED BY THE WEALTHIEST
IN SAN FRANCISCO. I ASK THIS THAT LAND USE
COMMITTEE AND APPRECIATIVE OF MY COLLEAGUES WHO HAVE ALSO
WORKED TOWARDS THE SAME GOAL. I BELIEVE THAT WE COULD HAVE
CREATED AN UP ZONING PLAN THAT MET THE GOALS IN OUR HOUSING
ELEMENT WHILE ALSO PROTECTING RENT CONTROLLED TENANTS.
>> BUT THAT IS NOT THE PLAN BEFORE US TODAY.
FOR THIS REASON I WILL BE SUPPORTING SUPERVISOR CHAN'S
AMENDMENTS AND SHOULD THAT FAIL VOTING NO ON ITEMS 36 THROUGH
38 AS THEY ARE CURRENTLY WRITTEN.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG WE GOT TO FIX SUPERVISOR WONG'S
MICROPHONE. >> WHAT'S GOING ON OVER THERE?
>> OKAY THERE IT IS. >> FIRST MEETING WELCOME FOUR
FOR ME. >> I'VE LIVED ALL MY LIFE IN IN
LAWS IN THE SUNSET. >> ALWAYS FOR MOST PEOPLE IT'S
RIGHT BEHIND A GARAGE AND THERE IS A LIVING AREA KIND OF BUILT
BEHIND THERE FOR THOSE THAT MAY NOT KNOW WHAT IN-LAW IS OR AN
ADA TO AND FROM MY LIFE MY FAMILY'S MOVED AROUND DIFFERENT
IN LAWS AND I'VE ALWAYS WANTED TO HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE
ACCESS TO BY MY OWN SUNSET DISTRICT FOR HOME BUT THAT HAS
BEEN VERY MUCH IMPOSSIBLE. THERE'S VERY LITTLE UNITS THAT
ARE ARE CONDOS OR AFFORDABLE THAT ARE IN IN DISTRICT FOUR.
ELSEWHERE THERE ARE THERE'S PLENTY AND OTHER OTHER
NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE MORE DENSE PARTS OF THE CITY.
BUT I ALWAYS WANT TO STAY IN ON THE WEST SIDE AND IN THE SUNSET
. AND HOMES COST NEARLY $2
MILLION. WE NEED MORE HOUSING OPTIONS
FOR OUR COMMUNITY SO THE NEXT GENERATION OF SUNSET FAMILIES
AND YOUNG PEOPLE LIKE MYSELF THAT HAVE GROWN UP
IN INTERGENERATIONAL HOUSEHOLDS AND IN-LAWS ARE ABLE TO HAVE
OPPORTUNITIES FOR FOR HOMES. >> I'M GLAD THAT THERE WERE
EARLIER TENANT PROTECTIONS THAT WERE MOVED FORWARD.
>> AND FOR ME I SUPPORT THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN AND IF WE
DON'T OFFER OUR OWN COMPLIANT SOLUTION SACRAMENTO WILL
DICTATE ZONING FOR US AND WE'LL LOSE LOCAL CONTROL WHICH IS NOT
ACCEPTABLE. >> I THINK THAT FOR US SAN
FRANCISCO HAS AN OPPORTUNITY TO GIVE OUR FEEDBACK AND WE KNOW
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS BEST AND NOT SACRAMENTO.
SO I'M COMMITTED TO WORKING WITH THE COMMUNITY MAYOR AND
COLLEAGUES OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO IMMEDIATELY
ADDRESS CONCERNS AND CONSIDER POTENTIAL TRAILING LEGISLATION
TO STRENGTHEN THIS PLAN. I'LL CONTINUE TO WORK WITH
CONSTITUENTS TO UNDERSTAND CONCERNS AND POSSIBLE
ADJUSTMENTS THAT CAN BE MADE TO THE CURRENT PROPOSAL
IN DISTRICT FOUR. I INTEND TO WORK WITH THE
COMMUNITY AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ON POTENTIAL
AMENDMENTS FOLLOWING ADOPTION. THIS TODAY I JUST MET WITH THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND TOUCH BASE WITH THEM TO GET FURTHER
CLARITY ON EVERYTHING THAT'S BEEN HAPPENING IN DISTRICT
FOUR. >> AND THEY COMMITTED TO ME
THAT EVEN AFTER THIS MOVES FORWARD SO LONG AS THE NUMBER
THE HOUSING NUMBER STAYS THE SAME AND IS COMPLIANT, WE CAN
OFFER FEEDBACK TO THE PLAN SO LONG AS WE IF WE SUBTRACT
ANYWHERE WE NEED TO ADD SOMEWHERE ELSE.
AND I WANT TO BE ABLE TO MOVE THIS FORWARD SO WE ARE NOT
BREAKING ANY DEADLINES AND PUTTING US AT RISK OF THE
STATE COMING IN AND US LOSING OUR LOCAL CONTROL.
WE HAVE SEVERAL DEADLINES COMING UP THAT REALLY PUT US AT
RISK. AND SO I THINK THAT IF WE MOVE
THIS THROUGH RIGHT NOW FOR AT LEAST FOR MY DISTRICT, I WANT
TO BE ABLE TO AT A LATER TIME ALSO BE ABLE TO MAKE
ADJUSTMENTS AS NECESSARY. AS BROUGHT UP BY MY
CONSTITUENTS IN DISTRICT FOUR, I'LL BE SUPPORTING THIS PLAN.
THANK YOU, CHAIRMAN LUGAR. >> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT.
I JUST WANTED AN OPPORTUNITY TO ADDRESS SOME OF THE COMMENTS BY
MY COLLEAGUES AND ALSO ADDRESS THE MOTION ON THE FLOOR BECAUSE
WE DID CONSIDER THIS AT THE LATEST TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE
. SO TO SUPERVISOR WALTON'S
COMMENTS IT IS CORRECT IT IS THEORETICAL.
THIS PLAN DOESN'T BUILD ANY HOUSING.
>> IT ONLY ALLOWS MORE HEIGHTS AND MORE DENSITY.
IT DOES NOT BUILD BUT IT IS A FACT AND A REALITY THAT
CURRENTLY TODAY THE ZONING ON THE WEST SIDE AND THE NORTH OF
THE CITY DOES NOT PERMIT IT. IT IS ILLEGAL.
IT IS NOT POSSIBLE. SO THIS IS WHY WE HAVE TO DO
THIS MOST CERTAINLY AS SUPERVISOR FIELDER DESPITE
SOME, YOU KNOW, STATEMENTS DONE BY A FORMER MEMBER OF THIS
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> THIS PLAN DOES INCLUDE
SEACLIFF AND IT DOES INCLUDE JORDAN PARK AND ALSO SAINT
FRANCIS WOODS AND COW HOLLOW AND WEST PORTAL.
IT INCLUDES THE MARINA. IT INCLUDES ALL OF THOSE
NEIGHBORS. ALL THOSE ARE EACH ONE
DIMENSIONS NOW ARE A DENSITY CONTROLLED AND WILL ALLOW UP TO
SEVEN UNITS IN THAT SAME BULK IN HEIGHT.
SO IT MOST CERTAINLY DOES. I ALSO WANT TO ADDRESS THIS
NUMBER OF 20,000 BECAUSE IT'S BEEN THROWN AROUND QUITE A BIT.
>> SO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT DOES NOT KEEP THE DATA OF
TENURE. THAT IS SOMETHING THAT WE CAN
GET FROM THE CENSUS. BUT IT IS AN APPROXIMATION.
WE DO NOT HAVE THAT DATA. WE KNOW WHICH PARCELS HOLD TWO
UNITS OR MULTIFAMILY HOUSING BUT WE DON'T KNOW WHETHER THOSE
TWO UNITS ARE A SINGLE FAMILY HOME WITH AN EDU TWO CONDOS OR
TENANCIES AND COMMONS OR WHETHER THEIR RENT CONTROLLED
UNITS BUILT BEFORE 1970. WE JUST DON'T HAVE THAT DATA.
SO THAT 20,000 NUMBER IS EVERYTHING.
IT INCLUDES CO-OPS. IT INCLUDES CONDOS.
IT INCLUDES TENANCIES AND COMMENTS.
IT INCLUDES SINGLE FAMILY HOMES WITH 80 YOUTH.
WE DO NOT KNOW WHETHER IT INCLUDES SINGLE FAMILY HOMES
WITH UDY USE BECAUSE WE JUST THEY'RE ILLEGAL BY DEFINITION.
IF YOU WATCH THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE
YOU KNOW THAT THE PROCESS THAT WE WENT THROUGH TO DECIDE WHICH
AMENDMENTS WERE ADOPTED IN WHICH WERE NOT.
WE WENT THROUGH A THOROUGH AND VERY DISCIPLINED PROCESS TO
ASSESS THE LOSS OF CAPACITY OR THE CREATION OF NEW CONSTRAINTS
FOR EVERY SINGLE AMENDMENT. >> WE LOOKED AT IT.
>> WE WANT TO FIGHT IT. WE GOT ON THE PHONE WITH HPD
AND WE RAN IT THROUGH WHETHER OR NOT WE WERE LOOKING AT IT
CORRECTLY OR NOT. AND IN FACT A BUNCH OF THE
AMENDMENTS THAT WERE KIND OF IFFY THEY TOLD US OH, I DON'T
KNOW, THIS THING MIGHT BE A NEW CONSTRAINT OR IT MIGHT BE LOSS
OF CAPACITY. WE STILL ADOPTED THEM BECAUSE
IT WAS WORTH IT FROM A PUBLIC POLICY PERSPECTIVE.
MANY OF SUPERVISOR CHANS AMENDMENTS AND SOME SUPERVISOR
CHEN'S AMENDMENTS WEREN'T INCLUDED IN THIS FASHION.
THE AMENDMENT THAT PUT BACK THE UNIT MIX REQUIREMENTS WAS AN
AMENDMENT THAT EACH SIDE ACTUALLY FLAGGED AND WE
INCLUDED IT BECAUSE IT WAS IMPORTANT TO HAVE FAMILY SIZED
UNITS IN THIS PLAN. I WANT TO CLARIFY TO THE
AMENDMENT THAT I BELIEVE IN RENT CONTROL THE IMPORTANCE
OF CRIME CONTROL IN PREVENTING DEMOLITIONS.
I COULDN'T AGREE MORE. I THINK THERE HAS BEEN A
DELIBERATE MISLEADING OF THE PUBLIC ON THIS TOPIC.
MANY PEOPLE ARE UNDERSTANDABLY UPSET ABOUT THE PROSPECT OF
DEMOLISHING RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING TO BUILD HIGHER BUT THE
FAMILY ZONING PLAN DOES NOT TOUCH THE PROCESS OF WHETHER
ONE IS GIVEN PERMISSION TO DEMOLISH A UNIT OR NOT.
BECAUSE WHETHER WE LIKE IT OR NOT AS SUPERVISOR FIELDER
STATED SB 330 AUTHORED BY STATE SENATOR SKINNER IN 2019 GAVE
ANYONE THE RIGHT TO DEMOLISH IT AS LONG AS YOU ADD ONE
ADDITIONAL UNIT OF HOUSING. WE MOVING TWO UNIT BUILDINGS
FROM THE LOCAL PROGRAM ALSO WILL NOT PROHIBIT DEMOLITION
BUT IT WILL KNOCK US ENTIRE PLANT OUR ENTIRE PLANT OUT OF
COMPLIANCE WITH HPD BECAUSE WE CAN'T SUPPORT THESE NUMBERS.
>> WE DO NOT HAVE THAT DATA. WE DO NOT KNOW HOW MANY PARCELS
HAVE TWO UNITS A SINGLE FAMILY HOME WITH A NEW TO YOU AND WE
CAN ESTIMATE THAT THERE'S MANY, MANY MORE WE JUST CANNOT
QUANTIFY IT NOR SUPPORTED THIS .
MANY PEOPLE HAVE SINGLE FAMILY HOMES WITH UNPERMITTED UNITS.
THIS IS A DIRECT RESULT OF A HOUSING CRISIS COUPLED WITH
ZONING AND BUILDING RESTRICTIONS AND PEOPLE FOR
DECADES WHO HAVE GONE OUTSIDE OF THE RULES TO DEAL WITH THIS
HOUSING SHORTAGE AND MAKE DO WE NEED TO PROTECT RENTERS AND WE
NEED TO PROTECT TENANTS AND WE NEED TO DO IT RESPONSIBLY
IN THE WAY THAT WILL BE EFFECTIVE.
THE FAMILY ZONING PLAN IS FOCUSED ON SETTING ALLOWABLE
FACE HEIGHTS OF THE LOTS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE CITY
AND ON MAKING IT MORE ATTRACTIVE THAN THE STATE
PROGRAM. THAT'S HOW WE GET ALL THESE
GOODIES AFFORDABLE HOUSING, WARM SHELTER, SMALL BUSINESSES,
RENT CONTROL ALL OF THESE THINGS WE GET BECAUSE WE ARE
GIVING SOMETHING IN THE ZONING PROGRAM AT THE LAND USE
COMMITTEE. WE ARE STILL TOILING AWAY AT
SUPERVISOR CHEN'S TENANT PROTECTION ORDINANCE TO MAKE IT
A STRONG THING AS LEGALLY POSSIBLE.
THERE WILL BE SOME FINAL TWEAKS TO THE LANGUAGE NEXT WEEK.
>> WE'VE BEEN WORKING WITH THE ADVOCATES AND WE HAVE FOCUSED A
LOT OF OUR ENERGY TO PROTECT TENANTS AND BUILDINGS FROM
DEMOLITION AS MUCH AS WE CAN FOR THE PUBLIC WHO MAY HAVE
READ IT. >> SUPERVISOR CHEN'S
LEGISLATION INCLUDES SECTION 317 OF OUR PLANNING CODE WHERE
WE DEFINE WHAT QUALIFIES AS A DEMOLITION.
BEYOND THAT, NEXT YEAR I INTEND TO WORK WITH OUR STATE
REPRESENTATIVES TO REFORM SB 330 WHICH HAS OVERWRITTEN SOME
OF OUR LOCAL TENANT LAWS. US AND SOME OTHER
MUNICIPALITIES AROUND THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA WHO HAVE STRONG
RENT CONTROL LAWS FOR SOME MUNICIPALITIES SB 330 WAS
GROUNDBREAKING AND AN EVOLUTION AND MUCH BETTER THAN WHAT THEY
HAD BEFORE BUT NOT QUITE FOR US.
I WILL SPEAK TO THIS MORE AT DURING ROLL CALL BUT AFTER ALL
THEY ARE THERE TO PROTECT SAN FRANCISCO'S INTERESTS AND IF A
LAW ISN'T WORKING WELL FOR US WE SHOULD WE SHOULD PUT SOME
ATTENTION TO IT AND I COMMIT THAT WE WILL DO THAT.
I THINK THAT OUR TIME IS BETTER SPENT AFFECTING REAL CHANGE AT
THE STATE LEVEL THAT ACTUALLY ACCOMPLISH WHAT WE WANT THAN
BEING COUNTERPRODUCTIVE IN HOW WE ARE DOING OUR ZONING CODES.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU
SO MUCH SUPERVISOR AND CHAIR MELGAR JUST TO CLARIFY MY
QUESTION WAS WHY ARE WE UP ZONING SITES WHERE RENT
CONTROLLED TENANTS LIVE IN NOT BILLIONAIRES ROW ST FRANCIS
WOODS SEACLIFF THESE LOCATIONS MIGHT BE SUBJECT TO DENSITY
DECONTROL BUT THAT IS NOT UP ZONING AS IS AS ARE THE PARCELS
WITH RENT CONTROLLED UNITS. >> THANK YOU.
>> OKAY. >> IF I'M IF I'M LAST ON THE
MOTION I MEAN I I, I DO THINK THAT THIS COMMUNITIES BELIEVE
THAT DENSITY DECONTROL IS UP ZONING ALTHOUGH I STRONGLY
SUPPORT DENSITY DECONTROL I THINK THOSE COMMUNIT THERE ARE
COMMUNITY COMMUNITIES ON THE WEST SIDE THAT ARE RECEIVING
THIS ARE AT LEAST IN SOME MEASURE EXPRESSING CONCERN.
I DO HAVE A QUESTION. >> CHAIR MELGAR IF YOU WILLING
TO ENTERTAIN A QUESTION YOU HAD SAID THAT THE COMMITTEE HAD
CONSIDERED THIS AMENDMENT BUT I DON'T THINK THIS PARTICULAR
AMENDMENT WAS EVER INTRODUCED IN COMMITTEE.
AM I WRONG ABOUT THAT? >> NO.
THE COMMITTEE DID NOT CONSIDER THE AMENDMENT THAT SUPERVISED
OR CHAN INTRODUCED TODAY. OKAY.
THANK YOU FOR THAT CLARIFICATION.
OKAY. BEFORE I SAY ANYTHING ELSE, JAN
,IT WAS SIMPLY BECAUSE THE AMENDMENT BY THE WAY IS LEGAL
AND SIGNED LIKE APPROVED TO FORM BY CITY ATTORNEY BECAUSE
OUR ORIGINAL WAS REALLY BROAD. ORIGINAL AMENDMENTS WAS TO NOT
DO NO DEMOLITION FOR ANY PROJECT WHOP THAT NO PROJECT
SHOULD BE ALLOWED SHOULD THEY HAVE DEMOLITION OF DWELLING
UNITS AND RESIDENTIAL FLATS. SO IT IS MUCH BROADER WHERE
TODAY WE ARE SIMPLY TO TACK ON THE AMENDMENTS THAT SUPERVISOR
CHAIR MELGAR ACTUALLY HAD PROPOSED WHICH IS NO DEMOLITION
FOR ANY BUILDINGS THAT HAS THREE OR MORE RENT CONTROL
UNITS TO BE SO TO TACK ON THAT WE'RE SAYING WELL THEN YOU KNOW
LET'S PROTECT RESIDENTIAL FLAT THAT ARE RENT CONTROL AND THAT
IS OUR AMENDMENT TODAY BASED ON THAT IF I MAY THOUGH TO SAY
IT'S REALLY A POLICY DECISION THAT WE'RE MAKING, IT'S IT'S AS
PARTICULARLY ON THIS AMENDMENT THAT I'M PROPOSING IS A POLICY
DECISION TO SAY WHETHER WE'RE GOING TO PROTECT ALL RENT
CONTROL UNITS FROM DEMOLITION OR ONLY THE 80,000 UNITS OR
JUST WHATEVER IT IS THE THREE UNITS OR MORE BUILDINGS WHAT
RENT CONTROL UNITS? IT'S A POLICY DECISION THAT
WE'RE MAKING AND I'M ASKING US TO MAKE TODAY.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SHAN IF I'M LAST I
AM NOT SURE THAT THIS IS THE FORUM OR PLACE TO MAKE THAT
PARTICULAR POLICY DECISION IN ONE SENSE THAT YOU KNOW OF
COURSE WE COULD ACT ON THIS AMENDMENT TODAY BUT FOR THE FOR
THE FOLKS AT HOME AND I WANT TO START BY EXPRESSING A LOT OF
GRATITUDE FOR CHURCH AND FOR CHURCH.
I'M SURE MELGAR AND THE MEMBERS OF THE COMMITTEE SUPERVISORS
MAHMOOD AND CHEN FOR OF COURSE FOR MEETINGS OF THE LAND USE
COMMITTEE BUT A LOT MORE WORK THAN THAT AND SOME OF THE WORK
THAT WAS INVOLVED IN THIS WAS CHAIR MELGAR.
>> I THINK GETTING ON THE PHONE, GETTING ON THE ZOOM WITH
WITH STATE DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT WHICH HAS BEEN CLOSELY WATCHING THIS PROCESS
AND SAN FRANCISCO SAN FRANCISCO IS UNDER IS VIEWED BY THE STATE
RIGHTLY OR WRONGLY I BELIEVE WRONGLY BUT IS VIEWED BY THE
STATE AS A PARTICULARLY BAD ACTOR THAT NEEDS PARTICULAR
OVERSIGHT. AND AND SO ALL OF THIS HAS BEEN
CAREFULLY NEGOTIATED WITH THE STATE AND JERRY MELGAR HAS BEEN
DOING THAT NEGOTIATION AND TO THE EXTENT THAT SHE'S BEEN ABLE
TO GET AMENDMENTS SOME OF WHICH CAME FROM ME APPROVED THROUGH
THAT PROCESS I'M I ALSO WANT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE FOR THAT.
>> MY UNDERSTANDING FROM THE CONFERENCE, FROM SPEAKING WITH
PLANNING AND SPEAKING WITH CHAIR MELGAR HAS BEEN THAT HK
IS INDIFFERENT LARGELY INDIFFERENT TO THE PARTICULAR
CONSTRAINTS THAT WE PUT INTO THIS INTO THIS LEGISLATION THAT
AS LONG AS WE'RE CREATING THE ADDITIONAL CAPACITY THAT WE ARE
COMMITTED TO ON OUR HOUSING ELEMENT WE CAN DO IT JUST ABOUT
ANY WAY WE WANT TO AS LONG AS THEY'RE PERSUADED THAT IT'S
REAL WE CAN CAN PROVIDE ADDITIONAL PROTECTIONS OR
CONSTRAINTS AROUND DEMOLITION OF RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING.
WE CAN PROTECT EVERY SINGLE HISTORIC RESOURCE IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. WE CAN DO ALL OF THESE THINGS
BUT AS WE DO THOSE THINGS WE HAVE TO IDENTIFY THE ADDITIONAL
CAPACITY SO THAT THE UNITS THAT WE'RE TAKING OFF THE BOARD ARE
MADE UP FOR BY UNITS COMING ONTO THE BOARD IN THAT REGARD I
HAVE SAID THAT THIS BOARD THAT I THOUGHT THIS BOARD WAS GOING
TO NEED TO APPROVE SOMETHING GENERALLY IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
OF WHAT MAYOR LEARY AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT PROPOSED
FOR SOME TIME NOW I THINK WE MADE SOME DECISIONS EARLY ON TO
CUT SWATHS OF THE CITY OUT OF THIS UP ZONING THAT I THINK MAY
NOT HAVE ACTUALLY BEEN CORRECT .
I THINK THERE ARE PARTS OF THE CITY THAT HAVE NOT UNDERGONE
PRIOR REZONING THAT WERE EXCLUDED FROM THIS PLAN THAT WE
REALLY OUGHT TO LOOK AT UP ZONING.
I FRANKLY FOR MY FRIENDS TO THE WEST OF TWIN PEAKS THINK THAT
WE MAY HAVE GONE A LITTLE LATE ON ON YOU FOLKS.
I THINK WE MADE A LOT OF DECISIONS AND TOOK A LOT OF
STUFF OFF THE TABLE THAT GOT US TO THE SITUATION WHEN THIS
FINALLY CAME TO THE LAND USE COMMITTEE FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION BEGINNING A COUPLE OF MONTHS AGO YOU WERE
IN A TIGHT LITTLE UNIVERSE OF WHERE YOU COULD ADDRESS MY
DEMANDS TO PRESERVE HISTORIC RESOURCES EVERYONE'S DEMANDS TO
PRESERVE, TO PRESERVE RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING ALL THE
THINGS THAT WE WANT TO DO. >> AND IN THAT ENVIRONMENT I
THINK YOU DID THE BEST THAT YOU COULD.
>> IT IS POSSIBLE THAT IF THIS PARTICULAR AMENDMENT HAD BEEN
PROPOSED TWO MONTHS AGO MAYBE AND I THINK THIS IS PROBABLY NO
BUT YOU KNOW THERE MIGHT HAVE BEEN SOME UNIVERSE IN WHICH WE
COULD HAVE CRIBBED AND CRABBED AND SOMEHOW PUT BECAUSE THIS IS
A MANY THOUSANDS OF UNITS THE IMPLICATIONS OF THIS ARE MANY
THOUSANDS OF UNITS THAT ARE NOT CURRENTLY IN THE PLAN AND WE
WOULD HAVE HAD TO FIND THOSE SOMEWHERE.
WE ARE NOT GOING TO BE ABLE TO DO THAT BETWEEN NOW AND THE END
OF THE MONTH AND SO I DON'T THINK THAT I CAN SUPPORT THIS
AMENDMENT BUT TO SUPERVISOR WONG'S POINT, THIS IS NOT THE
END OF THE STORY. WE CAN AND SHOULD PURSUE FUTURE
UP ZONING NEXT YEAR, CREATE ADDITIONAL CAPACITY AND FIX
THINGS THAT MAYBE IN SHORT OUGHT TO BE FIXED WHICH COULD
INCLUDE TAKING THIS OF BRINGING IN SUPERVISOR CHAN'S AMENDMENT
SOMETIME NEXT YEAR WE WOULD HAVE TO HAVE A POLICY ARGUMENT
AT THAT POINT ABOUT WHETHER THAT IS ACTUALLY A GOOD IDEA
BECAUSE THE IMPLICATION OF THIS THIS DOES NOT PROTECT THESE
UNITS FROM DEMOLITION. IT TAKES THESE UNITS OUT OF THE
LOCAL PROGRAM, THE LOCAL PROGRAM IS BEING PROPOSED TO
PROVIDE INCENTIVES TO TO TO ENCOURAGE DEVELOPERS TO AVOID
USING THE STATE DENSITY BONUS PROGRAM, THE STATE DENSITY
BONUS PROGRAM IS RESPONSIBLE FOR SOME OF THE MOST BIZARRE
PROPOSALS FOR VERY TALL BUILDINGS THAT LOOK NOTHING
LIKE OUR ZONING AND IN FACT MUCH WE LOOK MUCH MORE LIKE
BUILDERS REMEDY THAN ANYTHING ALLOWED IN OUR LOCAL REMOTELY
ALLOWED IN OUR LOCAL PROGRAM. SO WE'RE PUSHING PEOPLE AWAY TO
THE EXTENT WE GO DOWN THIS PATH OF TAKING THINGS OUT OF THE
LOCAL PROGRAM WE ARE ENCOURAGING DEVELOPERS,
PROPERTY OWNERS TO GO DOWN ALTERNATIVE STATE PATHS WHICH
IN MY VIEW ARE LESS DESIRABLE FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
SO I'M WILLING TO THINK ABOUT THIS AMENDMENT.
I'M WILLING TO THINK ABOUT IT NEXT YEAR IN THE CONTEXT OF
ADDITIONAL UP ZONING TO LOOK FOR MORE CAPACITY IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO WHICH I THINK WE SHOULD DO BUT
I DON'T THINK I CAN VOTE FOR IT TODAY.
AND SO IF THERE ARE NO MORE COMMENTS WE SHOULD PROBABLY
VOTE ON THE MOTION. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION ON THE AMENDMENT TO ITEM NUMBER
38. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MY MY BALLOT NO SUPERVISOR
GENTLEMAN NO AMENDMENT NO SUPERVISOR MILL GUARD NO NO
GUARD NO SUPERVISOR SADR SADR NO SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG NO WONG NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO THERE ARE FOUR EYES AND SEVEN
NOSE WITH SUPERVISOR WAS MAHMOOD MENDELSOHN MELGAR SADR
CHERYL WANG AND DORSEY VOTING NO THE MOTION FAILS.
ALL RIGHT COLLEAGUES MORE COMMENTS OR DISCUSSION ON ITEMS
3638 OR ARE WE TIRED? WE WE MAY WE MAY HAVE HAD
ENOUGH. ALL RIGHT THEN I'M GOING TO
OFFER JUST A FEW MORE JUST A COUPLE MORE COMMENTS I WANT TO
FOR MY PART ON THE LEGISLATION AGAIN THANK THE COMMITTEE BUT I
REALLY WANT TO THANK THE PLANNING STAFF WHO HAVE HAD TO
DEAL WITH ME AND THANK YOU DIRECTOR SARAH DENNIS PHILLIPS
AND JOSH SLUTSKY AND LISA AND RACHEL FOR FOR THE ENRICH
THROUGH CRAIG'S OVER THERE WITH THE WITH THE HISTORIC
PRESERVATION TEAM I EXPRESSED I'VE HAD CONCERN AND IT'S LESS
ABOUT THE PLAN ITSELF THAN THE WAY IN WHICH STATE LAWS COULD
INTERACT WITH INCREASED CAPACITY IS ALLOWED UNDER THE
PLAN AND LEAD TO THE DEMOLITION OF HISTORIC RESOURCES.
AND I GOT REALLY CONCERNED THAT GIVEN ALL THE OTHER CONSTRAINTS
THAT HAD COME INTO THIS PLAN THROUGH DECISIONS OVER THE LAST
FEW YEARS THAT WE WERE REALLY DOING THIS MAKING A PLAN FOR
THE YOU KNOW, TO MEET OUR TO MEET OUR HOUSING NEEDS THROUGH
MINISTERIAL DEMOLITION OF OUR HISTORIC RESOURCES WHICH WOULD
BE A REALLY BAD THING IN MY VIEW AND I AM STILL WORRIED
ABOUT THAT BUT I AM GRATEFUL FOR THE COLLABORATION AROUND A
COUPLE OF AMENDMENTS THAT WENT IN AND COLLEAGUES THANK YOU.
THANK YOU TO THE LAND USE COMMITTEE AGAIN FOR MAKING
THOSE AMENDMENTS AND THEN THANK YOU CHAIR MELGAR FOR CARRYING
MAKING THE CASE STAGE CITY BUT REALLY THANKS TO TO THE
PLANNING STAFF AND CALVIN IN MY OFFICE FOR FOR THINKING
THROUGH THERE WAS AMENDMENTS AND ALSO THINKING THROUGH MORE
BROADLY ADAM TALKS ABOUT I AM HOPING THAT THIS BY THE END OF
THIS MONTH THAT WE WILL MANAGE TO MAKE SOME ANNOUNCEMENTS WITH
THE MAYOR ABOUT YOU KNOW SOME BROADER COMMITMENTS AROUND
HISTORIC PRESERVATION GOING FORWARD BECAUSE I DO THINK THIS
DENSITY CAN MAKE THE CITY BETTER DENSITY CAN MAKE OUR
PLANNING, OUR TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS BETTER.
>> DENSITY OF COURSE CAN HELP ADDRESS OUR HOUSING CRISIS.
BUT I WORRY IN A DENSELY BUILT OUT HISTORIC CITY THAT WE COULD
LOSE SOME OF THE SOME OF THE HISTORIC RESOURCES THAT ARE
REALLY IMPORTANT TO OUR NEIGHBORHOODS, TO THE CHARACTER
OF OUR CITY. AND I DON'T THINK WE WANT TO DO
THAT. AND GIVEN THE CURRENT CONTEXT
OF OUR STATE LAWS WE NEED TO GET AHEAD OF THIS SOONER RATHER
THAN LATER. SO THANK YOU FOR ALL OF THAT.
THANK YOU TO THE HISTORIC PRESERVATION COMMUNITY SAFE
HERITAGE FOR FOR THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS TO OUR HISTORIC
PLANNING DISTRICT PRESERVATION COMMISSIONERS WHO ARE GEMS
AND WHO HAD A LOT OF GOOD THOUGHTS ABOUT THIS PLAN HOW TO
MAKE IT BETTER. I JUST WANT TO EXTEND A LOT OF
THANKS ON THAT. IS THIS THE PERFECT PLAN OR IS
IT THE PLAN THAT I WOULD HAVE WRITTEN IF I WERE THE ZONING
CZAR FOR SAN FRANCISCO? NOW IS IT GOOD ENOUGH?
YES. AND THIS IS A CASE WHERE I
DON'T THINK THE PERFECT SHOULD BE THE ENEMY OF THE GOOD ENOUGH
AND FOR THOSE WHO WORKED ON IT, THANK YOU VERY, VERY MUCH FOR
ALL THAT YOU'VE DONE TO GET US THROUGH A REALLY HARD PROJECT.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS
36 THROUGH 38 SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MENDHAM HIGH MENDHAM
AND I SUPERVISOR MILL GUARD I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SOLDER
SOLDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON NO SUPERVISOR WONG YES WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN NO
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND FOUR NOS WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER
WALTON CHAN AND CHEN VOTING NO THESE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON
FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE LET'S GO TO ITEM 39 YES
ITEMS 39 AND 40 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE RULES COMMITTEE AT A
REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY DECEMBER FIRST, 2025
AND RECOMMENDED TO THE FULL BOARD TODAY ITEM 39 IT IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO
ELIMINATE THE FOLSOM STREET ENTERTAINMENT ZONE AND CREATE
THE WEST SOMA ENTERTAINMENT ZONE IN AFFIRMING THE SQUARE
DETERMINATION PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 39 SUPERVISOR
FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR
GENTLEMAN HI MENZEL MEAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SARDAR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WANG WANG I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION
THIS ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM 40 I DID MEMBER 40 WAS AMENDED TO STRIKE
REJECTING FROM THE MOTION AND IT IS NOW A MOTION
APPROVING THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS RAFAEL
MENDELSSOHN'S NOMINATION OF ROBIN ABAD BELLO FOR
APPOINTMENT TO THE BOARD OF APPEALS FOR A TERM ENDING JULY
1ST, 2026 AND WE'LL TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THIS MOTION IS APPROVED AND WE'LL GO BACK
TO ROLL CALL MADAM CLERK AND I THINK WE WERE ON SUPERVISOR
MELGAR YES. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR, YOUR NEXT
STEP. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK
PRESIDENT COLLEAGUES AS I HAD SPOKEN ABOUT EARLIER TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING THE STATE TO AMEND THE HOUSING
CRISIS ACT MOST COMMONLY KNOWN AS SB 330 SO THAT WE CAN GO
FURTHER TO PROTECT TENANTS AND RENT CONTROLLED UNITS FROM
DEMOLITION. >> THIS STATE LAW WAS CREATED
TO ALLOW STREAMLINED APPROVAL TO DEMOLISH EXISTING STRUCTURES
IN ORDER TO BUILD MORE UNITS ON THE SAME LOT.
IT INCLUDES PROVISIONS TO TEMPORARILY RELOCATE TENANTS
IN COMPENSATE THEM DURING THE REBUILD.
>> FOR SOME CITIES THIS LEGISLATION HELPS EXISTING
TENANTS WHILE SPURRING DEVELOPMENT OF MORE UNITS ON
UNDERUTILIZED LOT. HOWEVER WITHIN CITIES LIKE OURS
WITH OLDER TENANT LAWS IT ACTUALLY HAS UNDONE SOME LONG
STANDING PRINCIPLES DUE TO UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES IN THE
STATE PREEMPTION. MOST IMPORTANTLY SB 330 ALLOWS
YOU TO DEMOLISH EXISTING RENT CONTROLLED BUILDINGS AS LONG AS
YOU PROMISE TO REPLACE THOSE UNITS AND ADD AT LEAST ONE MORE
UNIT. >> BUT THE LOOKBACK PERIOD FOR
TENANT OCCUPANCY IS ONLY FIVE YEARS SO IT CREATES AN
INCENTIVE TO JUST LEAVE THE UNITS VACANT FOR FIVE YEARS TO
GET AROUND REPLACEMENT UNITS AND TENANT RIGHTS.
EVEN SB 79 HAS A SEVEN YEAR LOOKBACK WHILE SB 423 HAS A TEN
YEAR LOOKBACK. SB 330 WAS ALSO AMENDED BY ITS
AUTHOR TO EXCLUDE TENANTS WHO MAKE MORE THAN LOW INCOME
TENANTS FROM THE RELOCATION ASSISTANCE AND RIGHT OF RETURN
WHICH IS NOT CONSISTENT WITH OUR FUNDAMENTAL PRINCIPLES IN A
RENT CONTROL IN SAN FRANCISCO EVEN FOR LOW INCOME TENANTS
THERE IS NO REQUIREMENT THAT THEIR RENTAL UNITS ARE ACTUALLY
REPLACED WITH RENTAL UNITS. THEY CAN BECOME CONDOS INSTEAD
SO THE RIGHT TO PURCHASE INSTEAD MAY NOT BE POSSIBLE OR
DESIRED IF YOU CARE ABOUT EXISTING TENANTS AND PROTECTING
RENT CONTROL RENTAL UNITS ALONG WITH A SMALL BUSINESSES WITHIN
THEM, I URGE YOU TO CO-SPONSOR THIS RESOLUTION AND WORK WITH
ME WITH OUR STATE ASSEMBLY PERSON FROM 8017 WHO IS THE
CHAIR OF THE HOUSING COMMITTEE .
I AM COMMITTED TO SEEING THIS THROUGH AND I HOPE THAT YOU
WILL SUPPORT THIS AS WELL. >> ADDITIONALLY, I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION URGING THE LURIE ADMINISTRATION TO
DEVELOP A PLATFORM AND STRATEGY TO SUPPORT THE SAFETY
AND HEALTH OF WOMEN AND ADVANCED GENDER EQUITY
IN OUR CITY. I WANT TO ECHO THE SENTIMENTS
SHARED BY SOME OF MY COLLEAGUES ABOUT THE HORRIFIC ABUSE
AND DEHUMANIZING ACTS THAT WE LEARNED ABOUT IN OUR JAIL.
IT SADDENS ME. IT SADDENS ME GREATLY
AND NAUSEATED ME AND IT ALSO ENRAGED ME WHAT ALLOWS THE
TYPES OF HEINOUS ACTS IS A PERVASIVE CULTURE THAT DEVALUES
THE RIGHTS OF WOMEN. I AM INTRODUCING THIS
RESOLUTION TO REQUEST THAT THIS ADMINISTRATION DEVELOP
AND CLARIFY THE VISION FOR WOMEN SUCCESS IN THE CITY.
WE MAKE UP 50% OF THE POPULATION OF OUR CITY AND WE
DEFINITELY KNOW THAT WE HOLD UP MORE THAN HALF THE SKY.
I WANT US TO TAKE A REAL HONEST LOOK AT OURSELVES AS A CITY
THAT CLAIMS TO SUPPORT WOMEN AND GIRLS.
IN THE PAST YEAR WE HAVE DEMOTED THE DEPARTMENT OF THE
STATUS OF WOMEN WITH AN INDEPENDENT OVERSIGHT
COMMISSION TO A BRANCH OF THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION, A
DEPARTMENT WITH A MAN AS ITS CURRENT DIRECTOR IN OUR CITY
WOMEN MAKE $0.78 FOR EVERY DOLLAR A MAN MAKES.
WE HAVE MADE PROMISES TO WOMEN ABOUT WORKFORCE ABOUT EQUITY,
ABOUT ACCESS TO CAPITAL FOR WOMEN OWNED BUSINESSES BUT
PILOT PROGRAMS HAVE EXPIRED AND THAT DISPARITY STILL
PERSIST. WE PROMISED VOTERS UNIVERSAL
CHILDCARE FOUR YEARS AGO AND WE STILL HAVE NOT DELIVERED
DESPITE HAVING ALMOST $500 MILLION JUST SITTING IN THAT
FUND. SAN FRANCISCO TODAY HAS THE
WORST HEALTH DISPARITIES OR PREMATURE BIRTH RATES
AND INFANT MORTALITY RATES FOR BLACK WOMEN AND BABIES IN THE
STATE OF CALIFORNIA. WE PROMISE CIVIL DEFENSE FOR
VICTIMS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE. WHEN WE PASSED PROPOSITION D WE
STILL HAVE NOT DELIVERED RESOURCES TO PREVENT GENDER
BASED VIOLENCE AND HARASSMENT CONTINUE TO BE UNDERFUNDED
AND DIMINISHED. >> TWO WEEKS AGO TIPPING POINT
PUT OUT A REPORT ON HOW POVERTY IN SAN FRANCISCO IN THE BAY
AREA IS AT AN ALL TIME HIGH. WE HAVE GONE BACKWARDS BUT
COLLEAGUES THE FACE OF POVERTY IN SAN FRANCISCO AND IN
CALIFORNIA IS A WOMAN USUALLY A SINGLE MOM RECEIVING FOOD
STAMPS AND MEDICAID. WE CANNOT WITH A STRAIGHT FACE
SAY THAT WE CARE ABOUT POVERTY OR PUBLIC SAFETY WITHOUT
ADDRESSING THE SPECIFIC ISSUES OF POVERTY AND THE SAFETY OF
WOMEN. A FEW YEARS AGO THE THEN
DEPARTMENT OF THE STATUS OF WOMEN EVOLVED FROM AN AGENCY
THAT CONCENTRÉ ON GRANT MAKING SUPPORTING WOMEN EXPERIENCING
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE AND HUMAN TRAFFICKING TO A DEPARTMENT
THAT HELD OUR CITY ACCOUNTABLE TO UPHOLD THE HUMAN RIGHTS
IN THE SUCCESS OF WOMEN IN OUR CITY WE EVOLVED FROM SEEING
AND ADDRESSING WOMEN ONLY AS VICTIMS TO A VISION OF WOMEN A
SUCCESSFUL AGENCIES IN THEIR SUCCESS AND SELF-DETERMINATION
. THIS GOES BEYOND ONE DEPARTMENT
WE NEED A PLATFORM THAT IS ADMINISTERED THROUGH OUR
CULTURE AS A CITY AND ACROSS OUR DEPARTMENTS.
>> THIS MUST COME FROM THE ADMINISTRATION'S LEADERSHIP.
I WANT TO KNOW WHAT IS OUR VISION NOW?
HOW WILL THE NEW ORGANIZATIONAL CHANGES SUPPORT THAT VISION?
WHAT IS OUR ROLE IN WHAT IS NEEDED?
WHAT DOES ACCOUNTABILITY FOR WOMEN'S RIGHTS LOOK LIKE?
>> I LOOK FORWARD TO HEARING CLARITY SUPPORTING OUR
COLLECTIVE EFFORTS AND I WILL BE INTRODUCING A PACKAGE THAT
WILL LAY OUT THESE QUESTIONS AND HOPEFULLY COMPEL AN
ACTIONABLE PLAN. AND FINALLY I HAVE SOME VERY
SAD NEWS TODAY WE PAUSE TO HONOR THE LIFE OF CLAUDE THE
ALBINO ALLIGATOR FOR A ONE OF A KIND SAN FRANCISCO ICON WHO
BROUGHT A SMILE A SENSE OF WONDER IN MORE THAN A FEW
SURPRISES TO EVERYONE THAT CROSSED THIS PATH OUR ALLIGATOR
WITH A MELLOW DEMEANOR CLYDE'S JOURNEY TO SAN FRANCISCO BEGAN
FAR FROM HERE IN THE BAYOUS OF LOUISIANA.
CLYDE WAS HATCHED IN 1995. HE EVENTUALLY FOUND A HOME
IN THE CALIFORNIA ACADEMY OF SCIENCES.
>> CLAUDE AND ALL OF SAN FRANCISCO CELEBRATED HIS 30TH
HATCH DAY IN SEPTEMBER A JOYFUL MILESTONE THAT REMINDED US OF
HOW REMARKABLE HIS LIFE TRULY WAS IN A CITY KNOWN FOR ITS
CHARACTERS, HUMAN AND OTHERWISE, CLYDE STOOD OUT
AS A REMINDER THAT EVEN THE MOST UNEXPECTED RESIDENTS CAN
CAPTURE OUR HEARTS. HE BECAME MORE THAN JUST AN
EXHIBIT OR CURIOSITY. HE BECAME OUR SHARED COMMUNITY
STORY FOR COUNTLESS VISITORS ESPECIALLY FOR YOUNG PEOPLE
ESPECIALLY MY KIDS. CLAUDE SPARKED CURIOSITY ABOUT
WILDLIFE RESPECT FOR NATURE AND THE IMPORTANCE OF
PROTECTING THE NATURAL WORLD ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO, I WANT TO EXTEND OUR DEEPEST THANKS TO
THE STAFF AT THE CALIFORNIA ACADEMY OF SCIENCES AND THE
DEDICATED ANIMAL CARE PROFESSIONALS WHO LOVINGLY
CARED FOR CLAUDE THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE AND SHARE THEM WITH
GENERATIONS OF VISITORS. >> TODAY WE SAY GOODBYE TO A
REMARKABLE AMBASSADOR WHO REMINDED US THAT SAN FRANCISCO
ALWAYS HAS ROOM FOR WONDER AND TO WELCOME THOSE WHO ARE A
LITTLE BIT DIFFERENT SOMETIMES IN THE MOST UNEXPECTED FORMS
THE CALLA ACADEMY PLANS TO HOLD A PUBLIC MEMORIAL IN THE NEAR
FUTURE BUT IN THE MEANTIME ENCOURAGES PEOPLE TO SHARE
THEIR MEMORIES OF CLAUDE AND THE MESSAGES FOR HIS
DEDICATED ANIMAL CARE TEAM BY EMAIL AT CLAUD AT CAL
ACADEMY.ORG. REST IN PEACE CLAUDE YOU WILL
BE REMEMBERED YOU WILL BE MISSED AND THE REST I SUBMIT
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUPERVISOR SAUDER THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHERYL. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A HEARING REQUESTS FOCUSED ON EXPANDING
ELIGIBILITY OF BABY PROP C THE EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION FOR
ALL INITIATIVE. >> NOW I THINK WE ALL ARE VERY
AWARE THAT SAN FRANCISCO HAS THE FEWEST CHILDREN PER CAPITA
OF ANY MAJOR CITY IN THE COUNTRY AND ONE OF THE REASONS
FOR THAT IS THAT IT IS INCREDIBLY UNAFFORDABLE FOR
FAMILIES HERE AND IT'S IMPERATIVE ON THAT MEASURE TO
WORK TO MAKE IT MORE AFFORDABLE ,MORE INVITING FOR FAMILIES TO
START HERE, TO GROW HERE AND THEN TO STAY HERE IN OUR
CITY AND EARLY CHILD CARE AND CHILD EDUCATION IS A
CRITICAL PART OF THAT JOURNEY. THIS PAST JULY THE STANFORD
CENTER ON EARLY CHILDHOOD FOUND THAT 3 IN 4 CALIFORNIAN
FAMILIES WITH YOUNG CHILDREN REPORTED DIFFICULTY MAKING ENDS
MEET WITH CHILD CARE BEING CITED AS ONE OF THE MOST COMMON
HARDSHIPS I DON'T THINK ANYONE LISTENING IS SURPRISED TO HEAR
THAT AND IF THAT IS THE CASE WE SHOULD DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT
IN ORDER TO BRING REAL AFFORDABILITY FOR FAMILIES WE
MUST ADDRESS THESE COSTS HELPING FAMILIES QUALIFY FOR
SUBSIDIZED CHILD CARE IS A DIRECT AND DIRECTLY EFFECTIVE
WAY TO DO SO. CURRENTLY SAN FRANCISCO
FAMILIES EARNING BETWEEN 151% AND 200% AREA MEDIAN INCOME
THAT'S UP TO $311,000 DO NOT QUALIFY FOR A FAMILY OF FOUR.
DO NOT QUALIFY FOR ANY SUBSIDIZED CARE OR TUITION
CREDIT DESPITE BABY PROP C ORIGINALLY INTENDING TO INCLUDE
THESE HOUSEHOLDS. IN ESSENCE, THESE FAMILIES ARE
CAUGHT IN THE MIDDLE. THEY CURRENTLY EARN TOO MUCH TO
QUALIFY FOR ASSISTANCE YET THEY DO NOT EARN NEARLY ENOUGH TO
COMFORTABLY PAY 2000 $3,000 IN MONTHLY CHILD CARE COSTS BY
FULFILLING THE ORIGINAL PROMISE OF BABY PROP C AND SUBSIDIZING
CHILD CARE FOR FAMILIES UNDER 200% AMI WE PROVIDE INSTANT
FINANCIAL RELIEF MAKING SURE SAN FRANCISCANS ARE NOT LIVING
PAYCHECK TO PAYCHECK SOLELY TO CARE FOR THEIR CHILDREN.
MOREOVER, THIS HEARING WILL EXPLORE HOW EXPANDING
ELIGIBILITY CAN BEST SUPPORT OUR CIVIL SERVANTS AND DOWNTOWN
WORKERS HELPING BRING PEOPLE BACK TO DOWNTOWN
AND REVITALIZING OUR ECONOMIC ENGINE.
THIS POLICY IS A WIN WIN. WE HAVE THE MONEY AND WE HAVE
THE CARE INFRASTRUCTURE TO ACCOMPLISH THIS TRANSFORMATIVE
CHANGE. THIS PAST FISCAL YEAR THE
DEPARTMENT OF EARLY CHILDHOOD REPORTED A RESERVE FUND BALANCE
OF $572.5 MILLION A KEY SOURCE GENERATED BY BABY PROP C THAT
CAN CRITICALLY STRENGTHEN THE CITY'S ENTIRE EARLY CHILD CARE
SYSTEM. >> THEREFORE THIS HEARING WILL
BE FOCUSED ON HOW WE CAN UTILIZE THIS EXISTING POOL OF
MONEY TO FULFILL ITS INTENDED MISSION.
>> MAKING SAN FRANCISCO MORE AFFORDABLE, MORE ACCESSIBLE,
MORE ATTRACTIVE FOR THE FAMILIES WHO ARE HERE AND THE
FUTURE GENERATIONS OF FAMILIES. WE'RE BUILDING ROOTS IN OUR
CITY. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
MELGAR WHO HAS WORKED LONG AND HARD ON THIS ISSUE
AND SUPERVISOR WONG FOR THEIR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP ON THIS
HEARING REQUEST. I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH
YOU BOTH ON THIS CHANGE TO CITY POLICY AND WORKING WITH THE
DEPARTMENT ON THIS AS WELL. >> THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR SHERYL SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES TODAY FIRST IN LINE WITH CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHU'S
LAWSUIT AGAINST FOOD AND TOBACCO COMPANIES THAT
DECEPTIVELY PROMOTE ULTRA PROCESSED FOODS AS HEALTHY
AND DISGUISE HEALTH EFFECTS. >> I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
CALLING FOR CERTAIN CITY DEPARTMENTS TO REVIEW THEIR
DISTRIBUTION AND SUPPORT OF ULTRA PROCESSED FOODS DIRECTLY
THROUGH CONTRACTORS AND TO ENSURE ALIGNMENT WITH THE GOALS
OF CALIFORNIA REAL FOODS AND THE HEALTHY KIDS ACT
AND URGING THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO DEVELOP A
FRAMEWORK FOR IDENTIFYING AND EVALUATE ULTRA PROCESSED
FOODS FOR THE CITY TO USE IN DECISIONS CONCERNING FOOD
DISTRIBUTION AND PROCURE PERMIT AND FOR REPORTING PURPOSES.
OUR COMMUNITIES HAVE LIVE WITH THE CONSEQUENCES OF ULTRA
PROCESSED FOODS. >> FOR FAR TOO LONG THESE
PRODUCTS HAVE SHAPED DIETS IN WAYS THAT FUEL CHRONIC
DISEASE AND PLACE THE HEAVIEST BURDENS ON WORKING FAMILIES,
LOW INCOME NEIGHBORHOODS AND COMMUNITIES OF COLOR.
WHEN AN INDUSTRY PRIORITIZES PROFIT OVER PUBLIC HEALTH, THE
GOVERNMENT HAS A RESPONSIBILITY TO STEP IN.
DEMAND TRANSPARENCY AND PROTECT RESIDENTS FROM PREVENTABLE HARM
. IF WE WANT A FOOD SYSTEM THAT
PUTS PEOPLE FIRST, WE HAVE TO START WITH OUR OWN HOUSE CITY
DEPARTMENTS SUPPORT FOOD DISTRIBUTION AND PROGRAMING
THAT PROVIDES FOOD EVERY SINGLE DAY AND SHELTERS, JAILS, YOUTH
PROGRAMS, LONG TERM CARE AND COMMUNITY BASED SERVICES.
THOUSANDS OF SAN FRANCISCANS RELY ON US FOR MEALS THAT
SHOULD PROMOTE HEALTH AND DIGNITY, NOT CONTRIBUTE TO
THE VERY CONDITIONS WE ARE TRYING TO ELIMINATE.
WE CANNOT CALL FOR ACCOUNTABILITY FROM
CORPORATIONS WHILE IGNORING THE IMPACT OF FOODS WE DISTRIBUTE.
>> ADDRESSING THIS HARM AT ITS SOURCE BEGINS WITH CITY
GOVERNMENT MODELING THE STANDARDS WE WANT TO SEE ACROSS
THE COUNTRY. >> THIS IS HOW WE ADVANCE
HEALTH EQUITY, PROTECT FAMILIES AND ENSURE SAN FRANCISCO IS
LEADING BY EXAMPLE. I WANT TO THANK CITY ATTORNEY
DAVID CHU AND HIS TEAM FOR HIS LEADERSHIP AND FOR TAKING BOLD
ACTION TO HOLD THIS INDUSTRY ACCOUNTABLE.
SAN FRANCISCO WILL NOT SIT BY WHILE CORPORATIONS PROFIT FROM
PRODUCTS THAT DECEPTIVELY HARM OUR RESIDENTS.
I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK MY LEGISLATIVE ANALOGY DEPUTY CITY
ATTORNEY JESSE LANER AND AM PEARSON FOR THEIR WORK ON
PUTTING THIS RESOLUTION TOGETHER.
THIS EFFORT CREATES THE FOUNDATION FOR STRONGER PUBLIC
HEALTH PROTECTIONS STATEWIDE AND IT REINFORCES WHY IT IS SO
IMPORTANT FOR THE CITY TO EXAMINE OUR OWN PRACTICES AS
WELL. I LOOK FORWARD TO PASSING THE
RESOLUTION AND TO TO BETTER BEHAVIOR FROM OUR CITY AS WELL.
I WANT TO THANK MY CURRENT CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISORS CHEN
MELGAR AND CHERYL FOR THEIR SUPPORT.
>> AND LAST I HAVE A LETTER OF INQUIRY FOR THE COMPTROLLER'S
OFFICE. YESTERDAY WE HEARD OUR
ORDINANCE TO ESTABLISH THE REPARATIONS FUND AT RULES
COMMITTEE. AS YOU KNOW THIS BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS COMMISSIONED A REPARATIONS COMMITTEE IN ORDER
TO EXPLORE THE INJUSTICES SUFFERED BY BLACK PEOPLE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND FOR THE COMMITTEE TO COME UP WITH CONCRETE
SOLUTIONS TO ADDRESS THE HARMS OF THE PAST.
THE COMMITTEE CAME UP WITH OVER 100 RECOMMENDATIONS THAT WILL
WORK TO ACHIEVE REPARATION FOR BLACK PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO
IF THEY MET THE SPECIFIC REQUIREMENT IDENTIFIED BY THE
COMMITTEE. TO THIS THE CITY ALSO PROVIDED
A FORMAL APOLOGY VIA RESOLUTION FROM THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
TO THE BLACK COMMUNITY HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THE RECOMMENDATIONS PROVIDED BY THE TASK FORCE ARE ONLY LIP
SERVICE IF WE DO NOT DO ANYTHING TO PROVIDE RESOURCES
TO ADDRESS THE PROPOSED RECOMMENDATIONS ALONG WITH THE
ORDINANCE TO ESTABLISH THE REPARATIONS FUND TO RECEIVE
MONEYS APPROPRIATED OR DONATED TO SUPPORT AND IMPLEMENT
RECOMMENDATIONS DESCRIBED IN THE SAN FRANCISCO
REPARATIONS PLAN. TODAY I AM FORMALLY REQUESTING
A LETTER OF INQUIRY FROM THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE
SPECIFICALLY THE BUDGET ANALYSTS IN THE COMPTROLLER'S
OFFICE TO FORECAST HOW MUCH MONEY COULD BE YIELDED FROM THE
REPARATIONS FUND YEARLY AND WHAT MECHANISMS DO WE NEED
IN PLACE TO FUND THAT ACCOUNT? >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON SUPERVISOR WONG.
SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SUPERVISOR CHEN. THANK YOU, MADAM COURT
COLLEAGUE. >> TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A
HEARING REQUESTS IN LIGHT OF THE ATROCIOUS ALLEGATIONS OF
SEXUAL MISCONDUCT COMMITTED AGAINST AT LEAST 20 WOMEN BEING
HELD IN SAN FRANCISCO JAIL. THIS WAS NOT AN ISOLATED EVENT
BUT THE CONTINUATION OF A PATTERN OF PERVASIVE BEHAVIOR
THAT HAS HISTORICALLY BEEN SWEPT UNDER THE RUG.
>> I WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR THIS WOMAN AND ANY OTHER WHO HAVE
BEEN VICTIMIZED OR ABUSE WHY IN OUR JAILS ARE OWE TO
JUSTICE. IT IS OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO USE
OUR POWER TO FORCE THESE ISSUES TO LIGHT.
>> I'M CALLING A HEARING THAT WILL ENABLE US TO EXAMINE TWO
CONDITIONS FOR WOMEN IN CUSTODY OF OUR JAILS INCLUDING
SAFEGUARDS FOR THEIR PERSONAL SAFETY AND SERVICES OR
RESOURCES THAT ARE PROVIDED TO THEM.
I WILL ALSO BE ASKING WHAT OVERSIGHT POLICIES
AND PROCEDURES HAVE BEEN IMPLEMENTED BY THE SHERIFF'S
DEPARTMENT TO PREVENT REPORT OR ADDRESS ALLEGATIONS OF SEXUAL
MISCONDUCT. EXAMINE THE HIRING
AND ASSIGNMENTS PROCESS FOR JAIL STAFFING THE COMPLAINT
PROCESS FOR WOMEN IN CUSTODY AND THE DISCIPLINARY PROCESS
FOR DEPUTIES WHO COMMIT MISCONDUCT.
I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR WALTON CHEN MALKA AND FILNER
FOR THEIR EARLY CO-SPONSORSHIP AND THEIR ASSESSMENT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN, SUPERVISOR
DORSEY THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> THAT CONCLUDES THE ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS.
ALL RIGHT. >> LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT.
PLEASE LINE UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
AS A REMINDER ITEMS 36 THROUGH 30 EIGHT REGARDING THE FAMILY
ZONING PLAN HAVE ALREADY HAD THEIR PUBLIC COMMENT
OPPORTUNITY SO YOU ARE NOT ABLE TO COMMENT ON THOSE TODAY.
>> YOU MAY SPEAK ON ITEMS 43 THROUGH 47 ON THE FLOOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA AND GENERAL
MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA BUT ARE WITHIN
THE BOARD SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT WILL HAVE BEEN REPORTED TO THE BOARD
BY AN APPROPRIATE COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT
REQUIREMENT OCCURRED. >> FIRST SPEAKER YES.
OKAY. SO BEFORE I FORGET ABOUT THE
LIES BEHIND THE REASONS YOU GAVE CONCERNING THE FAMILY
PLANNING PLANS, UNDERSTANDING FAMILY ZONING AND PLANNING
GENERALLY SPEAKING IS IN THE HANDS OF SPECIFICALLY AND NOT
ONLY BUT CHILD TRAFFICKING FROM THE STATES COUNTRY THE ONTARIO
GOVERNMENTS NOT ONLY IN THE US .
OKAY SO I'M GOING TO GIVE THIS TO YOU IF YOU DON'T WANT IT
IT'S FINE. >> I KNOW I WILL HAVE I'VE
GIVEN IT TO YOU SO IT MEANS IF YOU DON'T PAY ATTENTION ENOUGH
CONSIDERING IT'S NOT IMPORTANT ENOUGH MAYBE FOR YOU YOU ARE.
>> WE KNOW WHAT TO THINK. OKAY.
FOR ANYONE OF YOU LISTENERS HERE YOU GOT THIS IN THE
MAILBOX ALREADY BUT 3000 WERE DISTRIBUTED ALREADY IN THE CITY
THROUGHOUT. NOW IT'S GOING TO GO IN THE
BUSINESSES AND STEP BY STEP JUST KNOW YOU ARE NOT ISOLATED
YOUR NEIGHBORS AS ONE TO YOU SEE SO YOU CAN ACT EVEN THOUGH
THE SUBJECT IS EXTREMELY SENSITIVE AND AND BIGGER AND I
AGREE EXTREMELY DISTURBING. >> MORE DISTURBING IT'S CALLED
IMPOSSIBLE CHILD TRAFFICKING INSTEAD PERSONALIZED CHILD
TRAFFICKING, MURDERING, TORTURING.
>> I MEAN YOU NAME IT, IT'S THERE.
>> SO THAT'S IT FOR FIVE SECONDS.
>> YES, I WAS GOOD. WHAT IS.
>> YOU DON'T WANT TO TAKE A STAND.
IT'S GOING TO GO IN ALL POLICE STATIONS TO FIRE DEPARTMENTS,
OLIVER. >> I MEAN IT'S ALREADY ABOUT
SEVEN THOUSANDS TO BE GIVEN. IF PEOPLE DON'T ACT, IT'S FINE
. >> MY MISSION IS OWN WOULD HAVE
NOTHING TO REPROACH MYSELF. I'M PROTECTING THE KIDS.
IT'S THE ONLY WAY YOU CAN STOP THE MESS YOU PUT YOURSELF IN.
>> ONCE YOU ADDRESS THIS, THIS IS GAME OVER FOR THE ONTARIO
SYSTEM. ABSOLUTELY UGLY SYSTEM.
WORSE YOU DIE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER YOU ARE ONE FOR YOU.
HAVE A GOOD NIGHT. >> I'M PETER WARFIELD,
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR LIBRARY USERS AND ASSOCIATION.
WE CAN BE REACHED AT P.O. BOX 170544 SAN FRANCISCO,
CALIFORNIA 94117-0544. >> THERE'S A MOVIE CALLED THE
LIBRARIANS THAT IS GOING TO BE PLAYING THIS WEEK STARTING THIS
WEEK DECEMBER 4TH AT THE ROXY. THE MAKERS WERE ON THE RADIO
THIS MORNING K L W TALKING ABOUT HOW IT'S DOCUMENTING THE
ATTACKS THAT LIBRARIANS ARE GETTING WITH REGARD TO THE
CONTENTS OF THEIR COLLECTIONS AND DEMANDS FOR THEIR REMOVAL
WHICH IS IN SUCH A DEMAND THAT SO UNORGANIZED AND I THINK IT'S
VERY IMPORTANT TO SUPPORT OUR LIBRARIES AS AN INDEPENDENT
AND VERY VALUABLE SOURCE FOR ENTERTAINMENT AND EDUCATION
ESPECIALLY ABOUT WHAT'S GOING ON IN OUR SOCIETY.
UNFORTUNATELY OUR LIBRARY IN SAN FRANCISCO ISN'T WE'RE
NOT AWARE OF REQUESTS OR DEMANDS TO REMOVE BOOKS BUT WE
HAVE HAD THE LIBRARY EXCLUDING SERVICES TO CERTAIN PEOPLE
AND WE HAVE HAD THE LIBRARY BE VERY, VERY UNCRITICALLY PRO
TECH ALMOST AS A RECRUITER FOR TECH.
THEY'RE CONSTANTLY PUTTING MORE AND MORE PROGRAMS ON TECH MORE
AND MORE MATERIALS ELECTRONICALLY WHERE THOSE WHO
DON'T HAVE THE ACCESS DON'T HAVE ANY OPPORTUNITY TO GET AT
THE MATERIALS AND SO ON. >> ONE CITY, ONE BOOK IS IS
PROMOTING THE WORLDS I SEE BY DR. FAY FAY LEE NOT BAD FOR A
MEMOIR BUT IT'S VERY, VERY THIN ON DOWNSIDES OF OF A.I. AND OF
TECH. THERE IS NO READING
MATERIAL THAT'S SERIOUSLY VISIBLY OPPOSED TO A.I. AND IN
GENERAL TO THE DOWNSIDES OF TECH.
THIS IS A BOOK AS AN EXAMPLE THE AGE OF EXTRACTION TIM WU
NOT ON THE LIST OF READING MATERIAL THE TECH WHO NOT ON
THE LIST ONCE. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> NEXT SPEAKER I HAVE SOMEONE
COME PASS THESE OUT. >> OKAY.
>> YOU KNOW SAN FRANCISCO LOVES I AND SOMEONE I KNOW CREATED
THIS REPORT USING AI SO I HOPE YOU ENJOY IT.
>> PLEASE LET ME KNOW IF THERE IS ANY YOU KNOW AN UNTRUE STUFF
AS WE KNOW AI MAKES FACTUAL ERRORS SO I DON'T KNOW HOW YOU
FEEL ABOUT THE SANCTITY OF YOUR HOME BEING ALLOWED TO CONTROL
WHO ENTERS YOUR HOME. >> FOR MANY PEOPLE ESPECIALLY
BIPOC LGBTQ PLUS PEOPLE YOUR HOME IS LITERALLY YOUR ONLY
SANCTUARY FROM SOCIETY. MY HOME IS IN A BUILDING
COMPLEX AND THE FRONT DOORS TO THE LOBBY ARE WHERE I CONTROL
TO ALLOW ACCESS INCLUDING ACCESS TO THE GOVERNMENT
IN GENERAL. >> THEY NEED A WARRANT FOR ME
TO FORCE THEIR WAY PAST THOSE TWO DOORS AND MANY TIMES THOSE
DOORS HAVE BEEN THE ONLY SAFETY I GET FROM MEN STALKING MY WIFE
AND MYSELF DOWN MARKET STREETS REPEATEDLY BECAUSE IF YOU'RE A
LESBIAN OR TRANS OR TRANS LESBIANS GUESS WHAT THAT'S A
PART OF EVERYDAY LIFE BEING STALKED BY MEN.
>> SCARY STUFF. SO YOU KNOW THROUGH NO FAULT OF
THE BOARD OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, THIS ONE HERE WHO
REPRESENTS ME WILL BE ENTERING MY BUILDING WITHOUT MY
PERSONNEL CONSENTS. BUT THESE ARE DECISIONS MADE
BEYOND MY CONTROL. >> I AM JUST HERE TO EXPRESS
MYSELF AS A RESIDENT TO SAN FRANCISCO, A HOMEOWNER OF SAN
FRANCISCO WHO PAYS A LOT OF MONEY FOR THAT ONE LITTLE PIECE
OF SANCTUARY EXPRESSING MY DISPLEASURE AT HAVING MY
GOVERNMENT AND ALSO AN ELECTED SFO TRIPLE C PERSON ENTER MY
SANCTUARY AGAINST MY WILL AND THAT'S ALL I REALLY HAVE TO
SAY ABOUT THAT. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> BOARD OF SUPERVISOR
AND OFFICE MAYOR OF SAN FRANCISCO THE TITLE OF THIS
SPEECH IS GRAB THE BATON. A WEEK AND A HALF AGO I HEARD
ONE OF THE BOARD MEMBERS RUNNING FOR CONGRESS FOR NANCY
PELOSI SPEAKER OF THE HOUSE. I'M HERE TO OFFER UNWAVERING
SUPPORT FOR THIS PARTICULAR BOARD MEMBER BEING FOUR YEARS
AND SIX FLAGS AND A PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICER SIX FLAGS.
I DO TAKE CARE OF THE ALLIGATORS.
SO I MET CLAUDE AND ALSO MET JOHN GOOD WHO WAS STARTING 51ST
STATE BY ADAM SANDLER. SO THIS IS MY SPIEL ON THE
BUCKS BY ANY STAGE. ALL RIGHT, LADIES MANDELMAN,
GOOD AFTERNOON. WELCOME TO THE UNITED STATES OF
TODAY. THREE OF THE FINEST ARE
COMPETING FOR THE TITLE BEST CHANCE TO EACH ONE WHICH WAS A
PARTNER. THEY COME AND SING A SONG AS
CHOICE. WELL, FOLKS, LET'S PICK THEM
OUT HERE. A CONSENSUS.
THE FIRST IS A BUNNY WE LEARN TO LOVE BUGS BUNNY AND BEING
THE LOVER OF LYRICS I HAVE TO SAY THIS CAGE ONLY AGO SAID IT
LONG AGO CAUSING A LOUD ECHO COURT CANTINA.
HEY ACTUALLY TALKING ABOUT THE GOTTI I'M A FAN HERE YOKO
CHEER TO ME LAST NIGHT UNLV'S WIN SUPPORT BEING THE 48TH
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES FOR THE WELL-BEING OF THE
UNITED STATES, THE WORLD AND INTERPLANETARY SPECIES FOR
DARK NO PARTICLE THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER HI, GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD OF COMMITTEE. MY NAME IS PEREZ BROWN.
I AM ENTREPRENEUR AND WE ALL KNOW THAT THE SUPER BOWL IS
COMING HERE AND SO WITH THE SUPER BOWL COMING HERE I HAVE
DESIGNED A PRODUCT THAT WILL BE A BENEFIT FOR THE GUESTS THAT
ARE COMING HERE AND WE ALL KNOW ABOUT YOUR SCAN CODES AND WITH
THE QR SCAN CODES THEY ARE, YOU KNOW, BASIC AND GENERIC BUT I
CREATE IT IN DESIGN THIS QR CODE AND IT CAN BE BENEFICIAL
FOR FOR TRAFFICKING I FAR FOR TRANSPORTATION AS FAR AS FOR
GUEST SCANNING FOR INFORMATION AND I CAN CONTRIBUTE TO THIS
NEW FORM OF QR SCAN CODE SO IT WILL BE ONE OF A KIND FOR BUILT
FROM SILICON VALLEY RESIDENT AND THIS WILL BE THE UPDATE
MODEL OF USING QR SCAN CODES AND SO I THINK THIS WILL BE A
GREAT OPPORTUNITY TO SHOWCASE AND ADVERTISE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO WHEN GUESTS COME THEY KNOW HOW TO GO AN INTERNET SCAN
IS WE CAN ADVERTISE THIS AROUND THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND PEOPLE WITH THIS SCANNERS AND GET DIRECT INFORMATION
ABOUT LOCATION HOW TO GET AROUND TO DIFFERENT HOTELS
AND HAVING THIS AT THE AIRPORT AS WELL AND SO IF YOU WANTED TO
KNOW MORE BECAUSE THIS IS MY PRODUCT AND I AM LOOKING FOR AN
INVESTOR BECAUSE I DON'T HAVE AN INVESTOR AT THIS POINT
BECAUSE THEN I CAN USE THEIR MONEY TO BUILD OUT MY TEAM THAT
CAN HELP CONTRIBUTE TO PUSHING THIS OUT ON A LOCAL PUTS US OUT
TO THE PUBLIC. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> NEXT SPEAKER I'D LIKE TO
GIVE GIFTS FOR HER LIKE A FALCON UP TO THE SKY HIGH SO
LIKE A FALCON TO THE HEAVENS. HI.
HI. HI.
HI. HAVE THE ANTICIPATION OF THE
FALCON AND THE PRIDE OF THE LEOPARD AND THE TIMES OF THE
HUNT BE GRACEFUL AND THE TIMES OF WAR VICTORIOUS DON'T PAY TOO
MUCH HEED TO THE NIGHTINGALE OR THE PEACOCK ONE IS ALL TALK THE
OTHER ALL COLOR. YOU CAN FLY.
YOU CAN FLY. YOU CAN FLY I'M TORTURED.
>> I'VE BEEN TORTURED TRAUMATIZED MISS WITHOUT
HOUSING, WITHOUT A PLACE TO HEAL FROM THE VIC WITH BEING A
VICTIM OF VIOLENCE NOT HELP FROM THE VICTIMS OF VIOLENCE
COMMITTEE NOT HELPED BY ANYBODY JUST STRUGGLING AS A WOMAN.
YES THERE ARE SEXIST HATE CRIMES.
YES THERE ARE JUST HATE CRIMES. >> YES THERE ARE XENOPHOBIC ARE
RACIST AT THE UNION AND THERE IN THE COURTS THEY ARE IN THE
SECURITY SYSTEM. THEY ARE IN THE HOUSING.
>> WHEN YOU GAVE THE EPISCOPAL BILLS FOR A DOLLAR THE HOUSING
AT 1066 AND 1064 THEY CAN'T HEAT IT HEAT THE TUB.
>> IT'S A FLIP THE SWITCH TURN IT UP HIGHER.
>> THEY CAN'T GIVE YOU AIR. AND THEN THE PARK THE YERBA
BUENA PARK WHERE IT'S JUST UNBELIEVABLE WITH THE MARINA
SECURITY JUST CANNOT DO THINGS RIGHT.
YOU ARE AN ENEMY IF YOU ARE AN EXCEPTIONAL HUMAN BEING WHO
WANTS TO HEAL AND BE THERE TO HEAL BUT INSTEAD YOU ARE ABUSED
ABUSED BECAUSE THE SECURITY MAKES THE RULES THAT YOU ARE
SUPPOSED THAT THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO ENFORCE.
>> THAT DOESN'T HAPPEN. WHAT THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. >> I SEE NO OTHER SPEAKERS, MR.
PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR FOR
ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 43
THROUGH 47 ITEMS 43 THROUGH 47 WE'RE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY, A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM IN SENDING ITEM 47 TO COMMITTEE OKAY SUPERVISOR
CHIN SEVER ITEM 44 OKAY AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER I WOULD
JUST LIKE TO BE ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR TO 43 PLEASE.
>> OKAY. >> SO WITH THAT MADAM CLERK
COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON ALL THE ITEMS EXCEPT 44 AND 47 YES
ON ITEMS 4345 AND 46 SUPERVISOR FIELDER FILTER I SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD MAHMUD I SUPERVISOR BENJAMIN I MEANT THEM AND I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN I CAN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE LEBANESE WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THE MOTIONS ARE APPROVED AND MADAM CLERK PLEASE
CALL ITEM 44. ITEM NUMBER 44 IS A RESOLUTION
TO SUPPORT THE PASSAGE OF THE STOP BALLROOM BRIBERY ACT TO
ROOT OUT PAY TO PLAY BY IMPOSING DONATION RESTRICTIONS
TO PROJECTS INVOLVING PUBLIC PROPERTY AND CALLING ON LOCAL
DONORS TO RETURN THEIR DONATIONS.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMANDO MY COLLEAGUES
AS ELECTED OFFICIALS WE KNOW HOW IMPORTANT IT IS FOR US TO
HAVE A GOOD GOVERNMENT THAT EARNS AND BUILDS PUBLIC TRUST
WHEN WE ALLOW THE CULTURE OF PAY TO PLAY, WE ALLOW
GOVERNMENT CORRUPTION TO FESTER AND AS A RESULT WORKING PEOPLE
CANNOT DEPEND ON OUR GOVERNMENT TO DELIVER CRITICAL AND HONEST
SERVICES AND PEOPLE SUFFER SENATES BILL 3191 AND HOUSE
BILL 6085 COLLECTIVELY CALL TO STOP BALRAM BRIBERY ACT ARE
IN DIRECT RESPONSE TO THE DONATION BEING COLLECTED YOU
KNOW OUR OPINION AS A BY BRIBERY TO PAY FOR PRESIDENT
TRUMP'S BALLROOM RENOVATION AND EXPANSION WHILE AMERICAN
PEOPLE ARE FACING CUTS TO HEALTH CARE AND FOOT NUTRITION
PROGRAMS AND ELIMINATION OF MANY CRITICAL SERVICES IS FOR
THE MOST VULNERABLE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ACROSS THE NATION
TO STOP BAR ON BRIBERY ACT IS THE FIRST STEP TO IMPOSE
RESTRICTIONS AND LIMITATIONS TO PRIVATE DONATION TO REQUIRE
TRANSPARENCY AND TO ENABLE ENFORCEMENT MEASURES.
THE STOP BY BALLROOM BRIBERY ACT ALSO SERVES AS A REMINDER
FOR ALL OF US AS OUR CITY CONTINUE TO SEEK PRIVATE
DONATION TO SUPPORT OUR PUBLIC PROGRAMS, ROOTING OUT PAY TO
PLAY OPPORTUNITIES AND SETTING REGULATIONS TO PREVENT
IMPROPRIETY IS IMPORTANT AT ALL LEVELS OF GOVERNMENT AND THIS
BILL IS A GOOD FIRST STEP FOR THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
BUT WE KNOW MORE NEEDS TO BE DONE NOT JUST FOR THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT BUT IN SAN FRANCISCO AS WELL.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS?
>> WE DO NOT HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS TODAY.
COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM US?
YES ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDOLIN FOR THE LATE MRS. O.
TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
FOR THE LATE MRS. WITH HONOR SAPP ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR
MELGAR FOR THE LATE CLAUDE THE ALBINO ALLIGATOR AND I BELIEVE
THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA.
MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US
TODAY? THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR
TODAY. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK
AND COLLEAGUES. >> WE ARE ADJOURNED